<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Moneycle</title>
    <description>Don your money monocle (top hats are optional) as we explore topics related to money, investing and early retirement.
</description>
    <link>http://www.moneycle.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.moneycle.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2015 12:05:14 -0600</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2015 12:05:14 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Safe Withdrawal Rates for Vampires</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If you search the web for retirement withdrawal strategies,
you can find countless articles about how to withdraw your fund within the
construct of a 30-year retirement.  The most commonly cited strategy is the 4%
withdrawal strategy which starts withdrawing 4% of the initial portfolio value
and increases spending each year by the rate of inflation.
Using monte carlo analysis techniques, such a portfolio
may be found to have some small probability of exhausting the portfolio before
30 years have passed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if you’re a Vampire named Vlad and want your assets to last forever, you can’t
afford to have your portfolio run dry in 30 years or even 100 years.
Or maybe you aren’t not a vampire but are retiring early and want your funds to last
50 years, which seems like forever.
Let’s explore the idea of withdrawing funds from a portfolio indefinitely
to try to gain some insights into long-term safe withdrawal rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-vampire-strategy&quot;&gt;The Vampire Strategy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way Vlad can ensure that he never runs out of money is to just withdraw a fixed
percentage from the portfolio every year.  But Vlad doesn’t want his spending power
to decrease each year, so he needs to be careful with how much he spends.  In other
words, he wants his portfolio on average to grow by the rate of inflation while at
the same time withdrawing some amount of money to live on.  In equation form:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
(portfolio-withdrawal)(1+appreciation) &amp;gt;= portfolio(1+inflation)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This equation says that the portfolio in a given year will appreciate by at
least the rate of inflation after subtracting the withdrawal amount.
Let’s use shorter variable names to help make it more readable&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
(P - W)(1 + r) &amp;gt;= P(1 + i)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;P = portfolio value&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;W = withdrawal amount&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;w = withdrawal rate = W/P&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;r = porfolio appreciation&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;i = inflation rate&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Replacing withdrawal amount with &lt;code&gt;W = Pw&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we can divide both sides of the equation by the &lt;code&gt;P&lt;/code&gt; we get:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
(1 - w)(1 + r) &amp;gt;= (1 + i)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now it’s fairly simple to solve the &lt;code&gt;withdrawal rate&lt;/code&gt; as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
w &amp;lt;= (r - i) / (1 + r)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice that the numerator is the difference between Vlad’s portfolio return
and long-term inflation.  So if his portfolio appreciates at a rate less than
inflation, he’ll have to work forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stocks-only&quot;&gt;Stocks Only&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s see what happens if we assume Vlad invests everything in stocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moneychimp has an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.moneychimp.com/features/market_cagr.htm&quot;&gt;excellent tool&lt;/a&gt;
for getting historical stock returns.
With this tool you can see that for the past 100 years (1915-2014) stocks have
returned a compounded average rate of 10.31%.
If Vlad could invest in Vanguard Total Stock Market ETF (VTI),
he would incur a fee of 0.05% for a total return of 10.26%.  To be a little
conservative, let’s round that down to 10.2%.
Moneychimp also has an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.moneychimp.com/articles/econ/inflation_calculator.htm&quot;&gt;inflation calculator&lt;/a&gt;
which shows a historical inflation rate of 3.2% over the same time period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plugging those numbers into the above equations gives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
withdrawal rate &amp;lt;= 6.35%
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, with average stock returns and average inflation values, a withdrawal of 6.35%
or less could allow Vlad to keep up with inflation.  Keep in mind that average
returns are not realistic.  In fact, those average returns have a standard deviation
of 19.9% so if Vlad just used a 100% stock portfolio, he would have about a 95%
chance that his portfolio would return between -30% and +50%.  A 30% loss would
be a big hit to his annual income so Vlad probably wants to consider ways to smooth
out the market swings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stocks-and-bonds&quot;&gt;Stocks and Bonds&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to reduced volatility to a portfolio is by adding bonds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Historical bond rates are harder to come by but over period of 1926-2014
bonds have returned approximately 5.4% with a standard deviation of 5.6%&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:11&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:11&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.
So if Vlad invests his bond portfolio in Vanguard Total Bond Market ETF (BND)
with an expense ratio of 0.07%, let’s assume he gets a return of 5.3% on the bonds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following table shows the maximum withdrawal rates for different portfolio
allocations based on the returns estimated for each allocation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Stocks/Bonds =&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;20/80&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;40/60&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;60/40&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;80/20&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Historical Portfolio Return&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6.6%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7.3%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8.2%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;9.2%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Spending Standard Deviation&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;11%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;15%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Maximum Withdrawal Rate&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2.9%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3.8%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4.7%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5.5%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Expense Multiplier&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;35&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;27&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;22&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;18&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “Expense Multiplier” value represents the amount of money that Vlad needs
to save before he begins his retirement in terms of his annual expenses.
So for a moderate 60/40 portfolio, Vlad would need to save at least 22 times his
annual expenses before he could retire from his night job, and he could withdraw
up to 4.7% to keep up with inflation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;buffer-the-vampire-strategy22&quot;&gt;Buffer the Vampire Strategy&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:22&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:22&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even with the moderate 60/40 portfolio, Vlad has a decent chance that his portfolio
(and spending) could drop by 14%&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; in any given year.&lt;br /&gt;
One way he could reduce the volatility of his expenses even further is to allocate
a portion of his portfolio to a spending buffer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To describe how a spending buffer works, consider a 5-year spending buffer
as an example.  With a 5-year buffer, Vlad would carve out 4 times his annual
expenses as part of his portfolio.  Since this represents the next 4 years of
his spending, it would be invested conservatively in short-term bond and cash
equivalents.  At the end of each year, Vlad applies his withdrawal rate to his
entire portfolio then moves that amount into his spending buffer (now the buffer
has 5 years worth of spending).  He then withdraws 1/5th of the spending buffer
for spending in the following year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;pieWithBuffer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;stock-slider&quot; style=&quot;width: 300px;&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a 5-year buffer for his spending means that Vlad’s spending will only be
impacted by 1/5th of the fluctuations in the market.  The standard deviation of
Vlad’s spending will be reduced&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; by approximately &lt;code&gt;1/sqrt(5)&lt;/code&gt;.
In our example with a 60/40 split, the standard deviation goes from 11% down to 5%.
Vampires get grumpy with big swings in spending so this helps to prevent Vlad
from biting people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One possible downside of the buffering is that the returns from Vlad’s portfolio
would be slightly reduced.  Assuming that the buffer piece is allocated to the
bond side of the portfolio, then the bond returns would be reduced if the buffer
is allocated to cash or cash equivalents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Re-working the original equations with a spending buffer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
(P - kW)(1 + r) + kW - W &amp;gt;= P(1 + i)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where &lt;code&gt;k = spending buffer size in years&lt;/code&gt;.  In this equation &lt;code&gt;P-kW&lt;/code&gt; represents
the piece of the portfolio that is invested and &lt;code&gt;kW-W&lt;/code&gt; represents the buffer after
1 year’s worth of spending has been withdrawn.  In short, we want the appreciation
from the invested part of the portfolio to be enough so that the &lt;strong&gt;entire&lt;/strong&gt;
portfolio keeps up with inflation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solving this equation for withdrawal rate,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
w &amp;lt;= (r - i) / (1 + kr)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking this a little further, if Vlad wants to keep the stock portion of the
portfolio fixed at some percentage while bonds and the buffer make up the remainder,
then the rate of return could be written in terms of this percentage,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
r = p*r_s + (1 - p)*r_b - (k - 1)*w*r_b
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;x = percentage of portfolio in stocks&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;r_s = rate of return on stocks&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;r_b = rate of return on bonds&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first 2 terms of this equation represent the return we would have had without
buffering and the last term represents the amount of potential returns lost to
the buffering (assuming it would have been invested in bonds).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Substituting &lt;code&gt;r&lt;/code&gt; from the last equation into the equation before that gives us
a quadratic equation to solve for withdrawal rate (I may expand this
in another article but will leave this detail out for now).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this math probably is putting you to sleep so let’s look at some portfolios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Stocks/Bonds&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;/Buffer&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; =&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;20/72/8&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;40/50/10&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;60/27/13&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;80/5/15&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Historical Portfolio Return&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5.9%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6.7%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7.6%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8.4%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Spending Standard Deviation&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3.5%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Maximum Withdrawal Rate&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2.0%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2.6%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3.2%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3.7%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Expense Multiplier&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;50&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;38&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;31&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;27&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if our friend Vlad has a portfolio with 60% in stocks and transfers 3.2%
of his portfolio to his 5-year spending buffer every year, his portfolio should roughly
keep pace with inflation.  The buffer needed for this withdrawal would account for
about 13% of his overall portfolio initially and would fluctuate with the market.
And the reduced variations in his income due to the buffering should help Vlad
sleep during the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;caveats&quot;&gt;Caveats&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this article explores the safe withdrawal rates for a portfolio that follows
historical returns, this is known to not be a good strategy for determining actual
safe withdrawal rates.  This is really more of a thought experiment to think about
long-term withdrawals combined with the spending buffer concept in order to reduce
income volatility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably a better way to complete this analysis would be to do a monte-carlo simulation
with an appropriate success criterion.  For example, most studies of 30-year withdrawal
rates consider how a withdrawal performs relative to how often the portfolio drops to
zero during the 30-year period.  For a vampire, the measure of success would probably
be whether the portfolio has kept pace with inflation over 50 years (or more).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;insights&quot;&gt;Insights&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of it’s weaknesses, this analysis does shed some light on very-long-term
withdrawals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For an aggressively allocated (80% stock) 5-year buffered portfolio, the
withdrawal rate of 3.7% could keep up with inflation. This rate isn’t too
far off from the widely discussed 4% rates you see in the financial press but it
is for a pretty aggressive allocation.  Reducing stock allocation quickly reduces the “safe”
withdrawal rate.  A much safer 40% allocation requires reducing the withdrawal rate all
the way down to 2.6%.  This highlights the need to
stay invested in higher-performing assets in order to keep up with long-term inflation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The buffered withdrawal strategy could be employed to cushion the ups and down of the
markets.  One cost of a buffered strategy is that it will reduce overall returns
by about 0.6% for moderate allocations.
But that lost return could be recouped by increasing the stock allocation by about 10%.
The 5-year buffer suggested here has a good chance of spanning at least 1 or 2 good
years even over the course of a bear market.  Over all 5-year periods stock returns
have been &lt;a href=&quot;http://awealthofcommonsense.com/u-s-stock-investors-doomed-high-returns/&quot;&gt;positive about 87% of the time&lt;/a&gt;.
This suggests that 87% of the time the 5-year buffered income would continue to increase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another cost of buffering is that it reduces the withdrawal rate that can keep
up with inflation.  So the ultimate balance is between stability and income.
If you want more income, you &lt;strong&gt;could&lt;/strong&gt; reduce the buffer size and take a higher
amount of income with full understanding that you should see larger swings in the market.
You could also do away with buffering and reduce the volatility by choosing a less
risky allocation.  Over the very long term it seems like Vlad would do better by
keeping his portfolio as heavily invested as is bearable and using buffering to
reduce the volatility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a vampire who wants to implement a Roth ladder strategy, you might
want to consider a 6-year buffer. This would allow you convert your traditional IRA
to a Roth IRA and wait the required 5 years before withdrawing the money without
penalty&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  But 6-years is a long time to not keep money invested so with such
a large buffer it might make sense to invest 1 or 2 years of a bigger buffer into
a bond fund.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;next-steps&quot;&gt;Next Steps&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there’s any interest, the next logical step for this analysis would be to
take it to the domain of monte-carlo simulations to see how the estimated rates
do over very long periods with the given portfolios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interesting variation of this analysis would be to include the effects
of social security on withdrawal rates.  Future social security or
pension earnings will probably allow for increased withdrawals until that income
stream kicks in.  It would be interesting to see how much of an effect that is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
var pieData = [
  {
    &quot;label&quot;: &quot;Buffer&quot;,
    &quot;value&quot;: 13,
    &quot;color&quot;: &quot;#387e45&quot;,
    &quot;caption&quot;: &quot;{percentage}%, withdrawal = 3.2%&quot;
  },
  {
    &quot;label&quot;: &quot;Bonds&quot;,
    &quot;value&quot;: 27,
    &quot;color&quot;: &quot;#386a7e&quot;,
    &quot;caption&quot;: &quot;{percentage}%&quot;
  },
  {
    &quot;label&quot;: &quot;Stocks&quot;,
    &quot;value&quot;: 60,
    &quot;color&quot;: &quot;#7e3838&quot;,
    &quot;caption&quot;: &quot;{percentage}%&quot;
  }
];
stockReturn = 0.102;
bondReturn = 0.053;
inflationRate = 0.032;
bufferSize = 5;

updateData = function(stockPercent) {
    var stock = stockPercent * 0.01
  var bufferlessReturn = stock*stockReturn + (1-stock)*bondReturn;
  var a = bufferSize*(bufferSize-1)*bondReturn;
  var b = 1+(bufferSize-1)*bondReturn+bufferSize*bufferlessReturn;
  var c = bufferlessReturn - inflationRate;
  var withdrawalRate = (b-Math.sqrt(b*b-4*a*c))/(2*a);
  var bufferPercent = (bufferSize-1)*withdrawalRate*100;
  var bondPercent = 100-stockPercent-bufferPercent;

  pieData[0].value = bufferPercent;
  pieData[0].caption = &quot;{percentage}%, withdrawal = &quot; + Math.round(withdrawalRate*1000)/10 + &quot;%&quot;
  pieData[1].value = bondPercent;
  pieData[2].value = stockPercent;
}
updateData(55);

var pie = new d3pie(&quot;pieWithBuffer&quot;, {
	&quot;header&quot;: {
		&quot;title&quot;: {
			&quot;text&quot;:     &quot;Portfolio Allocation with a Spending Buffer&quot;,
			&quot;fontSize&quot;: 22
		},
    subtitle: {
      text:     &quot;5-year buffer, 10.2% stock returns, 5.3% bond returns&quot;,
      color:    &quot;#666666&quot;,
      fontSize: 14,
    }
	},
  footer: {
    text: 	  &quot;use slider to change stock allocation&quot;,
    color:    &quot;#666666&quot;,
    fontSize: 10,
    location: &quot;bottom-center&quot;
  },
	&quot;size&quot;: {
		&quot;canvasHeight&quot;: 400,
		&quot;canvasWidth&quot;: 420,
		&quot;pieOuterRadius&quot;: &quot;88%&quot;
	},
	&quot;data&quot;: {
		&quot;content&quot;: pieData
	},
	&quot;labels&quot;: {
		&quot;outer&quot;: {
			&quot;format&quot;: &quot;none&quot;,
			&quot;pieDistance&quot;: 32
		},
		&quot;inner&quot;: {
			&quot;format&quot;: &quot;label&quot;
		},
		&quot;mainLabel&quot;: {
			&quot;color&quot;: &quot;#e1e1e1&quot;,
			&quot;font&quot;: &quot;verdana&quot;,
			&quot;fontSize&quot;: 12
		},
		&quot;percentage&quot;: {
			&quot;color&quot;: &quot;#e1e1e1&quot;,
			&quot;font&quot;: &quot;verdana&quot;,
			&quot;decimalPlaces&quot;: 0
		},
		&quot;value&quot;: {
			&quot;color&quot;: &quot;#e1e1e1&quot;,
			&quot;font&quot;: &quot;verdana&quot;
		},
		&quot;lines&quot;: {
			&quot;enabled&quot;: true,
			&quot;color&quot;: &quot;#cccccc&quot;
		},
		&quot;truncation&quot;: {
			&quot;enabled&quot;: true
		}
	},
	&quot;tooltips&quot;: {
		&quot;enabled&quot;: true,
		&quot;type&quot;: &quot;caption&quot;,
		&quot;string&quot;: &quot;{label}: {percentage}%&quot;
	},
	&quot;effects&quot;: {
		&quot;pullOutSegmentOnClick&quot;: {
			&quot;effect&quot;: &quot;linear&quot;,
			&quot;speed&quot;: 200,
			&quot;size&quot;: 12
		}
	},
	&quot;callbacks&quot;: {
    &quot;onload&quot;: function() { pie.openSegment(0); },
		&quot;onMouseoverSegment&quot;: null,
		&quot;onMouseoutSegment&quot;: null,
		&quot;onClickSegment&quot;: null
	}
});

d3.select(&#39;#stock-slider&#39;).call(d3.slider().axis(true).min(0).max(85).step(5).value(pieData[2].value).on(&quot;slideend&quot;, function(evt, stockPercent) {
  updateData(stockPercent);
  pie.updateProp(&quot;data.content&quot;, pieData);
}));
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:11&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Bond Performance - 1926-2014: 5.4%, std dev = 5.6%, comes from a combination of &lt;a href=&quot;https://personal.vanguard.com/us/insights/saving-investing/model-portfolio-allocations&quot;&gt;Vanguard data&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jvlassociates.com/files/Performance%20Probabilities%20(Bell%20Curve%20)%20%201926%20-%202014.pdf&quot;&gt;comparable intermediate govt bond&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:11&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Portfolio return for mixed portfolios are crude approximations for illustrative purposes only. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Standard deviations for different allocations estimated from graph on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.forbes.com/sites/rickferri/2015/02/06/the-center-of-gravity-for-retirees/2/&quot;&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:22&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;No relation to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buffy_the_Vampire_Slayer&quot;&gt;Buffy the Vampire Slayer&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:22&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;14% drop is 2 standard deviations, or 22%, below average return of 8.2% &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Standard_error#Standard_error_of_the_mean&quot;&gt;standard error of the mean&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Bonds and buffer percentages are initial values, buffer size varies slightly after the first year. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Based on portfolio deviation divided by sqrt(5) for the buffering effect. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I’m pretty sure vampires are not subject to the rules concerning age of 59.5 and withdrawals. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 29 May 2015 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        
          <link>http://www.moneycle.com/safe-withdrawal-rates-for-vampires/</link>
        
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.moneycle.com/safe-withdrawal-rates-for-vampires/</guid>
        
        <category>investing</category>
        
        <category>spending</category>
        
        <category>other</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Maximize Your Employer Match before Using a Roth 401(k)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;While the Roth 401(k) is still a fairly new&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; option in the 401(k) world,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://aon.mediaroom.com/2014-04-28-Aon-Hewitt-Analysis-Finds-More-Employers-Adding-Roth-Features-to-Expand-Savings-Options&quot;&gt;half of employers&lt;/a&gt;
now offer a Roth option.  While contributing
to a Roth is not necessarily the best choice for everyone, it can be a good
choice for younger workers who haven’t reached their peak earnings potential
(and tax bracket).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, younger workers also tend to be those who are struggling to survive and
may have a hard time contributing enough to get the full match that their employer
provides.  For workers in this donut hole, it may make more sense
to contribute to the traditional 401(k) to get the maximum benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;example&quot;&gt;Example&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s look at a hypothetical example.  Let’s say your employer matches 50% of
your contribution up to 8%.  So if you are able to contribute 8%, the company
will match 4%.  And let’s assume you are single and making $75,000 which puts
you in the 25% tax bracket. Further, let’s assume that the most
you can afford to contribute to your 401(k) is $6,000 (before taxes)
or 8% of your income.  In other words, in order to cover your cost of living,
you need an income stream of $69,000/year after your 401(k) contributions are taken out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re contributing to a Roth, your $6000 becomes $4,500 after taxes which
is how much you can actually afford to contribute.  In this scenario,
you are getting 3% of the company match, but are missing out on the other 1% of
free money that your company could match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conversely, if you defer your taxes and contribute the entire $6,000 to a traditional
401(k), you will get the entire match from your employer which amounts to an
additional $750 added to your 401(k).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Roth 401(k)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Traditional 401(k)&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Gross Income&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$75,000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$75,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;401(k) Contribution&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$4,500&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$6,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;401(k) Taxes&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$1,500&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$0 (deferred)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Livable Income&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$69,000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$69,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Employer Match&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$2,250&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$3,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, eventually you will have to pay taxes on your traditional 401(k)
contribution.  If your future tax rate is still 25%, then you will pay the same
$1,500 (adjusted for gains) as you would have in the Roth case.  So you’re still
ahead by $750 (plus future gains).  Or in percentage terms, you would be ahead by
&lt;code&gt;(6000(1-0.25)+3000)/(6000-1500+2250)&lt;/code&gt; or 7.14%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are able to reduce your tax rate in retirement, which most early retirees
do, then the gain is even higher.  For example, if you pull your money out while in
a 15% tax bracket, then your potential gain is &lt;code&gt;(6000(1-0.15)+3000)/(6000-1500+2250)&lt;/code&gt;
or 20%!  A 20% future gain just by picking the right type of 401(k) is a pretty
big deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if your rate is higher in the future?  At what higher tax rate would you
break even?  To figure that out we solve the equation
&lt;code&gt;6000(1-rate)+3000 = 6000(1-0.25)+2250&lt;/code&gt; which gives a rate of 37.5%.
That means your future tax rate would have to be above 37.5% in order for the
Roth to be the right choice in this scenario.
And since you’d have to earn over $425,000 to hit the 39% tax rate, this is
what I would call a good problem to have and you can afford to hire a
financial advisor to help you figure it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;counter-example&quot;&gt;Counter Example&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if you have enough money to contribute fully to either a Roth or a traditional
401(k)?  In the above example, instead of assuming you can invest $6000, let’s assume
you can invest $8,000 (and live off of $67,000) which will give you the maximum
employer match either way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Roth 401(k)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Traditional 401(k)&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Gross Income&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$75,000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$75,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;401(k) Contribution&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$6,000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$8,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;401(k) Taxes&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$2,000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$0 (deferred)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Livable Income&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$67,000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$67,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Employer Match&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$3,000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$3,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, it comes down to what your current tax rate is versus your future
tax rate.  With these numbers the comparison is between &lt;code&gt;(8000(1-current_tax)+3000)&lt;/code&gt;
(Roth) and &lt;code&gt;(8000(1-future_tax)+3000)&lt;/code&gt; (traditional).  In other words, the decision
comes down to a simple comparison of tax rates and whether you think you will be
able to reduce your future tax rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there’s actually more to it than that.
It’s really a comparison between today’s &lt;em&gt;marginal&lt;/em&gt; tax
rate versus your retirement’s &lt;em&gt;total&lt;/em&gt; tax rate&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  Why?  Because if you’re living
off of your money in the future, some of the money you withdraw will be at a 0%
tax rate, and some at 10%, and so-on up to your marginal tax rate.
So even if your future marginal tax rate is the same as your current tax rate,
your future total tax rate would be lower because you have to fill
in those lower tax buckets first.  In other words, there’s a good chance that the
traditional 401(k) will still fare better than the Roth 401(k) if you don’t
inflate your future lifestyle spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Younger workers in lower tax brackets are often encouraged to invest in the Roth
option provided by their employers so that they can take advantage of their lower
career tax rates.  However, these workers should also consider that they could
be giving up free money if they are unable to contribute up to the full value
matched by their employers.  When in doubt, make sure you
get your full employer match using traditional 401(k) contributions before
contributing to a Roth 401(k).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roth_401(k)&quot;&gt;Roth 401(k)&lt;/a&gt; first went into effect in 2006. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://thefinancebuff.com/case-against-roth-401k.html&quot;&gt;“The Case Against Roth 401(k)”&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 23 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        
          <link>http://www.moneycle.com/maximize-your-employer-match-before-using-a-roth-401-k/</link>
        
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.moneycle.com/maximize-your-employer-match-before-using-a-roth-401-k/</guid>
        
        <category>investing</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to Take Early IRA Withdrawals without Penalty</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If you are like many early retirees, then you may find most
of your savings are tied up in your &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.investopedia.com/terms/d/deferredaccount.asp&quot;&gt;tax-deferred accounts&lt;/a&gt;
like traditional 401k or IRA accounts when you are ready to retire.
If you are younger than 59.5 years old,
then how do you withdraw your funds without penalty?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are three possible choices for withdrawing your money without penalty:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Roth Ladder - a Roth ladder is where you convert your traditional IRA
  funds to Roth then withdraw them 5 years later.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Annuities - traditional IRA funds can be used to purchase a single premium
  immediate annuity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Substantially Equal Period Payments (SEPP) - also referred to as 72(t) which
  is the section of the tax code that allows this withdrawal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-sepp&quot;&gt;Why SEPP?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I prefer the Roth Ladder approach for withdrawing fund, it may not be enough
to meet your spending needs if you don’t have enough in your Roth to begin with.
Annuities have their place in retirement too, but for early retirees they are
less attractive (rates go up as you get older).  The SEPP withdrawal can help
fill the spending gap until you are 59.5 at which point you will have other
options to avoid penalties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sepp-rules&quot;&gt;SEPP Rules&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of things you need to be aware of when setting up a SEPP
withdrawal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The account you from which you do you SEPP withdrawals needs to be a stand-alone
  account.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You cannot trade in or out of the SEPP account after the payments have begun.
  Doing so will result in stiff penalties, so don’t do it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You must continue withdrawals for at least 5 years and until you are age
  59.5 or greater.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You must calculate your withdrawal using one of three methods:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;amortization&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;annuitization&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;required-minimum distributions (RMD)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you ever get audited you may need to show the calculation, so document
  the calculation and save it somewhere you can find later.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there are 3 approved methods for withdrawing your money, I suggest you stick
with amortization.  The RMD method will give the smallest amount of money, especially
for younger retirees, since it is just your account value divided by your remaining
life expectancy. Amortization and annuitization tend to result in similar payouts
that are both larger than RMD.  And a larger payout is good because it means you can
use a smaller portion of your retirement funds for the SEPP withdrawals and retain some
flexibility with your remaining funds.  Between amortization and annuitization
I prefer the amortization method because it is a easier to calculate and
therefore less prone to error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;setup-the-sepp-account&quot;&gt;Setup the SEPP Account&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you have decided to setup a SEPP withdrawal, the first thing you should do
is create a separate account inside of your existing brokerage account.  For example,
if you have funds at Vanguard, you can break your accounts into separate sub-accounts
that each have their own set of funds in them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amount you put into your SEPP account depends largely on the calculation
you’ll be doing below.  I recommend that you first determine how much &lt;strong&gt;income&lt;/strong&gt; you
will need from the SEPP withdrawal and then reverse the calculation to determine how much
money to put into your newly created account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;doublecheck-the-calculation&quot;&gt;Doublecheck the Calculation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are three ways to do this calculation: spreadsheet formula, web calculators
and good old mathematics. All 3 methods should give you the same number so it’s
a good idea to try at least 2 of these methods to sanity check that you’re doing
it right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all of these methods, you will need the following 3 numbers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;rate&lt;/code&gt; = 120% of the Applicable Federal Rate.  Don’t worry, you’re not alone,
  nobody else has heard of this number either.  It’s a number that the IRS
  publishes monthly and can be
  &lt;a href=&quot;http://apps.irs.gov/app/picklist/list/federalRates.html&quot;&gt;found here&lt;/a&gt;.
  You are allowed to choose one of the past 2 months when you do the calculation
  but to be safe I would just choose the rate from the most recent month.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;expectancy&lt;/code&gt; = your remaining life expectancy in years.  This is also published
  by the IRS and can be &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.irs.gov/pub/irs-pdf/p590b.pdf&quot;&gt;found here&lt;/a&gt;.
  Look in Appendix B for the life expectancy tables using the age you will be on
  your birthday this year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;principal&lt;/code&gt; = the size of the account you will be taking distributions from.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spreadsheet-formula&quot;&gt;Spreadsheet Formula&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spreadsheet formula that I have tested using Google Spreadsheet is simply:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
=-pmt(rate, expectancy, principal)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will give you the amount you can withdraw annually so divide by 12 if you
are going to make monthly withdrawals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sepp-calculators&quot;&gt;SEPP Calculators&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several calculators that will help you figure out the SEPP withdrawals.
I recommend the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://72t.net/72t/Calculator/Distributions&quot;&gt;72t.net Calculator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dinkytown.net/java/Retire72T.html&quot;&gt;Dinkytown Calculator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I prefer the 72t.net calculator since it gives results to the nearest penny.
But go ahead and verify that you get the same number to the nearest dollar from
both calculators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;math-equation&quot;&gt;Math Equation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the mathematically inclined, you can also plug your numbers into
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amortization_calculator#The_formula&quot;&gt;the annuity formula&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
income = principal * rate / (1 - (1+rate)^-expectancy)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;account-size-needed-for-a-desired-income&quot;&gt;Account Size Needed for a Desired Income&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are thinking about using SEPP withdrawals, there’s a good chance that you
already know how much income you need and just want to figure out how much principal
you need to put aside to generate that income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One approach would be to calculate how much income you get from $100,000 then
use that to figure out how much you need for your desired income level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, let’s say you want an annual income of $12,000,
the current mid-term rate is 2.04%, and your remaining life expectancy is 36 years.
Plugging in those numbers for $100,000 of principal gives you an income of $3,948.53.
To get to your desired income of $12,000 you then divide $12,000 by $3,948.53 and
multiply by $100,000 to arrive at a principal of $303,910.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more direct approach, is to invert the ‘math equation’ above and calculate
your payment directly with this formula:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
principal = income * (1 - (1+rate)^-expectancy) / rate
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, once you arrive at what you think the correct principal amount is,
double check it by any of the above methods to make sure it gives you the desired
income.  Then set aside that amount in an account that you won’t touch except to
do the SEPP withdrawals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SEPP withdrawals aren’t for everyone.  But if you find yourself in a situation
where you need to use them, this article should help you figure out how to do the
calculations needed. Regardless of what happens in the market you should
continue withdrawing the exact same amount, so have your brokerage do
an automatic withdrawal so that you aren’t tempted to mess with it.
Also, don’t forget that you will need to pay income taxes on your withdrawals
since this is just income that you deferred from the past.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 27 Mar 2015 18:55:50 -0600</pubDate>
        
          <link>http://www.moneycle.com/how-to-take-early-ira-withdrawals-without-penalty/</link>
        
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.moneycle.com/how-to-take-early-ira-withdrawals-without-penalty/</guid>
        
        <category>spending</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Penny Saved Is Four Dollars Earned</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We’ve all heard the phrase “a penny saved is a penny earned”, which is usually
attributed to Benjamin Franklin, inventor of the bifocals.
And while Benjamin Franklin is revered by the monocle-loving crowd,
his adage does not accurately represent the true worth of a penny saved in the
context of an early retirement.  Let’s take a look at what a penny saved in your
monthly expenses equals in terms of how much money you need to save.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;retirement-income&quot;&gt;Retirement Income&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When thinking about retirement income, a good rule-of-thumb is to use the 4% rule.
This isn’t a hard and fast rule, but it does give us a good idea of how much
money we need to save for a particular income.  For example, a portfolio of
$300,000 can reasonably be expected to generate an income of $12,000 per year
(4% of $300,000), or $1000 per month.  Conversely, if we want an
income of $1000 per month, we need to save 300 times that amount in our retirement
account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we talk about income needs in retirement, all we’re really talking about
is covering our living expenses.  So, if we can reduce our expenses by
$1 per month, then we can retire with $300 less in our portfolio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;taxes&quot;&gt;Taxes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accounting for taxes can be a little more tricky because the tax rate depends
on when the money is taxed.  If it is taxed while you are in your peak earning
years, you might be paying a combined 33% or more federal and state taxes,
not to mention sales tax on whatever your are spending your money on.
But after retirement, you should be in a lower tax bracket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the sake of argument, let’s assume you have deferred your taxes until retirement
and that the money you’re spending is coming out of a traditional IRA.
And let’s say you’re in the 15% federal bracket, 5% state and 5% sales tax.
It’s pretty easy to get to 25% combined taxes even at lower tax brackets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this 25% tax rate, instead of saving $300 now to spend $1 later, we would
have to save $400.  So, if you start with $400, and subtract 25%, or $100 for
taxes, then you arrive at the $300 needed to sustain $1 in monthly spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In equation form, you need to save &lt;code&gt;$300/(1-tax_rate)&lt;/code&gt; to sustain a dollar of monthly
expenses.  For example, if you’re combined tax rate is 40%, then the
amount you need to earn to save for a $1 monthly expense would be &lt;code&gt;$300/0.6&lt;/code&gt; or $500!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;monthly-expenses&quot;&gt;Monthly Expenses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the $400 multiplier from above, consider some typical monthly expenses and their
impact on your savings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;If you will be spending …&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;You need to save…&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;$8 your Hulu subscription&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$3,200&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;$30 to have your dachshund bathed&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$12,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;$50 extra on your phone bill&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$20,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;$100 extra on your cable bill&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$40,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The math on this is easy to do in your head, which is partly why I chose the
25% tax rate for our examples.  Multiplying by 400 is simply multiplying by
2 twice then adding 2 zeroes.  So, when you consider the money you need to
save to cover a cost of say, $6.35, times 2 is $12.70, times 2 is $25.40,
and add 2 zeros to arrive at $2540.  You don’t need a fancy monocle to do
that in your head!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;daily-expenses&quot;&gt;Daily Expenses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daily expenses have an even bigger impact per dollar.  If you consider a daily
expense to be around 25 times per month, then you need 25*$400, or $10,000,
to cover every $1 of daily expenses in the future.
The math couldn’t be easier, just add 4 zeros.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;If you will be spending …&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;You need to save…&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;$1 to have your monocle cleaned&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$10,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;$2 for a fountain drink with lunch&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$20,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;$5 for a venti Starbucks Frappucino&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$50,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if you can’t live without your Starbucks, maybe just downgrading to the
grande size will save you $10,000.  And maybe you could even learn to clean
your own damn monocle and save another $10,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been a little bit loose with the numbers partially because it’s hard to
know exactly what your withdrawal and tax rates will be.  But the point of this
article is to give you some ballpark numbers with which to evaluate whether an
added expense is worth it.  Simply put, to figure out how much money you’ll
need to support a spending level in retirement:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for monthly expenses, multiply the expense by 400.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for daily expenses, multiply the expense by 10,000.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully this rule-of-thumb will help you think about the impact of
spending on your retirement.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
          <link>http://www.moneycle.com/a-penny-saved-is-four-dollars-earned/</link>
        
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.moneycle.com/a-penny-saved-is-four-dollars-earned/</guid>
        
        <category>investing</category>
        
        <category>spending</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
