<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Moneycle</title>
    <description>Don your money monocle (top hats are optional) as we explore topics related to money, investing and early retirement.
</description>
    <link>http://www.moneycle.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.moneycle.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 19:12:39 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 19:12:39 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Journey to Financial Independence</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;My own journey to financial independence (FI) wasn’t exactly smooth and well
executed.  I was always a good saver and investor but I didn’t really consider
the endpoint thoroughly until I got there.  That’s not to say I didn’t have
the end goal in mind, I did.
But I didn’t have a clear picture of how my assets should be allocated
at the time of FI so I had to scramble a little bit at the finish line to
make sure my portfolio was set up to support retirement spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the problem is that most of the available investment advice
is geared towards the accumulation of assets.  The accumulation mindset
is great while you’re in the portfolio building years. But I think it’s
useful to have a clear idea of where you want your portfolio to end up at the
time you’re ready to stop taking a real paycheck from a job and start taking
money out of your portfolio. This “decumulation” process is
something I have a much better handle on
now that I’ve reached the FI milestone and it informs how I now think about
the whole financial journey in retrospect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, in this article I propose what I think is a lifelong investment
strategy that is better geared towards achieving and maintaining FI.
The graph below illustrates this strategy using a hypothetical timeline from an
investor’s beginning all the way through FI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/journey.png&quot; alt=&quot;FI Journey&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to keep the discussion simple, I have identified just 3 types of
investment buckets: growth (red), stability (blue), and safety (green).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally speaking these buckets are what they sound like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Growth - assets that aren’t needed for at least 10 years.  Growth
  assets have the advantage of time and this is the part of your
  portfolio that can take maximum risk.  Invest in assets that can be volatile
  in the short term but give you higher returns in the long term such as stocks,
  real estate, long-term bonds.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stability - assets that may be needed in the medium term (5-10 years).
  Invest in assets which have a relatively low risk but still some possibility
  for gain to keep up with inflation such as medium-term bonds or long-term CDs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Safety - assets that might be needed in the near term (less than 5 years).
  Invest in assets that have very low risk of losing value such
  as savings, CDs or short-term bonds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;understand-your-expenses&quot;&gt;Understand Your Expenses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before you do anything, you really need to have a handle on your current
monthly expenses.  Knowing your expenses is a key to implementing this
strategy and allows you to easily monitor your progress.
Also, being aware of your expenses drives home the fact that lowering your
expenses is a key towards reaching your goals sooner.&lt;br /&gt;
It’s the one variable you have the most direct control over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re not sure of your expenses, sign up for one of those services
that will help you track them.  Understanding where your money goes and
how much you spend every year is vital to informing where you are and how
to invest your assets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;milestone-1-m1---emergency-fund-invested-in-safety&quot;&gt;Milestone #1 (M1) - Emergency Fund Invested in “Safety”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first milestone in any investor’s life should be to set up an emergency
fund using “safety” investments.  In my opinion, the primary purpose of the
emergency fund is to handle employment gaps.  So the size of your emergency
fund should reflect how much time it might take you to find a new job if you
find yourself temporarily unemployed. For example, if you work in a high demand
field then maybe just having 3 months worth of expenses saved in your emergency
fund is adequate.
But if your skills are very specialized, you might want to consider something
like a year’s worth of emergency funds.
If you’re not sure, default to 6 months of expenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The emergency fund is the ballast of your “safety” bucket and should be invested
for safety only.  Resist the urge to invest these assets for growth.
The purpose of this fund is as a safety net, so you
don’t want to risk having it decline in value when you need it most.
After you have fully-funded your emergency fund it’s time to switch gears and
invest for long-term growth.  The simplest “growth” investment is 100% stocks
using something like a total market stock index fund.  But if a 100% stock
allocation seems too risky for you then consider a mix of stocks and bonds
such as 90/10 stocks/bonds, or 80/20 stocks/bonds.
But I wouldn’t go above 30% bonds in the “growth” bucket because you will be
adding more bonds to the overall portfolio later when you start adding to
the “stability” bucket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;milestone-2-m2---20-years-of-expenses-invested-in-growth&quot;&gt;Milestone #2 (M2) - 20 Years of Expenses Invested in “Growth”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can certainly celebrate other milestones such as 1, 5 and 10-years of expenses
in your “growth” bucket.  But the 20-year milestone is a big deal!  When you
have 20 years of expenses saved in growth, then the light of retirement is
visible at the end of your investment tunnel.
After you hit this milestone you are beginning a transitional phase that
sets you up for FI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-better-rule-of-thumb-for-bonds&quot;&gt;A Better Rule of Thumb for Bonds&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having hit 20x expenses in growth, it’s now time to start investing for “stability”.
Ultimately the “stability” bucket is the part of your portfolio that helps to cover expenses
that are a few years out, say 5-10 years.  So instead of the rules of thumb for investing
in bonds that are based on your age, I believe it should instead be based on how much you have
invested in the “growth” bucket.  I would state this new rule of thumb for bonds as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Start investing in your “stability” bucket (bonds) &lt;strong&gt;after&lt;/strong&gt; you have
accumulated 20 times your annual expenses in your “growth” bucket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 2 key points to this seemingly simple rule.  First, it’s not based on
age but rather on your progress towards your goal of financial independence.
Second, this rule puts the focus on your expenses as the key to measuring how
close you actually are to that FI goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After having hit the 20x milestone (M2), then once every year I suggest
you sweep your “growth” gains into your “stability”
bucket while keeping the “growth” bucket at 20x expenses.
Conversely, if your “growth” bucket had a bad year, then rebalance some
“stability” bucket funds back into the “growth” bucket to get it back up to
20x expenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a little different than traditional rebalancing concepts that are based
purely on target percentages. Instead of a using target percentage, you are
rebalancing based on a targeted expense multiplier (20x in “growth”).
Think of it as filling in your ultimate FI allocation from the riskiest assets
down to your least risky assets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;milestone-3-m3---5-years-of-expenses-invested-in-stability&quot;&gt;Milestone #3 (M3) - 5 Years of Expenses Invested in “Stability”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have 5 years of expenses in “stability” and 20 years in “growth”,
your overall portfolio will be at 80% “growth” and 20% “stability”.
So you can see that your portfolio is becoming more
conservative as you get closer to FI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you hit this milestone (M3), you’re not quite there yet but you can start
to think seriously about your impending financial independence and whether
you will want to continue working.  As such, the
next investment is back into “safety”.  I’m suggesting that you save 5 years
of expenses in “safety” but that number is somewhat arbitrary.  The key is to
have a comfortable amount of expenses in non-risky buckets so that you will
be positioned to pull the trigger on retirement and not have to worry about
a market correction in the first few years of retirement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want, you can just add these “safety” funds into your existing
emergency fund because the primary need for the emergency fund,
to cover employment income gaps, is going away.
In effect, your emergency fund is transforming from a safety net
into a spending bucket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, as with the previous milestone, you should still rebalance every year
to keep your “growth” bucket at 20x expenses and you “stability” bucket
at 5x expenses.
Based on market conditions you may find you need to backfill either growth
or stability.
But you can also use gains from those buckets to feed into your “safety”
buckets and get you to FI that much faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;milestone-4-fi---financial-independence-30-years-of-expenses&quot;&gt;Milestone #4 (FI) - Financial Independence (30 Years of Expenses)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you have 20x expenses in “growth”, 5x expenses in “stability”, and
5x expenses in “safety”, then congratulations!
You have reached financial independence!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you do choose to continue working after FI, I recommend putting all
future extra savings into the long-term “growth” bucket because, by design,
you won’t need those funds in the near term.
Alternatively, you could also just keep the 20/5/5 growth/stability/safety
ratios going and increase your spending accordingly when you do
eventually retire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you had chosen to keep 100% stocks in your “growth” bucket then,
when you hit the FI milestone, you will have 67% stocks in your overall portfolio.
If you prefer to target a little smaller stock allocation in your portfolio
at retirement, then you can &lt;strong&gt;use your target
percentage to inform how much to keep in your “growth” bucket&lt;/strong&gt;.
For example, if you’d like to hit a target of 60% overall stocks on your
FI date, then &lt;strong&gt;multiply the targeted stock allocation by 1.5&lt;/strong&gt;
(30 years total / 20 years in “growth”)
to arrive at a 90% stock percentage in your “growth” buckets.
I think any stock allocation between 75-100% is fine for the “growth” bucket
but you should give some serious thought to how you would feel if you reached
FI right before the market takes a big hit.  If you’re not sure, start with 90%
stocks in “growth”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;not-quite-a-target-date-fund&quot;&gt;Not Quite a Target-Date Fund&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Astute readers may notice that this investment strategy has similarities to
target-date funds.  Generally those funds invest aggressively early on and become
more conservative as you approach the target date.  While I think target-date
funds are pretty good for many people because of their simplicity, they differ
slightly from the strategy in this article in a few distinct ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First, target-date funds become &lt;strong&gt;too&lt;/strong&gt; conservative if you hold them to maturity.
Most target-date funds end up with a stock mix below 40% and some go as low as 24%.
I think this is okay for a fund where you’re targeting a big purchase near that
target date, but not necessarily for FI.  You want your assets to keep up
with inflation so I think your post-FI stock allocation
should be somewhere in the 45-65% range.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Second, target-date funds don’t give you a convenient way to access just the
“safety” part of the portfolio such as the short-term bonds and money market
funds.  There is a peace-of-mind in being able to access risk-free funds for
day-to-day expenses and ignoring the gyrations of the stock market.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Third, target-date funds don’t adjust the goal date if your financial
independence date changes because your portfolio is doing better or worse
than expected.
The strategy in this article would better be described as a “target expense”
fund than a “target date” fund as it is personalized to your level of
spending rather than an arbitrary future date.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if you use target-date funds during accumulation that’s fine.  But consider
that you will probably want to switch out of them at or near the time when you
start the transition to retirement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-considerations&quot;&gt;Other Considerations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While understanding your expenses is a key part of this strategy, it’s also
important to consider any future pensions or social security payments you may
receive.
For example, if you expect to be receiving a $1000/month social security check
at retirement, then you can effectively subtract that $1000/month from your
expenses for the purposes of figuring out how much you need to reach FI.
This could dramatically reduce the amount you need to invest/save to
reach retirement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, because it targets 30 years of expenses, this strategy effectively
presumes a 3.33% withdrawal rate (1/30 = 3.33%).
If you feel like your withdrawal rate should be different, you can modify
this plan accordingly by changing the sizes of the different buckets slightly.
But I think the plan as presented here is a good baseline for most people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I didn’t give any details on the types of accounts used to invest
these bucket assets.  While that’s important I didn’t want to confuse the point of
this article too much.  Suffice it to say that it’s a good idea to have some
tax diversity utilizing a combination of Roth, traditional
and taxable accounts for your portfolio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;key-takeaways&quot;&gt;Key Takeaways&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This strategy is geared towards achieving your actual future spending goals
instead of aiming for an arbitrary retirement date.&lt;br /&gt;
This helps to clarify what you actually need while simultaneously giving
you a good measure of your progress towards financial independence.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Put as much into the “growth” bucket as early as possible, then add
“stability” and “safety” later as you approach retirement.&lt;br /&gt;
This approach maximizes the amount of time your riskier assets have to grow.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Invest in “stability” (bonds) only after you have accumulated 20 years
worth of expenses in “growth”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Multiply your desired stock allocation at retirement by 1.5 to arrive at
the percentage of stocks to have in the “growth” bucket during accumulation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Following this investment strategy will slowly transition your assets into
retirement so you don’t have to scramble to reallocate assets to an
appropriate post-retirement mix.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This strategy could be implemented with as few as just 2 or 3 funds.
For example, you could put all of your “growth” assets into a
total stock market fund, all of your “stability” assets into a total
bond market fund,
and all of your “safety” assets into a savings account or short-term bond fund.
Also, after you reach FI you could combine your “growth” and “stability”
buckets into a single balanced fund.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t forget to consider other sources of income in retirement such as Social
Security or pensions.  These other income sources effectively reduce the
expenses you need to cover with your investment portfolio and can get you to
FI faster.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;related&quot;&gt;Related&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/comparing-target-date-fund-glide-paths/&quot;&gt;Comparing Target-Date Fund Glide Paths&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 08 Aug 2018 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        
          <link>http://www.moneycle.com/journey-to-financial-independence/</link>
        
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.moneycle.com/journey-to-financial-independence/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>To Roth or Not to Roth - Part 3, Retiring at Age 70</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;retiring-at-70&quot;&gt;Retiring at 70&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Age 70 is the focal point of this article because it’s the age (technically 70.5)
where you must begin taking distributions from your Traditional accounts in the
form of required minimum distributions (RMDs).  It’s also the latest age (and
possibly the optimal age) to which you can delay taking social security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to figure out the maximum Traditional portfolio value at age 70,
we need to figure out what portfolio value will generate the amount of income
that fills in the lowest tax brackets during retirement.
Combining that future income level with
the minimum withdrawal rate will allow us to calculate what the portfolio size
needs to be at age 70.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/roth_or_not_3-3_bands.png&quot; alt=&quot;age-70 bands&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;starting-simple&quot;&gt;Starting Simple&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To keep things simple, let’s start with the idea of just filling in the 0%
tax brackets in the future.  Just about everybody would benefit from deferring
taxes into a future time when the funds are taxed at 0% (untaxed) so this
simple case applies to most people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technically there isn’t a 0% tax bracket but rather income that is exempted
from taxes via the deductions and personal exemptions.
This is further complicated by the &lt;a href=&quot;/how-social-security-messes-with-your-tax-brackets/&quot;&gt;effects of taxes on social security&lt;/a&gt;
so, for now, let’s just assume that the first $20k of income for a married couple
($10k for singles) is not taxed.
If that’s the case, then the goal would be make sure your
Traditional IRA/401k/403b generates no more than $20k of income ($10k single)
at age 70 and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the government requires that you start taking distributions from
your tax-deferred accounts in the year you hit age 70.5. In that first year,
you are required to distribute at least 3.65% (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;portfolio_value/27.4&lt;/code&gt;)
of your tax-deferred portfolio as income.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
As such, the amount that must be taken in that first year dictates how big your
portfolio could be before you must start taking income that creeps into higher
tax brackets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;simple-example&quot;&gt;Simple example&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s use some real numbers to get an idea of what we’re talking about.
If you want to make sure your future portfolio (age 70.5) generates no more
than $20k of income, then the upper limit on your portfolio value at that age
is determined by&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;portfolio_income = portfolio_at_70 / 27.4 &amp;lt; $20k
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it’s a simple case to solve for the portfolio value&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;portfolio_at_70 &amp;lt; $20k * 27.4 = $548k.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So finally we have a number, $548k for a married couple ($274k for a single).
It’s a number with lots of assumptions and what-ifs
but it’s gives you an idea of about how much to put into your
tax-deferred accounts under those simple assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more general version of this equation is to use the income level, in
the future, that is taxed at or below your current tax rate.  Determining
that income threshold is more of an art than a science since future tax
brackets are somewhat unknowable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;portfolio_at_70 &amp;lt; income_threshold * 27.4
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you were born in the 2nd half of the year, replace 27.4 with 26.5 in the above
equation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;back-to-the-future&quot;&gt;Back to the Future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a future number or goal is nice, but in order to be useful, you need
to take into account your current situation in order to determine how much you
should contribute each year going forward in order for your non-Roth accounts
to stay at or below that number.
For example, if you are now aged 45 and expect to work until age 70,
then you have 25 years of appreciation in your portfolio that you want to keep
at or below $548k.  How does that translate to this-year’s contribution amount?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s break this down.  First, while the target amount is in today’s dollars,
you should expect some amount of appreciation in your portfolio after
inflation.  For example, if you expect your portfolio to earn 6% and inflation
to be 2% over the next 25 years, we could calculate what portfolio value today
would grow to $548k as,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;portfolio_target = portfolio_70 / (1 + net_return)^(70-age)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;net_return = portfolio_return - inflation
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So for that 45-year old in the example,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;portfolio_today = $548k / (1.04)^25
                = $205k
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does this mean?  If that 45-year old has already managed to save $205k
in tax-deferred accounts which return 4% after inflation, then they may want to
consider going all Roth contributions from here on out.
Remember that this assumes they work until age 70 and only want to generate
$20k of income (in today’s dollars) from the 401k/IRA portfolio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;todays-contributions&quot;&gt;Today’s Contributions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what if our 45-year-old hasn’t saved anything yet or only saved a smaller
amount?  Let’s determine the upper limit on their tax-deferred contributions
going forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we are representing the portfolio in today’s dollars, let’s
calculate the contributions needed in terms of the portfolio’s actual
value in today’s dollars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;portfolio_shortfall = (portfolio_target - portfolio_today)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply put, we need an annual contribution going forward that is big enough to
fill that shortfall, so using the present-value calculation,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;contribution = PV(net_return,
                  70-current_age,
                  portfolio_shortfall)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Present_value&quot;&gt;present value calculation&lt;/a&gt;
represents what level of regular contribution
that are needed to produce the present value of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;portfolio_shortfall&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;contribution = portfolio_shortfall * net_return ÷
                (1 - (1+net_return)^(age-70))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using our 45-year-old example, and assuming they have already saved $105k,
then the shortfall is $100k.  With a 4% return after inflation
they could contribute up to,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;contribution = $100k * 0.04 / (1 - 1.04^-25)
             = $6401
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So a contribution of $6401/year would get this theoretical person’s portfolio
to the level that would produce $20k of income (in today’s dollars) at age 70
using RMDs.
Any contributions above $6401 could go to a Roth account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, if they are starting with zero savings, then the shortfall in today’s
dollars is $205k which means they could contribute up to $13,122 to their
Traditional account every year to produce that same income in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;another-fun-interactive-plot&quot;&gt;Another Fun Interactive Plot&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now have a set of equations (highlighted) that help you determine the
contributions you should make until age 70.  But they are very sensitive to
the assumed rate of return.  Below is a plot the needed contribution amounts
as a function of the assumed rate of return.  Move the sliders around for
your age, inflation rate and future tax-deferred income target
to see how it looks for your situation.
For help on setting the future tax-deferred income target
take a look at the article about &lt;a href=&quot;/how-social-security-messes-with-your-tax-brackets/&quot;&gt;how social security messes with your tax
brackets&lt;/a&gt; and choose
a value that will be taxed below your current marginal tax rate (defaults to
$20k as a &lt;em&gt;crude&lt;/em&gt; approximation of the 0% tax bracket for a married couple).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;puppy&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you are seeing a puppy image below, then you are missing out on the
  amazingly excellent interactive content on the site.
  Click on the puppy to open the article in a browser
  and see what you are missing.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.randomdoggiegenerator.com/randomdoggie.php&quot; alt=&quot;puppy&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;percentRoth-graph&quot; class=&quot;chart&quot;&gt;
    &lt;svg&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Current Age (&lt;span class=&quot;current-age&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;age-slider&quot; class=&quot;slider&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inflation Rate (&lt;span class=&quot;inflation-rate&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;inflation-slider&quot; class=&quot;slider&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Future Tax-Deferred Income Target in Today’s Dollars (&lt;span class=&quot;income-threshold&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;threshold-slider&quot; class=&quot;slider&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
  .chart {
    clear: both;
  }
  .chart, svg {
    height: 360px;
  }
  .slider {
    width: 90%;
  }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
  d3.select('#puppy').remove();

  var age = 45;
  var portfolio = 100000;
  var threshold = 20000;
  var inflationRate = 0.025;

  var returnInc = 0.001;
  var maxReturn = 0.121;
  var maxContribution = threshold;
  var portfolioIncr = 10000;
  var maxThreshold = 100000;
  var thresholdIncr = 1000;
  var maxPortfolio = 540000;
  var minPortfolio = 100000;

  function contributionAmount(rate) {
    maxPortfolio = portfolioIncr * Math.ceil(threshold * 27.4 / portfolioIncr);
    maxPortfolio = Math.max(maxPortfolio, minPortfolio);
    var contributions = [];
    var portfolioAt70 = threshold * 27.4;
    var portfolioTicks = Array.from({length: 1+maxPortfolio/portfolioIncr}, (e, k) =&gt; k*portfolioIncr);
    contributions = portfolioTicks.map(
      function(portfolio) {
        var netReturn = rate - inflationRate;
        var yearsLeft = 70 - age;
        var appreciation = Math.pow(1+netReturn, yearsLeft);
        var portfolioTarget = portfolioAt70 / appreciation;
        var shortfall = portfolioTarget - portfolio;
        var contribution = (appreciation != 1) ?
          shortfall * netReturn * appreciation / (appreciation-1) :
          shortfall / yearsLeft;
        contribution = Math.max(contribution, 0);
        return [portfolio, contribution];
      });
    maxContribution = Math.max(maxContribution, 1000*Math.ceil(contributions[0][1]/1000));
    return contributions;
  }

  function updateData() {
    maxContribution = 0;
    var data = [
    {
      name: '4% return',
      xy: contributionAmount(0.04),
      color: '#aaaa20'
    },
    {
      name: '6% return',
      xy: contributionAmount(0.06),
      color: '#aa2020'
    },
    {
      name: '8% return',
      xy: contributionAmount(0.08),
      color: '#20aa20'
    },
    {
      name: '10% return',
      xy: contributionAmount(0.10),
      color: '#2020aa'
    },
    ];
    if (typeof theChart !== 'undefined') {
      theChart.xDomain([0.00, maxPortfolio]);
      theChart.yDomain([0, maxContribution]);
    }

    d3.selectAll(&quot;.current-age&quot;).text('' + age);
    d3.selectAll(&quot;.inflation-rate&quot;).text('' + Math.round(inflationRate*1000)/10 + '%');
    d3.selectAll(&quot;.portfolio-value&quot;).text(d3.format('$,f')(portfolio));
    d3.selectAll(&quot;.income-threshold&quot;).text('$' + threshold);

    return d3.select('#percentRoth-graph svg').datum(chartifyData(data));
  }
  var theData = updateData();

  function newChart(chartData, interactive) {

    var aChart = nv.models.lineChart()
                  .interactive(interactive)
                  .useInteractiveGuideline(interactive)
                  .showLegend(true)
                  .showYAxis(true)
                  .showXAxis(true);

    aChart.xAxis
        .axisLabel('Current Tax-Deferred Portfolio Value')
        .tickFormat(d3.format('$,f'))
        .showMaxMin(false);

    aChart.yAxis     //Chart y-axis settings
        .axisLabel('Annual Tax-Deferred Contribution')
        .tickFormat(d3.format('$,f'))
        .showMaxMin(false);

    aChart.xDomain([0.00, maxPortfolio]);
    aChart.yDomain([0, maxContribution]);

    chartData.call(aChart);

    //Update the chart when window resizes.
    nv.utils.windowResize(function() {
      aChart.update();
    });


    return aChart;
  }

  function chartifyData(data) {
    //Line chart data should be sent as an array of series objects.
    return data.map(function(obj) {
      return {
        values: transformXY(obj.xy),
        key: obj.name,
        color: obj.color,
        disabled: obj.disabled ? true : false
      }
    });
  }

  function transformXY(data) {
    var result = [];
    for (i = 0; i &lt; data.length; i++) {
      var point = data[i];
      result.push({x: point[0], y: point[1]});
    }
    return result;
  }

  theChart = newChart(theData, true);
  nv.addGraph(theChart);

  d3.select('#inflation-slider').call(d3.slider().axis(d3.svg.axis().ticks(6)).min(0).max(5).step(0.1).value(inflationRate*100).on(&quot;slide&quot;, function(evt, rate) {
    inflationRate = rate / 100;
    updateData().call(theChart);
  }));
  d3.select('#age-slider').call(d3.slider().axis(d3.svg.axis().ticks(11)).min(19).max(69).step(1).value(age).on(&quot;slide&quot;, function(evt, newAge) {
    age = newAge;
    updateData().call(theChart);
  }));
  d3.select('#threshold-slider').call(d3.slider().axis(d3.svg.axis().ticks(11)).min(thresholdIncr).max(maxThreshold).step(thresholdIncr).value(threshold).on(&quot;slide&quot;, function(evt, newValue) {
    threshold = newValue;
    updateData().call(theChart);
  }));


&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-you-assume&quot;&gt;When You Assume&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beware of the assumptions made in this article.  First and foremost, figuring
out what future tax brackets will look like is anybody’s guess.  So determining
your how much income to generate in the future is a guessing game.
I suggest erring on the conservative side and using the current 0% tax bracket
(deductions and exemptions) as a starting point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The assumed rate of return is also tricky.  If you use this article to set
your contribution amount, then do so knowing that things will change every year.
So make sure you revisit your assumptions every year with updated portfolio
values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many ways you could generate income in the future.
Taking RMDs as suggested in this article is just one method for taking income
from your portfolio.
Another possibility is buying a single premium income annuity (SPIA) which
guarantees lifetime income.
An annuity would likely return a rate much higher than 3.65% (over 5%) so if
you convert your Traditional account to an annuity at ge 70, you could have
higher income that you would with RMDs.  That could suggest lower contributions
than calculated by this article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, this article is meant to provide a framework for calculating the limit
on Traditional (tax-deferred) contributions if you work until age 70.&lt;br /&gt;
That doesn’t mean you shouldn’t save more.
On the contrary, save as much as you can but put extra contributions
into a Roth account if possible.
And if you don’t want to work until age 70, forthcoming articles in this series
will discuss how to calculate your contributions when retiring before age 70.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Technically, if your birthday is between July and December then you can begin RMDs in the year in which you turn 71 which has a divisor of 26.5 instead of 27.4.  For simplicity, this article only uses the 27.4 number but you may want to substitute 26.5 for your own calculations if you were born in the 2nd half of the year. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 14 Aug 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        
          <link>http://www.moneycle.com/to-roth-or-not-to-roth-part-3/</link>
        
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.moneycle.com/to-roth-or-not-to-roth-part-3/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Super-Simple Virtual-Buffer Withdrawal Strategy - Revisited</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I was recently re-reading the original article that presented the concept of
this simple withdrawal strategy and found the explanation to be overly complex
which seems wrong for something that’s supposed to be simple.
So I ask you, dear reader, for another chance to describe the strategy in a way
that is more approachable (with less math) to the average reader.
In fact, the most complex thing about the strategy is the name&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-simplest-version&quot;&gt;The Simplest Version&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In it’s simplest form, the strategy boils down to the following 2 equations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;initial_monthly_withdrawal = portfolio_value / 400
next_monthly_withdrawal    =
     ⅔ * current_withdrawal + ⅓ * current_portfolio_value / 400
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first equation tells you how much you can withdrawal monthly from
your portfolio in the first year that you start taking withdrawals.
Dividing your portfolio value by 400 is equivalent to taking a 3% annual
withdrawal and gets the process started.  Conversely, if you multiply your monthly
expenses by 400, that can give you an approximation of how big your portfolio needs
to be in order to retire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second equation tells you how much you should adjust your withdrawal amount
each year.  This particular version of the equation assumes a buffer-size of 3
years and 3% withdrawal rate.  In case you haven’t been reading other
articles on this site, the buffer is what provides ballast to the withdrawal
equation so that your withdrawal amounts aren’t whipped around too much by a
volatile investment portfolio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;That’s it!&lt;/strong&gt;  If you’re comfortable with the assumed withdrawal rate of 3%
and buffer of 3 years then you can stop reading and just follow the above
equations (which I use for my own situation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;example-900000-portfolio&quot;&gt;Example: $900,000 portfolio&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take a simple example, start with a portfolio worth $900k.  Dividing
a this by 400 gives the initial monthly withdrawal of,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;initial_monthly_withdrawal = $900000 / 400
                           = $2250/month
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Piece of cake.  It’s up to you if you actually save the full 3-years of that
withdrawal amount into a safe place.  I recommend you at least save 1 year’s
worth, $27k in this example, in a safe account such as an interest-bearing savings.
Or maybe you’d feel better putting the entire 3-year buffer, $81k, in savings,
that’s fine too.  It mostly depends on your risk tolerance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, after one year, you re-evaluate the portfolio to decide whether to increase
or decrease your withdrawal amount.  Let’s say portfolio has had a good year, and is
worth $990k at the end of the year.  Your next year’s withdrawal rate
is computed as,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;next_monthly_withdrawal = ⅔ * 2250 + ⅓ * 990000 / 400
                        = 1500 + 825
                        = $2325/month
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So even though the portfolio grew by 10%, you only increase the monthly withdrawal
amount by 3.33% (because of the buffering).  It works both way, if the market has
a particularly bad year, it won’t kill your monthly withdrawal income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In every year after the first year, you just use the 2nd equation to determine
the withdrawal amount for the following year.  Over
the long haul, with these equations, your withdrawal amount will hover around 3%
of your total portfolio value&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-general-version&quot;&gt;The General Version&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you prefer a little more control over the withdrawal rate and buffer size,
then here’s the more general equations for this strategy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;initial_monthly_withdrawal =
     portfolio_value * withdrawal_rate / 12
next_monthly_withdrawal    =
     (1-1/buffer_size) * current_withdrawal +
       (1/buffer_size) * portfolio_value * withdrawal_rate / 12
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if you prefer a more aggressive 4% withdrawal that is stabilized
by a larger 5-year buffer then the withdrawal equations would simplify to,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;initial_monthly_withdrawal = portfolio_value / 300
next_monthly_withdrawal    =
     ⅘ * current_withdrawal + ⅕ * current_portfolio_value / 300
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;easy-peasy&quot;&gt;Easy Peasy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s all there is to implementing the Super-Simple Virtual-Buffer Withdrawal Strategy.
If you want to see the math behind the strategy, refer to the overly-complex
&lt;a href=&quot;/super-simple-virtual-buffer-withdrawal-strategy/&quot;&gt;original article&lt;/a&gt;.
The main takeaway from this strategy is that you only need to know two data
points each year, (1) the current withdrawal amount and (2) the current
portfolio value.
With those two numbers, you can calculate the next year’s withdrawal amount in
a way that is simple to compute but still buffers your retirement income against
wild fluctuations in the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;related&quot;&gt;Related&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/super-simple-virtual-buffer-withdrawal-strategy/&quot;&gt;Super-Simple Virtual-Buffer Withdrawal Strategy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/safe-withdrawal-rates-for-vampires/&quot;&gt;Safe Withdrawal Rates for Vampires&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/buffer-withdrawals-to-stabilize-income/&quot;&gt;Buffer Withdrawals to Stabilize Income&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/the-30-30-withdrawal-strategy/&quot;&gt;The 30-30 Withdrawal Strategy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I’m open to suggestions on better names for the strategy &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Technically if the market steadily increases over the long term your withdrawal amount would probably lag slightly below 3% on average, but who’s counting? &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 17 Jun 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        
          <link>http://www.moneycle.com/super-simple-virtual-buffer-withdrawal-strategy-revisited/</link>
        
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.moneycle.com/super-simple-virtual-buffer-withdrawal-strategy-revisited/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>To Roth or Not to Roth? - Part 2, Reframing the Question</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Many articles are written about the virtues of the Roth account&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
or the Traditional account types, but it’s rare to find an article suggesting
why you should probably consider having both types.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article I try to show that both types have their place, but the
important thing is to understand the main concept that will help you to determine
how much of each type you should have.  In short, the thesis of this
article is that you should first determine the maximum amount to
contribute to your Traditional account, then you should allocate the remainder
of your qualified savings to your Roth account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;basics---tax-efficiency&quot;&gt;Basics - Tax Efficiency&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The core decision of choosing Roth vs Traditional comes down to your tax rate
now (when you save the funds) versus your tax rate in the future (when you
withdraw the funds).  If your tax rates are identical now
and in the future you should choose the Roth because it has more flexibility
(access to principal, no distribution requirements).
But if your tax rates in the future, at the time of withdrawal, are lower than
your current marginal tax rate, then you could save money by deferring those
taxes into the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re a good saver, then there’s a pretty good chance that you should
be using both Roth and Traditional.  Why?  Because there’s a very real
possibility that your Traditional savings will outgrow the lower tax brackets,
especially when you consider other future income sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;filling-future-tax-brackets&quot;&gt;Filling Future Tax Brackets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think about your tax brackets over time.  For example, in an over-simplified
view of the world (ignoring inflation and other adjustments), your tax brackets
might look like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/roth_or_not_2-brackets.png&quot; alt=&quot;Tax Brackets Over Time&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Granted this is a naive view of tax brackets (they actually do change over time),
but I’m just trying to make a point so ignore those details for the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The general idea of saving to a Traditional account is that in the future you
will take those withdrawals out in lower tax brackets.  I like to visualize this
as pouring those Traditional IRA funds into the lower tax brackets over the time
that spans all of your retirement years.
For example, the following picture shows IRA funds filling up the 0% tax bracket
from retirement forward, which would be appropriate for anybody in a tax bracket
above 0% (probably everybody reading this).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/roth_or_not_2-filling_0.png&quot; alt=&quot;Filling 0% Tax Bracket&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of the above picture can be extended to higher tax brackets.  For example,
if you’re in the 33% tax bracket now, any savings you put into a Traditional IRA
now could save you money in the future if they were poured into any tax
bracket below 33% over the course of your retirement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might be thinking that the growth on the assets matter, but for this decision
it really doesn’t.  That’s because taking a percentage out now and letting your
investment grow (Roth) is mathematically equivalent to letting your entire
investment grow and taking the same percentage out later (Traditional).  So it
just comes down to figuring out when the tax rates will be lower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trick then is to figure out how big your Traditional account savings bucket
can get before it starts to leak into your current tax bracket in the future.
Because if you’re going to fill in your future tax brackets at your current
(or higher) rates, then you might as well contribute to a Roth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;upper-bounds-for-traditional-accounts&quot;&gt;Upper Bounds for Traditional Accounts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So instead of determining what &lt;em&gt;percentage&lt;/em&gt; to put in a Roth, the problem
becomes one of figuring out the maximum &lt;em&gt;absolute&lt;/em&gt; amount to put into a
Traditional account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can approach this problem by putting an upper bound on the size of
the Traditional IRA bucket (in the picture).  Once you know what that
upper bound is, you can
project the maximum that your Traditional contributions should be in order
to fill that bucket by your retirement date.
The projection will never be an exact number because returns are unpredictable
and retirement dates change.  But if you have this framework in place,
then you can make minor adjustments every year to account for the shifts in
your portfolio balance and retirement date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-income-sources&quot;&gt;Other Income Sources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably one of the hardest variables to predict ahead of time is the amount
of money you might get from other income sources.  Social Security is one
source that is fairly predictable, but what about income interest, dividends,
side-job income, pensions, inherited IRAs, annuities, et cetera.
You may have a good handle on what those sources are now, but it’s
not always easy to predict all future income sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/roth_or_not_2-other_income.png&quot; alt=&quot;Filling 0% Tax Bracket&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The effect of future income sources is that they fill in your lower tax
brackets &lt;strong&gt;before&lt;/strong&gt; withdrawals from your Traditional accounts.  This means
that you might have less room to withdraw funds in those lower tax brackets
in the future.  So the more future income you have from other sources, the
less you should contribute to Traditional accounts now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;realistic-tax-brackets&quot;&gt;Realistic Tax Brackets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To determine the maximum Traditional contributions, we also should consider
a more realistic view of tax brackets in retirement.  If you’ve read previous
articles on this blog you may be familiar with the effects of taxes of a couple
life situations.  There are 3 general bands that can effect tax brackets as
show below.  The picture below does not represent every situation but is meant
to suggest how complicated it can get (your situation will be different).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/roth_or_not_2-3_bands.png&quot; alt=&quot;3 Tax-Bracket Bands&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are getting health care from the ACA before age 65 then you would fall
into the band I’m calling the “ACA years”.
Those people eligible to receive Affordable Care Act premium credits may see
their &lt;a href=&quot;/affordable-care-act-may-increase-your-marginal-tax-rate/&quot;&gt;tax brackets jumbled up&lt;/a&gt;
by those credits before they start taking medicare at age 65.
And this situation could very well change by the time you read this given
the current political climate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second band, which I call the “early medicare years”, is the time before
age 70 and after age 65.  This band has a fairly “normal” tax bracket signature
because it is not affected by ACA or Social Security effects on taxes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking social security can effect the tax brackets at the lower end of the
income spectrum.  As discussed in a &lt;a href=&quot;/how-social-security-messes-with-your-tax-brackets/&quot;&gt;previous article on this blog&lt;/a&gt;
these effects can have significant impacts to tax brackets at or below 25%.
Also, since most people should probably delay taking social security until age
70 (your situation may vary), we will consider the case of retiring at age 70
while taking social security in the next article in this series in this band
which I call the “Social Security years”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;coming-next&quot;&gt;Coming Next&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next articles in this series will attempt to address the different bands of
time and how they might inform how much to save in Traditional accounts.
Ultimately the goal is to give you the tools (and maybe a calculator) to
estimate how much to contribute to Traditional accounts every year going
forward until you exit the rat race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;related&quot;&gt;Related&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/to-roth-or-not-to-roth-part-1/&quot;&gt;To Roth or Not to Roth? - Part 1, The Ideal World&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/affordable-care-act-may-increase-your-marginal-tax-rate/&quot;&gt;Affordable Care Act May Increase Your Marginal Tax Rate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/how-social-security-messes-with-your-tax-brackets/&quot;&gt;How Social Security Messes With Your Tax Brackets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I use the generic terms “Roth” and “Traditional” to refer to all qualified accounts such as IRA, 401k and 403b.  The basic concepts are the same regardless of the actual account vehicle you use. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 06 Apr 2017 23:54:55 -0600</pubDate>
        
          <link>http://www.moneycle.com/to-roth-or-not-to-roth-part-2/</link>
        
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.moneycle.com/to-roth-or-not-to-roth-part-2/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How Social Security Messes With Your Tax Brackets</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;While Social Security provides a nice base-level of income for many retirees,
it can have some interesting effects on the tax brackets.  The basic
philosophy of Social Security taxation is that you won’t be taxed on Social
Security benefits if you have no other income sources.  But as your other income
sources grow, your Social Security benefits may be subject to taxation.  This is
really just a means test that allows Uncle Sam to increase your
taxable income if you are well off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting into the weeds for a minute, the rules for taxation of Social Security
are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First, calculate what’s called the “provisional income” by adding half of
  your social security income to your “other income”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Other income” is my term, but it represents your taxable income (AGI) plus
  your non-taxable interest income.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If your “provisional income” is above the first threshold ($25,000 single,
$32,000 married), then 50% of the amount above that threshold is
added to your taxable income.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If your “provisional income” is above the second threshold ($34,000 single,
$44,000 married), then an additional 35% of the amount above the second
threshold is added to your taxable income, for a total of 85%.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A maximum of 85% of your Social Security benefit may be taxed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The net effect of these rules is that, as your “other income” rises, then your
tax rate can rise proportionally.  So while the IRS frames it as a taxation on
your Social Security benefits, it’s mathematially equivalent to an increase
in your marginal tax rate.  For example, if you are married and your provisional
income is above $44,000, then your tax rate may be 85% higher than you think it
is because 85% more of your total income will be taxed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;for-math-nerds-click-to-showhide&quot;&gt;For Math Nerds &lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0);&quot; class=&quot;toggle&quot; onclick=&quot;toggle('#math')&quot;&gt;click to show/hide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;math&quot; class=&quot;hidden&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The graph in the previous section was generated by calculating the taxable income
and applying that to the income tax brackets to figure out the actual marginal
tax rates.  Here is the math that is used to calculate the taxable income.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, provisional income is defined as half of social security
income plus “other” income,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;income_prov = income_ss/2 + income_other
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Half of the provisional income above the first threshold (single = $25k,
married = $32k) is taxable,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;income_taxable = income_other +
                 max(0, 0.5(income_prov - threshold_1))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;max()&lt;/code&gt; constraint makes sure anything below the threshold is not subtracted
from &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;income_other&lt;/code&gt;.  Likewise, adding in the second threshold (single = $34k,
married = $44k), 35% of income above that threshold is added to the 50% above the
first threshold (for a total of 85% above both thresholds),&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;income_taxable = income_other +
                 max(0, 0.50(income_prov - threshold_1)) +
                 max(0, 0.35(income_prov - threshold_2))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;But we also need to add in the constraint that no more than 85% of social security
is taxed.  This gives us a unified equation to calculate taxable income,&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;income_taxable = income_other +
                 min(0.85*income_ss,
                     max(0, 0.50(income_prov - threshold_1)) +
                     max(0, 0.35(income_prov - threshold_2)))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interactive-plot&quot;&gt;Interactive Plot&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is all pretty abstract so let’s plot what the tax brackets looks like
versus income levels for a married couple in 2017 with social security income of
&lt;span class=&quot;ss-income&quot;&gt;$50,000&lt;/span&gt;.  Move the social income slider below
the graph to see how it affects the tax brackets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;puppy&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you are seeing a puppy image below, then you are missing out on the
  amazingly excellent interactive content on the site.
  Click on the puppy to go to the website post in a browser
  to see what you are missing.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;.&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.randomdoggiegenerator.com/randomdoggie.php&quot; alt=&quot;puppy&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;taxBracketWithSS&quot; class=&quot;chart&quot;&gt;
    &lt;svg&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social Security Income (&lt;span class=&quot;ss-income&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;ss-income-slider&quot; class=&quot;slider&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
  .chart {
    clear: both;
  }
  .chart, svg {
    height: 360px;
  }
  .slider {
    width: 90%;
  }
  .nvd3 path.nv-line {
    stroke-width: 2.5px;
  }
  .nv-series-1 .hover {
    display: none;
  }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
  d3.select('#puppy').remove();

  var salaryInc = 1000;
  var maxSalary = 250000;
  var deduction = 23300;
  var ssIncome = 50000;
  var ss50 = 32000;
  var ss85 = 44000;
  var maxBenefit = Math.round(2687*12*2*1.32/1000)*1000;

  var taxLevels = [0, deduction, 18650+deduction, 75900+deduction,
    153100+deduction, 233350 + deduction, 416700+deduction, 470700 + deduction, maxSalary*2];
  var taxBrackets = [0, 0.1, 0.15, 0.25, 0.28, 0.33, 0.35, 0.396];
  var salaryTicks = [];

  function taxBracket(income) {
    var i = 1;
    while (income &gt;= taxLevels[i]) {
      i++
    }
    return taxBrackets[i-1];
  }

  function totalIncomeFor(incomeTaxable, incomeSS) {
      var f1 = incomeTaxable + incomeSS;
      var f2 = (incomeTaxable + 1.25*incomeSS + 0.5*ss50) / 1.5;
      var f3 = (incomeTaxable + 1.425*incomeSS + 0.5*ss50 + 0.35*ss85) / 1.85;
      return Math.max(incomeTaxable+0.15*incomeSS, Math.min(f1, f2, f3))
  }

  function taxRate() {
    var marginalTax = [];
    var prevTaxable = 0;
    var prevSalary = 0;
    var taxIdx = 0;
    var maxTaxableSS = ssIncome * 0.85;

    var incomeTicks = Array.from({length: maxSalary/salaryInc}, (e, k) =&gt; (k+1)*salaryInc);
    var taxVertices = taxLevels.map(function(e) { return Math.ceil(totalIncomeFor(e, ssIncome)) });
    var ssCap50 = Math.floor((1.1*ssIncome + 0.5*ss50) / 0.5);
    var ssCap85 = Math.floor((1.275*ssIncome + 0.5*ss50 + 0.35*ss85) / 0.85);
    var ssVertices = [ssIncome, ss50 + ssIncome/2 + 1, ss85 + ssIncome/2 + 1, ssCap50, ssCap85, ssCap85+1];

    salaryTicks =
      incomeTicks.concat(taxVertices, taxVertices.map((e) =&gt; (e-1)),
                         ssVertices, ssVertices.map((e) =&gt; (e+1)))
        .sort((a,b)=&gt;(a-b))
        .filter(function(el,i,a){return i==a.indexOf(el);});

    return salaryTicks.filter((e,i) =&gt; e &gt;= ssIncome).map(function(salary) {
      var income = salary - ssIncome;
      var provisional = income + ssIncome * 0.5;
      var taxableSS =
        Math.max(0, (provisional - ss50) * 0.50) +
        Math.max(0, (provisional - ss85) * 0.35);
      var taxable = income + Math.min(maxTaxableSS, taxableSS);
      var percent = taxBracket(taxable) * (taxable - prevTaxable) / (salary - prevSalary);
      prevTaxable = taxable;
      prevSalary = salary;

      return [salary,percent];
    });
  }

  function updateData() {
    var marginalTaxXY = taxRate();
    var data = [
    {
      name: 'Other Income',
      xy: marginalTaxXY,
      color: '#20aa20'
    },
    {
      name: 'Social Security',
      xy: [[0,0], [ssIncome, 0]],
      color: '#aa2020',
      width: 5
    },
    {
      name: 'Tax Free',
      xy: [[ssIncome,1.0], [totalIncomeFor(deduction, ssIncome), 1.0]],
      color: '#ffeeaa',
      width: 5,
      area: true
    },
    ];
    d3.selectAll(&quot;.ss-income&quot;).text(d3.format(&quot;$,f&quot;)(ssIncome))
    return d3.select('#taxBracketWithSS svg').datum(chartifyData(data));
  }
  var marginalTaxData = updateData();

  function newChart(chartData, interactive) {

    var aChart = nv.models.lineChart()
                  .interactive(interactive)
                  .useInteractiveGuideline(interactive)
                  .showLegend(true)
                  .showYAxis(true)
                  .showXAxis(true);

    aChart.xAxis
        .axisLabel('Total Income ($)')
        .tickFormat(d3.format('$,f'))
        .showMaxMin(false);

    aChart.yAxis     //Chart y-axis settings
        .axisLabel('Marginal Tax Rate')
        .tickFormat(d3.format('.0%'))
        .showMaxMin(false);

    aChart.xDomain([0.00, maxSalary]);
    aChart.yDomain([-0.01, 0.50]);

    chartData.call(aChart);

    //Update the chart when window resizes.
    nv.utils.windowResize(function() {
      aChart.update();
    });

    aChart.interactiveLayer.tooltip.contentGenerator(function (d) {
      var income = d.value;
      var taxRate = d.series[0].value;

      return &quot;Total Income: &lt;b&gt;&quot; + d3.format(&quot;$,f&quot;)(income) + &quot;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&quot; +
          &quot;SS Income: &lt;b&gt;&quot; + d3.format(&quot;$,f&quot;)(ssIncome) + &quot;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&quot; +
          &quot;Other Income: &lt;b&gt;&quot; + d3.format(&quot;$,f&quot;)(income-ssIncome) + &quot;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&quot; +
          &quot;Marginal Tax Rate: &lt;b&gt;&quot; + d3.format(&quot;.4p&quot;)(taxRate) + &quot;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&quot;;
    });

    return aChart;
  }

  function chartifyData(data) {
    //Line chart data should be sent as an array of series objects.
    return data.map(function(obj) {
      return {
        values: obj.xy.map(function(el) { return {x: el[0], y: el[1]} }),
        key: obj.name,
        color: obj.color,
        area: obj.area ? true : false,
        disabled: obj.disabled ? true : false
      }
    });
  }

  rothChart = newChart(marginalTaxData, true);
  nv.addGraph(rothChart);

  d3.select('#ss-income-slider').call(d3.slider().axis(d3.svg.axis().ticks(11)).min(0).max(maxBenefit).step(1000).value(ssIncome).on(&quot;slide&quot;, function(evt, ssi) {
    salaryInc = 100000;
    ssIncome = ssi;
    updateData().call(rothChart);
  }).on(&quot;slideend&quot;, function(evt, ssi) {
    salaryInc = 1000;
    ssIncome = ssi;
    updateData().call(rothChart);
  }));

&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;observations&quot;&gt;Observations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you move the Social Security income slider, you may notice the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Social Security = $0&lt;/strong&gt; - with no Social Security, your tax brackets are
  just the normal stair-step brackets that we are all used to hearing about.
  The larger your income, the more your marginal tax rate is.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SS &amp;gt; $8,000&lt;/strong&gt; a “new” tax bracket of 27.75% appears and gets wider as your
  income increases.  This is due to the 15% tax bracket being increased by 85%
  as your provisional income goes above the 2nd threshold.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SS ≈ $17,000&lt;/strong&gt; at approximately $17,000 the 10% tax bracket effectively
  disappears!  That is due to the fact that 10% bracket is increased by 50% to 15%
  because your provisional income is between the 1st and 2nd thresholds.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SS ≈ $47,000&lt;/strong&gt; a crazy new 46.25% tax bracket appears and represents the
  25% tax bracket being increased by 85%.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SS ≈ $53,000&lt;/strong&gt; the 15% tax bracket becomes extinct if you are lucky enough
  to get this much Social Security income (for a married couple).  In other words,
  beyond the tax-free zone of deductions and exemptions, the first tax bracket
  you hit will actually be an 18.5% tax bracket (10% increased by 85%).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increasing income reduces the size of the tax-free zone.  The tax-free zone
  represents the standard deduction and personal exemptions.  This is effectively
  decreased because it is absorbed in the taxable portion of the social security
  income.  So even though it’s not technically decreased, mathematically the
  amount of untaxed income above and beyond Social Security decreases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;implications&quot;&gt;Implications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The effects of Social Security taxation can significantly impact how you save
for retirement and affects the Roth vs Traditional account tradeoff.
That’s why I decided to write this article before writing Part 2 of the
&lt;a href=&quot;/to-roth-or-not-to-roth-part-1/&quot;&gt;Roth or Not to Roth&lt;/a&gt; series.
The basic implication is that your future tax rate not be what you think it will
be (even without changes to the current tax code).
Given that your tax rate could very well be higher than you think, this could
push you to use a Roth account more often than you do currently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s not a single solution for all cases, but let’s break it down a little
for different levels of Social Security income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SS = $17,000&lt;/strong&gt;, at this level you still have $23,300 of untaxed “other”
  income beyond
  SS so you would ideally like to defer income that fills that tax-free zone.  But above
  this, your first tax bracket is effectively 15%.  If your current tax bracket
  is 15%, you might want to consider saving to a Roth account at the point you think
  your Traditional accounts will generate $23,300 of income.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SS = $47,000&lt;/strong&gt;, for this higher level you still have $18,367 of untaxed
  “other” income to play with.
  Beyond that tax rates increase pretty quickly into the 18.5% and
  27.75% brackets.  If you’re in the 15% tax bracket now, you should consider
  using Roth accounts to the extent that your future other income sources are
  above $20,000.
  If you’re in the 25% tax bracket you should consider using Roth accounts to
  the extent that your future other income sources are above $28,000.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SS = $53,000&lt;/strong&gt;, as your SS benefit increases to this higher level,
  the amount of “other” income is tax-free down to about $17,000.
  Above that your lowest tax rate is above 18.5%, so if you are currently in
  the 15% bracket, the Roth option is best beyond the point where you have
  $17,000 of other income.  If you’re currently in the 25% tax bracket,
  consider using Roth when your future income from taxable sources goes above $27,000.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you retire early (before taking any SS), then your tax brackets won’t
  be affected until you start taking SS.  So plan on using the existing unaltered
  tax brackets for your tax planning in the time before you start taking
  Social Security.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The general upshot of all of this is that, if you are not using
Roth accounts for retirement savings, you might want to take another look at that
decision in light of how your Social Security benefits affect your future tax rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;related&quot;&gt;Related&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/to-roth-or-not-to-roth-part-1/&quot;&gt;To Roth or Not to Roth? - Part 1, The Ideal World&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
          <link>http://www.moneycle.com/how-social-security-messes-with-your-tax-brackets/</link>
        
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.moneycle.com/how-social-security-messes-with-your-tax-brackets/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>To Roth or Not to Roth? - Part 1, The Ideal World</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Most often when you see an article discussing whether to choose a Roth
over a Traditional option (401k/403b/IRA), the decision is stated as a comparison
between current and future tax rates.  While that’s mostly correct advice,
it fails to recognize that future withdrawals tend to occur across &lt;em&gt;multiple&lt;/em&gt;
tax brackets while current contributions tend to be in a single tax bracket.
I first became aware of the concept of filling in lower tax brackets from an
&lt;a href=&quot;https://thefinancebuff.com/case-against-roth-401k.html&quot;&gt;excellent piece written by The Finance Buff&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this first of two articles, I take a look at an ideal-world example that
explores the concept of how much should go towards a Roth versus a Traditional
option.  In the second article, I will take a look at some more real-world
cases that should give more concrete advice on how to determine how much to
contribute to each option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;basics-of-roth-vs-traditional&quot;&gt;Basics of Roth vs Traditional&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, let’s discuss the basic differences between the Roth and Traditional
options.  The most important difference between the two options is &lt;strong&gt;when&lt;/strong&gt; you are taxed.
Roth options are taxed now in that you fund them with after-tax dollars and you are not
taxed again when you withdrawal the funds.  Traditional options
are taxed later, so you deduct your contributions from your taxes now and pay
income taxes later when you make withdrawals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to maximize how much money you keep, the basic tradeoff becomes
one of shifting the taxes to the point in time when you have the lower tax rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the tax rates are equal now and in the future, then mathematically the amount
you end up with is identical after the taxes are accounted for.  However, in this
case I recommend using the Roth option primarily because the Roth has fewer
requirements on the distribution of funds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-tradeoff&quot;&gt;The Tradeoff&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When deciding how much money to allocate to a Roth, the basic goal is to allocate
funds to the Roth that will be taxed at the same rate or higher in
the future.  Conversely, all funds that will fall into lower tax brackets in the
future should be allocated to the Traditional option now.
This last part is where most people fail to consider the whole picture.
Just because you may be in the same or even higher tax brackets
in the future does NOT mean that some of the funds won’t be taxed at a lower rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;filling-up-the-tax-brackets&quot;&gt;Filling Up The Tax Brackets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you make a contribution to a Traditional IRA/401k/403b today,
in most cases all of that contribution will be in your current income tax bracket.
Sometimes you might also cross over to the next lower tax-bracket when making a
contribution if you are near a tax boundary when you begin your contributions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in the future, when you start making withdrawals from your Traditional IRA,
your withdrawals start filling in the tax brackets from the bottom up.
I like to visualize this as pouring money into the income “funnel” as depicted below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
  .center {
    text-align: center;
  }
  .funnel {
    float: left;
    margin: 0.4em 1.5em 0.8em 0em;
  }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/roth_or_not-funnel.png&quot; alt=&quot;Money Funnel&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2016, for a married couple filing jointly, the personal exemption plus standard
deduction is $20,700 so that amount is taxed at 0% (which I think of as the 0% tax
bracket).  Then the 10% bracket swallows up the next $18,550 of income, and the
15% bracket gets the next $56,750, and so on.  I have made the tax brackets to
appear as funnel-shaped because the brackets get bigger as income increases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, most people will have other sources of income filling in the lower
tax brackets, and we will consider that case too.
But the key point is that future withdrawals fill in tax
brackets from the bottom up before reaching today’s marginal tax bracket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the goal of an investor should be to &lt;strong&gt;plan for today’s Traditional
contributions to fill up tomorrow’s lower tax brackets&lt;/strong&gt;, then
&lt;strong&gt;invest the remainder in the Roth option&lt;/strong&gt;.
That sounds easy on the surface, but the hard part is figuring out how
to translate that statement into actionable numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;saving-within-a-single-tax-bracket&quot;&gt;Saving within a Single Tax Bracket&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;funnel&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/roth_or_not-120-16.png&quot; alt=&quot;Earn 120, Save 16&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start by looking at a typical example where somebody has all of their
savings occur within a single marginal tax bracket.
Consider a married couple named Jon &amp;amp; Sally that makes a total income of $120,000
and saves a total of $16,000 to their retirement plans.  If that money
is saved in a Traditional retirement plan then they would have a
gross income (AGI) of $104,000.
With the standard deduction, the low-end of the 25% tax bracket occurs at $96,000
of gross income so the $104,000 puts them $8,000 above the lower threshold of
the 25% tax bracket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s further assume that they are saving all they can afford to and that the
$104,000 of income represents their current AND future day-to-day expenses.  This is
a bit of a stretch, but I would argue that most people’s spending habits don’t
change all that much when they transition into retirement.  You will probably be
spending more in some areas in less in others but basically your spending
profile won’t change by a drastic amount in retirement.
Mostly I’m just trying to get a baseline equation, so stick with me for now.
If that $104,000 of income represents what they need in the future (albeit in
today’s dollars),
that suggests that in the future their “livable income” would be roughly $8000
into the 25% tax bracket.  In the extreme case where this couple has no other sources of
retirement income, that would mean they would need about 96k/104k (92%) of their
withdrawals to occur in tax brackets below 25% and the remaining 8k/104k (8%)
would come out in the 25% tax bracket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you knew that your future funds would come out in the same tax bracket, then
those funds might as well go into a Roth account today.  So in this example,
the couple could contribute 8% to their Roth.  Mathematically,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;percent_to_roth = (livable_income - tax_threshold) / livable_income
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assigning variables,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;L = livable_income = current_income - max_savings
T = tax_threshold
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;then,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;percent_to_roth = (L - T) / L
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-income-sources&quot;&gt;Other Income sources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one assumption that is hard to ignore is that the couple has no other
income sources in retirement.  But almost everybody has at least one other
source of income such as Social Security or pensions, and many people will
have multiple sources of income.  So let’s adjust the math to account for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;funnel&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/roth_or_not-120-16-36.png&quot; alt=&quot;Earn 120, Save 16, Base 36&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Jon &amp;amp; Sally expect to receive other income in the form of social security
that will total $36,000/year in today’s dollars, then their savings don’t have
to provide the full $104,000 of income.  Their savings only have to fill the
funnel up between $36,000 and $104,000, which is a difference of $68,000.
So when they convert their nest egg to future
income, 8k/68k or about 12% of that future income is in the same tax bracket
they are saving in today.  That suggests that they
could save 12% today in a Roth because it would likely be in the same tax
bracket if deferred to the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modifying the first equation,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;percent_to_roth = (L - T) / (L - B)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;B = base income from &quot;other&quot; sources (in today's dollars)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowing what your future base income from “other” sources can be a difficult
thing to figure out.  But if you’re only expecting Social Security, I suggest
you start off with about 40% of your current income.  This is a &lt;strong&gt;very rough&lt;/strong&gt;
estimate based on the idea that, on average, people receive around 40% of their
income back in social security.  But you really should take a look at your
actual social security (or equivalent) statements to get an idea of how much
you’ll really get.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At what point does 100% of your total savings go towards a Roth?  Mathematically,
if &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;(L-T) &amp;gt; (L-B)&lt;/code&gt; the equation goes above 100%.  This simplifies to the
comparison of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;B &amp;gt; T&lt;/code&gt;.  So you should contribute everything to Roth when your
“base income” sources equal or exceed
your current lower tax threshold.  That makes sense because it means that
if you know that you will be at or above the current tax rate in the future
you might as well contribute everything to Roth today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s just modify the equation slightly to account for this scenario,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;percent_to_roth = min((L - T) / (L - B), 100%)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;saving-across-multiple-tax-brackets&quot;&gt;Saving Across Multiple Tax Brackets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;funnel&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/roth_or_not-120-30-36.png&quot; alt=&quot;Earn 120, Save 30, Base 36&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let’s consider the case where Jon &amp;amp; Sally, are able to save enough to cross
over into a lower tax bracket if the entire savings were deductible.  So consider
with the same $120,000 of income and a savings rate of $30,000 per year.
This suggests that they are able to live comfortably off of the remaining $90,000
of income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the bottom of the 25% tax bracket is at $96,000, Jon &amp;amp; Sally would then
be descending into the 15% marginal tax bracket.  Since we’re assuming that
the $90,000 of income represents their future income needs and $90,000 of income
would be marginally taxed at 15%, everything they save in the 25% tax bracket
should simply go to the Traditional savings option.  Then they would apply the
equation from earlier but only to the portion in the 15% tax bracket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the first $24,000 of savings goes into Traditional.  The remaining $6000 of
savings would follow the previous equation, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;(90000-39250)/(90000-36000)&lt;/code&gt; or
94% of $6000, that goes to Roth.  Notice that I’m using $39,250 as the low end
of the tax bracket because that’s where the 15% tax bracket bottoms out (for a
married couple using standard deductions).  Finishing the
math for this example, 94% of $6000 is &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;0.94*6000/30000&lt;/code&gt; or about 19% of the
overall savings that goes to Roth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mathematically, we can express the overall equation
for the dual-tax bracket case like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;percent_to_roth = everything in lowest tax bracket * previous equation
                = min((T1-L) / S, 100%) * min((L - T0) / (L - B), 100%)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;S = total amount saved
L = livable_income
T0 = tax bracket threshold below L
T1 = tax bracket threshold above L
B = future base income
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a plot of what Roth percentage looks like versus income levels
for a married couple&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; in 2016 with a savings rate of
&lt;span class=&quot;savings-rate&quot;&gt;12%&lt;/span&gt; and a future
base income equal to &lt;span class=&quot;base-percent&quot;&gt;40%&lt;/span&gt; of their current income
(move sliders below the graph to change percentages).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;percentRoth-graph&quot; class=&quot;chart&quot;&gt;
    &lt;svg&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Savings Rate as Percentage of Income (&lt;span class=&quot;savings-rate&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;savings-slider&quot; class=&quot;slider&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Base Income as Percentage of Income (&lt;span class=&quot;base-percent&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;base-slider&quot; class=&quot;slider&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
  .chart {
    clear: both;
  }
  .chart, svg {
    height: 360px;
  }
  .slider {
    width: 90%;
  }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
  var salaryInc = 1000;
  var maxsalary = 500000;
  var deduction = 20700;
  var basePercent = 0.4;
  var savePercent = 0.12;

  var taxLevels = [0, deduction, 18550+deduction, 75300+deduction,
    151900+deduction, 231450 + deduction, 413350+deduction, 466950 + deduction, maxsalary*2]
  var taxBrackets = [0, 0.1, 0.15, 0.25, 0.28, 0.33, 0.35, 0.396]

  function taxBracket(income) {
    var i = 1;
    while (income &gt;= taxLevels[i]) {
      i++
    }
    return taxBrackets[i-1];
  }

  function rothPercent(savePercent) {
    var percentRoth = [];
    tax0 = 0;
    tax1 = 1;
    for(var salary = salaryInc; salary &lt;= maxsalary; salary += salaryInc) {
      var savings = salary*savePercent;
      var x = salary - savings;
      var base = salary*basePercent;
      var savings = salary*savePercent;
      if (x &gt; taxLevels[tax1]) {
        tax0++;
        tax1++;
      }
      percent = Math.min((taxLevels[tax1]-x) / savings, 1.0) *
        (base &lt; x ? Math.min((x - taxLevels[tax0]) / (x - base), 1.0) : 1.0);

      // max allowed with catchup
      if (savings &gt; 48000) {
        percent = Math.min(percent*savings / 48000, 1.0);
      }

      percentRoth.push([salary, percent]);
    }
    return percentRoth;
  }

  function updateData() {
    var percentRothXY = rothPercent(savePercent);
    var data = [
    {
      name: 'Percent to Roth',
      xy: percentRothXY,
      color: '#aa2020'
    },
    ];
    d3.selectAll(&quot;.savings-rate&quot;).text('' + Math.round(savePercent*100) + '%')
    d3.selectAll(&quot;.base-percent&quot;).text('' + Math.round(basePercent*100) + '%')
    return d3.select('#percentRoth-graph svg').datum(chartifyData(data));
  }
  var percentRothData = updateData();

  function newChart(chartData, interactive) {

    var aChart = nv.models.lineChart()
                  .interactive(interactive)
                  .useInteractiveGuideline(interactive)
                  .showLegend(true)
                  .showYAxis(true)
                  .showXAxis(true);

    aChart.xAxis
        .axisLabel('Total Income ($)')
        .tickFormat(d3.format('$f'))
        .showMaxMin(false);
    aChart.xAxis.scale(d3.scale.log());

    aChart.yAxis     //Chart y-axis settings
        .axisLabel('Percent of Qualified Savings to Roth')
        .tickFormat(d3.format('.0%'))
        .showMaxMin(false);

    aChart.xDomain([0.00, maxsalary]);
    aChart.yDomain([0, 1]);

    chartData.call(aChart);

    //Update the chart when window resizes.
    nv.utils.windowResize(function() {
      aChart.update();
    });

    aChart.interactiveLayer.tooltip.contentGenerator(function (d) {
      var income = d.value;
      var percentToRoth = d.series[0].value;
      var savings = income*savePercent;
      var maxQual = Math.min(48000, savings);

      var html = &quot;Current Income: &lt;b&gt;&quot; + d3.format(&quot;$f&quot;)(income) + &quot;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&quot;;
      html += &quot;Tax Bracket: &lt;b&gt;&quot; + d3.format(&quot;.3p&quot;)(taxBracket(income)) + &quot;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&quot;;
      html += &quot;Future Base Income: &lt;b&gt;&quot; + d3.format(&quot;$f&quot;)(income*basePercent) + &quot;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&quot;;
      html += &quot;Savings Rate: &lt;b&gt;&quot; + d3.format(&quot;.2p&quot;)(savePercent) + &quot;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&quot;;
      html += &quot;Savings Amount: &lt;b&gt;&quot; + d3.format(&quot;$f&quot;)(savings) + &quot;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&quot;;
      html += &quot;Qualified Savings: &lt;b&gt;&quot; + d3.format(&quot;$f&quot;)(maxQual) + &quot;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&quot;;
      html += &quot;Percent to Roth: &lt;b&gt;&quot; + d3.format(&quot;.2p&quot;)(percentToRoth) + &quot;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&quot;;
      html += &quot;Amount to Roth: &lt;b&gt;&quot; + d3.format(&quot;$f&quot;)(maxQual * percentToRoth) + &quot;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&quot;;

      return html;
    });

    return aChart;
  }

  function chartifyData(data) {
    //Line chart data should be sent as an array of series objects.
    return data.map(function(obj) {
      return {
        values: transformXY(obj.xy),
        key: obj.name,
        color: obj.color,
        disabled: obj.disabled ? true : false
      }
    });
  }

  function transformXY(data) {
    var result = [];
    for (i = 0; i &lt; data.length; i++) {
      var point = data[i];
      result.push({x: point[0], y: point[1]});
    }
    return result;
  }

  rothChart = newChart(percentRothData, true);
  nv.addGraph(rothChart);

  d3.select('#savings-slider').call(d3.slider().axis(d3.svg.axis().ticks(11)).min(1).max(99).step(1).value(savePercent*100).on(&quot;slide&quot;, function(evt, percent) {
    salaryInc = 3000;
    savePercent = percent / 100;
    updateData().call(rothChart);
  }).on(&quot;slideend&quot;, function(evt, percent) {
    salaryInc = 1000;
    savePercent = percent / 100;
    updateData().call(rothChart);
  }));


  d3.select('#base-slider').call(d3.slider().axis(d3.svg.axis().ticks(11)).min(0).max(100).step(1).value(basePercent*100).on(&quot;slide&quot;, function(evt, percent) {
    salaryInc = 3000;
    basePercent = percent / 100;
    updateData().call(rothChart);
  }).on(&quot;slideend&quot;, function(evt, percent) {
    salaryInc = 1000;
    basePercent = percent / 100;
    updateData().call(rothChart);
  }));
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;insights&quot;&gt;Insights&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at the plot of Roth percent versus income and playing with the sliders gives
a few of insights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Roth savings rate drops off rapidly right above each tax bracket.  This is due
  to the fact that your savings at those income levels can quickly push
  you into a lower tax bracket.   So if you save enough to cross over into
  a lower tax bracket, all of the savings in the
  higher tax brackets would tend to go towards the Traditional option, while
  most of the savings that cross-over into lower tax brackets would go towards
  the Roth option.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Roth savings rates tend to peak just below the tax bracket boundaries.
  That’s because you are as far away as you can be from the lower edge of the
  tax bracket which means that a higher percentage of your retirement income
  is likely to be in the same tax bracket (or higher) as you are in now.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increases to future income pushes the entire curve up.  This means that the more
  you expect to earn from other sources such as social security and pensions,
  the closer your retirement tax bracket will be to your current tax bracket
  so you would tend to want to save more to a Roth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-you-assume-you-make-me-read-part-2&quot;&gt;When You Assume, You Make Me Read Part 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this analysis is interesting and moving the sliders around is fun, there
are many assumptions that make it not particularly useful.  Here are some of
the more egregious assumptions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The model assumes that the investor will retire exactly when they have enough
  to retire without considering the probability that most people will either have
  too little or too much at the time of retirement.  Assuming you work a little
  past the point of being financially independent, then you would probably want to
  allocate a little more to the Roth option because the extra savings in the
  Traditional option would fill up the lower tax brackets in the future.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Returns on the invested funds and inflation were both ignored.  If your
  investments beat inflation then the amount you have at retirement
  to fill in lower tax brackets would be larger.
  This also suggests allocating more funds to Roths.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Employer matches were completely ignored.  Since those matching funds would
  normally be in before-tax dollars, this would tend to suggest higher allocations
  towards the Roth option than shown in this analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Part 2 I’m going to change the perspective of the analysis from mostly theoretical
to be a bit more practical.  Also, instead of focusing how much to put
in a &lt;strong&gt;Roth&lt;/strong&gt;, I will change the perspective slightly to examine how much total
money you should save in your &lt;strong&gt;Traditional&lt;/strong&gt; savings option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For the plot, I capped the qualified contribution at $48,000 because each person in a couple over 50 can contribute a max of $24,000 to qualified accounts. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 19 Oct 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        
          <link>http://www.moneycle.com/to-roth-or-not-to-roth-part-1/</link>
        
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.moneycle.com/to-roth-or-not-to-roth-part-1/</guid>
        
        <category>investing</category>
        
        <category>spending</category>
        
        <category>other</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Radioactive Half-Life of Expenses</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In the world of science, the term “half-life” is used to describe &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Half-life&quot;&gt;“the time required
for a quantity to reduce to half its initial value”&lt;/a&gt;.
One common application of this concept is for radioactive decay and the half-life
is a useful measure in science to characterize how quickly something will decay over
time.  Probably the most common application of this concept is used in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radiocarbon_dating&quot;&gt;carbon dating&lt;/a&gt; which allows scientists
to fairly accurately estimate the age of objects containing radiocarbon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It occurred to me that portfolio expenses can have a similar effect as radioactive
decay.  Namely, the higher the expense, the faster your portfolio will reduce to
half of the value it would have achieved without the expense.  Let’s take a look
at the math of compounding returns to see how quickly a portfolio’s value decays
with expenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lump-sum-investment&quot;&gt;Lump-Sum Investment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the case of investing a lump-sum amount.  The compounded return
of the investment with a rate of return &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;r&lt;/code&gt;, after &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;N&lt;/code&gt; years is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;final_value = initial_value * (1 + r)^N
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, without any expenses eating into the return, the ratio of the final_value to
the initial value represents how much your portfolio would grow without expenses&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;growth_without_expenses = final_value / initial_value
                        = (1 + r)^N
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now consider a expense or expense of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;e&lt;/code&gt; being subtracted off of that return every year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;final_value = initial_value * [(1 + r)(1 - e)]^N
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the growth is smaller,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;growth_with_expenses = final_value / initial_value
                     = [(1 + r)(1 - e)]^N
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to compute the half-life of these expenses, we want to know when the the growth
with expenses is half of the growth without those expenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;growth_with_expenses / growth_without_expenses = 1/2
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;or,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;[(1 + r)(1 - e)]^N / (1 + r)^N = 0.5
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solving for &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;N&lt;/code&gt; gives us the half-life as a function of expenses,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;N = log(0.5) / log(1-e)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it!  We now have an equation that directly computes how many years it takes
for a given expense to cut your total portfolio in half.  Notice that for a lump-sum
investment, it doesn’t matter how big your return is, it only matters what
the expense is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the following plot I show the half-life as well as the 3/4-life and 7/8-life.
Losing half of your portfolio is terrible, but even losing a quarter or eighth
can be painful, especially when we’re talking about a portfolio that might
need to grow to over $1 million to support a comfortable retirement.  Do you want
to pay $125,000 (1/8 of $1M) or more in expenses over the course of your investment life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;halfLife-graph&quot; class=&quot;chart&quot;&gt;
    &lt;svg&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
  .chart {
    clear: both;
  }
  .chart, svg {
    height: 360px;
  }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
  var expenseInc = 0.0005;
  var maxExpense = 0.03;
  var halfLifeXY = [];
  var quarterLifeXY = [];
  var eighthLifeXY = [];
  for(var w = expenseInc; w &lt;= maxExpense; w += expenseInc) {
    w = Math.round(w*10000)/10000;
    halfLifeXY.push([w, Math.log(0.5)/Math.log(1-w)]);
    quarterLifeXY.push([w, Math.log(0.75)/Math.log(1-w)]);
    eighthLifeXY.push([w, Math.log(0.875)/Math.log(1-w)]);
  }

  var halfLifeData = [
  {
    name: 'Half-Life',
    xy: halfLifeXY,
    color: '#aa2020'
  },
  {
    name: '3/4-Life',
    xy: quarterLifeXY,
    color: '#2020aa'
  },
  {
    name: '7/8-Life',
    xy: eighthLifeXY,
    color: '#20aa20'
  },
  ];

  function newChart(data, selector, interactive) {

    var aChart = nv.models.lineChart()
                  .interactive(interactive)
                  .useInteractiveGuideline(interactive)
                  .showLegend(true)
                  .showYAxis(true)
                  .showXAxis(true);

    aChart.xAxis
        .axisLabel('Expense (%)')
        .tickFormat(d3.format('.3p'))
        .showMaxMin(false);

    aChart.yAxis     //Chart y-axis settings
        .axisLabel('Half-Life (years)')
        .tickFormat(d3.format('.1f'))
        .showMaxMin(false);

    aChart.xDomain([0.00, maxExpense]);
    aChart.yDomain([0, 105]);

    var chartData = chartifyData(data);

    d3.select(selector)
        .datum(chartData)
        .call(aChart);

    //Update the chart when window resizes.
    nv.utils.windowResize(function() {
      aChart.update();
    });

    return aChart;
  }

  function chartifyData(data) {
    //Line chart data should be sent as an array of series objects.
    return data.map(function(obj) {
      return {
        values: transformXY(obj.xy),
        key: obj.name,
        color: obj.color,
        disabled: obj.disabled ? true : false
      }
    });
  }

  function transformXY(data) {
    var result = [];
    for (i = 0; i &lt; data.length; i++) {
      var point = data[i];
      result.push({x: point[0], y: point[1]});
    }
    return result;
  }

  nv.addGraph(newChart(halfLifeData, '#halfLife-graph svg', true));

&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me walk you through some key points from the graph above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You want your half-life number to be very large which means you want to be as
  close to zero expenses as possible.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.forbes.com/sites/rickferri/2013/05/27/the-heavy-toll-of-investment-expenses/#3875f0443ebc&quot;&gt;According to Morningstar&lt;/a&gt;, in 2013 the “typical” managed fund of stocks has a expense of 1.2%.  Such a expense would eat up
  half of your gains in 57 years which seems like a long time.  But you would lose
  an eighth of your portfolio value in just 11 years.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It gets even worse if you consider the “all-in” costs of actively managed funds.
  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cfapubs.org/doi/sum/10.2469/faj.v70.n1.1&quot;&gt;John Bogle suggests&lt;/a&gt; that there are
  many unaccounted costs in an actively managed fund that can increase the actual
  “all-in” expense to something more like 2.21%.  The main unaccounted for costs are
  “transaction costs, cash drag, and sales loads”.  These extra costs are hard to
  quantify but they effectively can reduce your expected return beyond the published
  expenses.
  In any case, if you believe Bogle’s hypothesis, then an actively managed fund with
  a 2.2% expense has a half-life of only 31 years and a 7/8-life of just 6 years!
  That means that you could be losing as much as an eighth of your portfolio every
  6 years if you invest in actively-managed funds.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Contrast this with a leading low-cost index fund from Vanguard like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://personal.vanguard.com/us/funds/snapshot?FundId=0585&amp;amp;FundIntExt=INT&quot;&gt;Total Stock Market Index&lt;/a&gt; fund (VTSAX)
  which has an expense ratio of 0.05%.  This expense would take 1385 years to lose half
  it’s value or 267 years to lose an eighth.  To put it another way, after 40 years
  an expense of 0.05% would only take 2.0% off of your portfolio value which is less
  than some funds would cost in a single year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By now, just about everybody knows that low-cost funds are a great way to invest and maximize
returns.
Putting these expenses in terms of how they eat away at your portfolio can be eye-opening.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 25 Aug 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        
          <link>http://www.moneycle.com/radioactive-half-life-of-expenses/</link>
        
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.moneycle.com/radioactive-half-life-of-expenses/</guid>
        
        <category>investing</category>
        
        <category>spending</category>
        
        <category>other</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Super-Simple Virtual-Buffer Withdrawal Strategy</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;While the &lt;a href=&quot;/the-30-30-withdrawal-strategy/&quot;&gt;30-30 Withdrawal Strategy&lt;/a&gt; is a
nice clean method for withdrawing money from your portfolio,
it does require you to keep track of a buffer which
drives the calculation for your withdrawal amount every year.
I felt like there should be a way to calculate the withdrawal in terms of only
your current withdrawal amount and your current portfolio value thus alleviating
the need to keep track of a separate spending buffer.
After playing with the math, it turns out there is a pretty simple formula
that achieves this goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-bit-of-math&quot;&gt;A Bit of Math&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amount that is initially spent from your portfolio is determined directly
by multiplying your withdrawal rate by your portfolio value.  Using the same
variables as the &lt;a href=&quot;/safe-withdrawal-rates-for-vampires/&quot;&gt;Safe Withdrawal Rates for Vampires&lt;/a&gt;
article,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;W = Pw
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;W = annual withdrawal amount
w = annual withdrawal rate
P = portfolio value
k = buffer size in years
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if we have a buffer of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;k&lt;/code&gt; years, then the total buffer size initially
is,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;initial buffer size = kW
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a year of spending from the buffer, it is reduced by the withdrawal amount,
&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;W&lt;/code&gt;.  So we are left with,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt; buffer after 1 year of spending = kW-W = W(k-1)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, we add back an amount equal to the new portfolio value times the
withdrawal rate to arrive at the new buffer size,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt; updated buffer value after 1 year = W(k-1) + Pw
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to compute the new withdrawal amount, we just divide this amount
by the size of the buffer in years (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;k&lt;/code&gt;),&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;new annual withdrawal amount = W(k-1)/k + Pw/k
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I prefer to think of my withdrawals as monthly, let’s rewrite this
in terms of monthly withdrawals,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;new monthly withdrawal amount = (W/12)(k-1)/k + Pw/12k
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;k&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;w&lt;/code&gt; are constant values, we now have a formula for computing
our new withdrawal amount from the current monthly withdrawal (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;W/12&lt;/code&gt;),
and the current portfolio value (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;P&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;example-using-30-30-numbers&quot;&gt;Example Using 30-30 Numbers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s put some numbers to this to make it less abstract.  Start with a
portfolio of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;P = $720,000&lt;/code&gt; and go with the 30-30 Withdrawal Strategy numbers
for buffer size (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;k = 2.5 years&lt;/code&gt;), and withdrawal rate (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;w = 3.33%&lt;/code&gt;).
For these values, the initial monthly withdrawal is simply,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Pw/12 = $720000*0.0333/12 = $2000/month
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want, you can set aside your buffer of 2.5 years ($60,000) in a safe place.
But the beauty of this strategy is that you don’t have to do so.  You can also
just assume that your buffer is fully invested within the bond portion of your
portfolio; it’s up to you.  This is why I call it a “virtual” buffer because
you get the advantages the buffer gives you without having to keep track of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let’s assume a year has passed and it has been a good year and the portfolio
has gone up to $765,000.  Now your monthly withdrawal amount is computed as,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;(W/12)(k-1)/k + Pw/12k = $2000(1.5/2.5) + $765000*.03333/(12*2.5))
                       = $2000 * 0.6 + $765000/900
                       = $1200 + $850
                       = $2050
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So even though the portfolio increased by 6.25% (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;765000/720000&lt;/code&gt;), the monthly
spending only went up 2.5% (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;2050/2000&lt;/code&gt;) due to the virtual 2.5-year buffering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, look how simple the calculation is every year.  In this example, multiplying
your current income by 0.6, divide your portfolio by 900, and add those 2 numbers
together.  Pretty simple right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;making-it-even-simpler&quot;&gt;Making it Even Simpler&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As easy as this calculation is, I couldn’t help but noticing that dividing by
900 is a little awkward.  What if we changed the buffer size so that we ended
up dividing by 1000?  If we can divide by 1000 then the calculation can almost
be done in your head.  To state this mathematically, we want,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;12k/w = 1000
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the annual withdrawal rate is fixed, then we solve for the buffer size to get,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;k = 1000w/12
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Substituting this back into our withdrawal equation,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;new monthly withdrawal amount = (W/12)(1-0.012/w) + P/1000
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Revisiting the first example with a portfolio of $720,000 and a withdrawal
rate of 3.333%, the first year withdrawal is still $2000/monthly because the
withdrawal rate is the same.  After the first year with a new portfolio value
of $765,000, the new monthly withdrawal now becomes,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;(W/12)(1-0.012/w) + P/1000 = $2000(1-0.012/0.03333) + $765000/1000
                           = $2000 * 0.64 + $765000/1000
                           = $1280 + $765
                           = $2045
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, you can see that the slightly modified equation only decreased the income by
$5/month.  This decrease is due to a slightly larger buffer (2.778 years vs 2.5 years)
which means that the market gyrations are smoothed a little more than before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-super-simple-virtual-buffer-withdrawal-formula&quot;&gt;The Super-Simple Virtual-Buffer Withdrawal Formula&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To summarize all the above math, in the first year of withdrawals, you withdrawal
from your portfolio by simply multiplying your portfolio value by your withdrawal
rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;initial monthly withdrawal = Pw/12
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, after each year you compute your new withdrawal amount with this
super-simple formula.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;new monthly withdrawal = M * beta + P/1000
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;M = previous monthly withdrawal
beta = monthly withdrawal multiplier = 1 - 1.2%/w
w = annual withdrawal rate
P = current portfolio value
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The graph below shows the monthly withdrawal multiplier as a function of
annual withdrawal rate.  If you hover over the chart you will see other
information including a “Sample Allocation” which shows how you might need
to allocate more to stocks as your withdrawal rate goes up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;beta-graph&quot; class=&quot;chart&quot;&gt;
    &lt;svg&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
  .chart {
    clear: both;
  }
  .chart, svg {
    height: 360px;
  }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
  var betaXY = [];
  for(var w = 0.012; w &lt; 0.0451; w += 0.0001) {
    w = Math.round(w*10000)/10000;
    betaXY.push([w, 1-0.012/w]);
  }

  var betaData = [
    {
      name: 'Monthly Withdrawal Multiplier',
      xy: betaXY,
      color: '#2020aa'
    },
  ];

  function newChart(data, selector, interactive) {

    var aChart = nv.models.lineChart()
                  .interactive(interactive)
                  .useInteractiveGuideline(interactive)
                  .showLegend(true)
                  .showYAxis(true)
                  .showXAxis(true);

    aChart.xAxis
        .axisLabel('Annual Withdrawal Rate')
        .tickFormat(d3.format('.3p'))
        .showMaxMin(false);

    aChart.yAxis     //Chart y-axis settings
        .axisLabel('Monthly Withdrawal Multiplier')
        .tickFormat(d3.format('.3f'))
        .showMaxMin(false);

    aChart.xDomain([0.012, 0.045]);
    aChart.yDomain([0, 0.8]);

    var inflation = 0.02;
    var stockRet = 0.08;
    var bondRet = 0.03;
    aChart.interactiveLayer.tooltip.contentGenerator(function (d) {
      var w = d.value;
      var beta = d.series[0].value;
      var k = 1000*w/12;
      var totalRet = (w + inflation)/(1-w*k);
      var stockPercent = Math.round(100*Math.min(1.0, (totalRet + bondRet*((k-1)*w-1))/(stockRet - bondRet)))/100;
      var bufferPercent = Math.round(100*Math.min(1-stockPercent, 2*w))/100;
      var bondPercent = Math.max(0, 1.0 - stockPercent - bufferPercent);

      var html = &quot;Annual Withdrawal Rate: &lt;b&gt;&quot; + d3.format(&quot;.3p&quot;)(w) + &quot;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&quot;;
      html += &quot;Monthly Withdrawal Multiplier: &lt;b&gt;&quot; + d3.format(&quot;.3f&quot;)(beta) + &quot;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&quot;;
      html += &quot;Virtual Buffer Size: &lt;b&gt;&quot; + d3.format(&quot;.2f&quot;)(k) + &quot; years&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&quot;;

      html += &quot;Sample Allocation:&lt;br/&gt;&quot;;
      html += &quot;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;stocks: &lt;b&gt;&quot; + d3.format(&quot;%&quot;)(stockPercent) + &quot;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&quot;;
      html += &quot;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;bonds: &lt;b&gt;&quot; + d3.format(&quot;%&quot;)(bondPercent) + &quot;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&quot;;
      html += &quot;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;buffer: &lt;b&gt;&quot; + d3.format(&quot;%&quot;)(bufferPercent) + &quot;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&quot;;
      return html;
    });

    var chartData = chartifyData(data);

    d3.select(selector)
        .datum(chartData)
        .call(aChart);

    //Update the chart when window resizes.
    nv.utils.windowResize(function() {
      aChart.update();
    });

    return aChart;
  }

  function chartifyData(data) {
    //Line chart data should be sent as an array of series objects.
    return data.map(function(obj) {
      return {
        values: transformXY(obj.xy),
        key: obj.name,
        color: obj.color,
        disabled: obj.disabled ? true : false
      }
    });
  }

  function transformXY(data) {
    var result = [];
    for (i = 0; i &lt; data.length; i++) {
      var point = data[i];
      result.push({x: point[0], y: point[1], stock: 0.99});
    }
    return result;
  }

  nv.addGraph(newChart(betaData, '#beta-graph svg', true));

&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sample-portfolios&quot;&gt;Sample Portfolios&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are a few possible portfolio types you could choose from depending on your
risk tolerance.  The Step-By-Step section that follows walks through a simple example
using the “moderate” strategy numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;annual withdrawal rate&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;monthly withdrawal multiplier&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;virtual buffer size&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;conservative&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2.40%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;0.5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2.00 yrs&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;moderate&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3.00%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;0.6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2.50 yrs&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;moderately aggressive&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3.33%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;0.64&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2.78 yrs&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;aggressive&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4.00%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;0.7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3.33 yrs&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-by-step&quot;&gt;Step-By-Step&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Implementing the Super-Simple Virtual-Buffer Withdrawal strategy is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Compute your initial monthly withdrawal from the equation &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Pw/12&lt;/code&gt;.
For example, with a $400,000 portfolio (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;P&lt;/code&gt;) and a 3% withdrawal rate (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;w&lt;/code&gt;),
your monthly withdrawal is,&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$400,000*0.03/12 = $1000&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Withdrawal from the portfolio for a full year using the last computed value.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the end of each year, compute your new monthly withdrawal rate using
the equation &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;M * beta + P/1000&lt;/code&gt;.  For example,
with a 3% withdrawal rate (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;w&lt;/code&gt;), your beta multiplier is &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;1 - 1.2%/3% = 0.6&lt;/code&gt;.
If your portfolio (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;P&lt;/code&gt;) has increased to $420,000 after the first year,
then your new withdrawal is,&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$1000*0.6 + $420000/1000 = $600 + $420 = $1020&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Go back to step 2 and repeat.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;nerd-alert&quot;&gt;Nerd Alert&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some readers may have noticed that the formula for this withdrawal strategy
looks an awful lot like an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exponential_smoothing&quot;&gt;exponential smoothed average&lt;/a&gt;.
If we rewrite the withdrawal formula like this,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;M(t) = (1-alpha) * M(t-1) + alpha * Pw/12
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;alpha = 1.2%/w
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;then you can see that it is indeed an exponential moving average of the
term &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Pw/12&lt;/code&gt;.  That term represents the annual withdrawal rate projected down
to the monthly level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For exponential smoothed averages, a smaller &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;alpha&lt;/code&gt; represents an average that has
a larger smoothing effect.  In the case of this withdrawal strategy,
the smaller &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;alpha&lt;/code&gt; corresponds to larger withdrawal rates which means that larger
withdrawal rates will have larger smoothing effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;parting-thoughts&quot;&gt;Parting Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Albert Einstein has been attributed with the saying that “everything should be made
as simple as possible, but not simpler”.  The super-simple virtual-buffer withdrawal
strategy is simple and requires no bookkeeping other than checking your portfolio
value once a year.  Is there a simpler strategy?  Yes, you could simply
take a constant value out without checking your portfolio balance.
But such a strategy could be risky since it ignores the possibility of a
declining portfolio balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The super-simple strategy also has flexibility which comes from the fact that
the buffer is “virtual”.  Whether or not you keep an actual buffer is up to you.
Generally it’s a good idea to keep a couple years or so of spending outside
of your investments so that you know it will be there when you need it.  But this
strategy doesn’t require you do so, it’s up to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;related&quot;&gt;Related&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/super-simple-virtual-buffer-withdrawal-strategy-revisited/&quot;&gt;Super-Simple Virtual-Buffer Withdrawal Strategy - Revisited&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/safe-withdrawal-rates-for-vampires/&quot;&gt;Safe Withdrawal Rates for Vampires&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/buffer-withdrawals-to-stabilize-income/&quot;&gt;Buffer Withdrawals to Stabilize Income&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/the-30-30-withdrawal-strategy/&quot;&gt;The 30-30 Withdrawal Strategy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        
          <link>http://www.moneycle.com/super-simple-virtual-buffer-withdrawal-strategy/</link>
        
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.moneycle.com/super-simple-virtual-buffer-withdrawal-strategy/</guid>
        
        <category>investing</category>
        
        <category>spending</category>
        
        <category>other</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Affordable Care Act May Increase Your Marginal Tax Rate</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If you retire before you are eligible for Medicare at age 65, then you
may find yourself buying health insurance through one of the Affordable Care Act
health exchanges.
Furthermore, if your taxable income falls below 4 times the
Federal Poverty Level (FPL), then you will qualify for a subsidy which
could pay for a nice chunk of your health insurance premium.
For 2016 the FPL is set at $11,770 for singles and $15,930 for couples, so
you could be eligible for a tax credit for incomes below $47,080 (single) or
$63,720 (couples).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does this have to do with marginal tax rates?  It turns out that the
subsidy is a tax credit which gradually decreases as your taxable income increases.
For example, if your &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.investopedia.com/terms/m/magi.asp&quot;&gt;modified adjusted gross income&lt;/a&gt;
(MAGI) is between 3 and 4
times the FPL ($47,790 to $63,720 for couples), then your tax credit decreases
by 9.56% for every extra dollar earned.  And even though it’s a credit and not
a tax, the effect of a decreasing credit is mathematically equivalent to a
tax because the end result is that you will have 9.56% less money in your
pocket for every dollar of increased income.  Adding that to the
marginal tax rate means that your &lt;strong&gt;effective&lt;/strong&gt; marginal tax rate is higher
if you’re in the income range where you receive a health care premium subsidy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s certainly not bad to receive the tax credit because that’s free money.
But it’s good to understand how this affects your tax rate so that you
can plan on how and when to take income from your portfolio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;marginal-tax-rates&quot;&gt;Marginal Tax Rates&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you pay your taxes, then you’re probably already well aware of the tax brackets,
from 10% all the way up to 39.6% for the highest earners.  This article is
focused on the 10% and 15% brackets because that’s where the ACA
credits occur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To keep things simple, I’m just going to consider the simple case of a married
couple using the standard deduction ($12,600 in 2016) and the the personal
exemptions ($4,050 in 2016) which means that the first $20,700 of adjusted
gross income is tax free.  The same issue applies to single filers, just at
a lower income level.  Here’s a graph of the marginal tax rates versus income
for joint filers in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;brackets&quot; class=&quot;chart&quot;&gt;
    &lt;svg&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you itemize deductions, this graph will shift to the right by the amount
that your deductions exceed the standard deduction ($12,600).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;marginal-effects-of-tax-credit-decreases&quot;&gt;Marginal Effects of Tax Credit Decreases&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The IRS publishes a table that is used to calculate how much to reduce your
ACA subsidy by comparing your income to the Federal Povery Level (FPL).
This table can be found in Table 2 of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.irs.gov/pub/irs-pdf/i8962.pdf&quot;&gt;instructions for Form 8962&lt;/a&gt;
which lists incomes levels from 100% through 400%.  For a married couple,
the FPL is $15,930, so 100% to 400% of FPL corresponds to incomes between
$15,930 and $63,720.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the IRS table publishes different values for each FPL percentage point,
I have computed the marginal tax effect for every 1%  of FPL ($159) between 100%
and 400% FPL to come up with the following graph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;acacredits&quot; class=&quot;chart&quot;&gt;
    &lt;svg&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s break down this chart by income ranges:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;$15,930 - 21,187 (100-133% FPL)&lt;/strong&gt; - in the lower range the premium subsidy is
 reduced by the smallest amount, 2.01%.  But many people in this range would be eligible
 for Medicaid and may choose to not buy insurance and thus may not be affected at all.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;$21,187 (133% FPL)&lt;/strong&gt; - there is a spike at this income level because there’s
 a jump in the subsidy reduction from 2.01% to 3.02%.  So as your income increases
 from 132% to 133% of FPL, your subsidy goes down by &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;133*.0302-132*.0201&lt;/code&gt; =
 136% ($217 more taxes for $159 increase in income).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;$21,187 - 47,790 (133-300% FPL)&lt;/strong&gt; - in this range the IRS table publishes an
 ever increasing subsidy reduction rate which translates to a gradually
 increasing marginal tax rate.  The jaggedness is due the rounding of the values
 in the IRS table.  The average effect on marginal tax rate across this range is
 &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;(300*.0956-133*.0302)/(300-133)&lt;/code&gt; = 14.8%.
 At it’s peak it approaches 18.5% for incomes right below 300% of FPL.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;$47,740 - 63,720 (300-400% FPL)&lt;/strong&gt; - this is the top range in which a subsidy
 is available and the reduction is a constant 9.56% across the entire range.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;$63,720 (400% FPL)&lt;/strong&gt; - technically there could be a huge spike (cliff) at this
 income level because when you make $63,720, you lose all remaining premium
 credits.  There could also be no spike if you choose the cheapest health care
 plan, in which case your premium subsidy may have already been exhausted
 at this income level.  I chose not to show it on the graph because it’s not a
 constant percentage for all situations but it’s important to be aware of this
 premium cliff.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To summarize, you will see an increase anywhere from 9.56% to as much as 18.5% in
your effective marginal tax rate due to the reduction of the premium tax credit.
The average increase across the whole range (133-400%) is 12.8%.  Since this
occurs in the 10-15% income tax ranges, this is a big jump in marginal tax rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;effective-marginal-tax-rate&quot;&gt;Effective Marginal Tax Rate&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next graph simply combines the marginal tax rates with the effects of the
reduction in premium subsidies to come up with the &lt;strong&gt;effective&lt;/strong&gt; marginal tax rate.
It’s somewhat startling to see that the effective marginal tax rates can be higher
than those for people earning over $96,000 (603% FPL).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;effective&quot; class=&quot;chart&quot;&gt;
    &lt;svg&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we normally think of as the 10% tax bracket is now approximately a 25% tax
bracket.  The lower end of the 15% tax bracket (below $48,000) has become a 32%
tax bracket.  And between $48,000 and $64,000 the marginal tax rate is nearly 25%.
We finally return to the 15% tax rate above $64,000 but lose the premium subsidy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;capital-gains&quot;&gt;Capital Gains&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Long-term capital gains are are similarly affected.  Instead of having zero
marginal tax rates up to the 25% bracket, there are now significant marginal
effects in the 133-400% FPL range.  And in the 250-300% FPL range you would be
at a higher marginal rate (&amp;gt; 15%) than people with much higher incomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;capgains&quot; class=&quot;chart&quot;&gt;
    &lt;svg&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;strategies&quot;&gt;Strategies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discovery of this increase in marginal tax rate has colored my views on
how and when to take income from my portfolio.  It mostly boils down to the
concept of delaying my taxable income until age 65 when Medicare
kicks in and I no longer am eligible for ACA credits.  Alternatively, either
Mrs. Moneycle or I could get a job with health benefits, but that requires
working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some things you can do to push income forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deplete taxable and Roth assets before touching IRA/401k funds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Perform tax-loss harvesting to capture losses now (taking gains after 65)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Defer IRA to Roth conversions which produce taxable income&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Move dividend-producing assets like bonds into IRAs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Delay taking pensions and social security until after age 65&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When buying annuities, add a cost-of-living adjustment (COLA)
  which gives you less income in the early years and more income later.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use delayed income annuities which start at age 65 or beyond&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If most of your investable assets are in tax-qualified accounts (IRA/401k),
then you may not be able to defer your taxable income as much.  In this case
I would recommend spreading your Roth and taxable asset withdrawals from now
until age 65 so that you can get a little benefit each year.  But you might
want to consider lumping those same assets over just a few years if it allows
you to push your income below 400% FPL and get a tax subsidy for a few years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep in mind, if you are able to push income forward until age 65, you probably
want to take as much income as you can between ages 65 and 70 while staying
in the 15% tax bracket.  This is because at age 70, you will most likely begin
taking social security and also be required (at age 70.5) to take required minimum
distributions from your IRAs which all adds up to more taxable income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the overall strategy is,
(1) take as little taxable income as possible while receiving ACA subsidies,
(2) take as much taxable income as possible while not receiving ACA subsidies, and
(3) make it to age 70 and thank your younger self for planning ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
  .chart {
    clear: both;
  }
  .chart, svg {
    height: 360px;
  }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
  var fpl = 15930;
  var deduct = 20700;
  var income10 = deduct;
  var income15 = deduct + 18550;
  var income25 = deduct + 75300;
  var incomeMax = 100000;
  var irsData = [
    [99, 0],
    [100, 0.0201],
    [101, 0.0201],
    [100*(income10-50)/fpl, 0.0201],
    [100*(income10)/fpl, 0.0201],
    [131, 0.0201],
    [132, 0.0201],
    [133, 0.0302],
    [134, 0.0308],
    [135, 0.0314],
    [136, 0.0320],
    [137, 0.0326],
    [138, 0.0331],
    [139, 0.0337],
    [140, 0.0343],
    [141, 0.0349],
    [142, 0.0355],
    [143, 0.0361],
    [144, 0.0367],
    [145, 0.0373],
    [146, 0.0378],
    [147, 0.0384],
    [148, 0.0390],
    [149, 0.0396],
    [150, 0.0402],
    [151, 0.0407],
    [152, 0.0411],
    [153, 0.0416],
    [154, 0.0421],
    [155, 0.0425],
    [156, 0.0430],
    [157, 0.0434],
    [158, 0.0439],
    [159, 0.0444],
    [160, 0.0448],
    [161, 0.0453],
    [162, 0.0458],
    [163, 0.0462],
    [164, 0.0467],
    [165, 0.0472],
    [166, 0.0476],
    [167, 0.0481],
    [168, 0.0486],
    [169, 0.0490],
    [170, 0.0495],
    [171, 0.0499],
    [172, 0.0504],
    [173, 0.0509],
    [174, 0.0513],
    [175, 0.0518],
    [176, 0.0523],
    [177, 0.0527],
    [178, 0.0532],
    [179, 0.0537],
    [180, 0.0541],
    [181, 0.0546],
    [182, 0.0550],
    [183, 0.0555],
    [184, 0.0560],
    [185, 0.0564],
    [186, 0.0569],
    [187, 0.0574],
    [188, 0.0578],
    [189, 0.0583],
    [190, 0.0588],
    [191, 0.0592],
    [192, 0.0597],
    [193, 0.0602],
    [194, 0.0606],
    [195, 0.0611],
    [196, 0.0615],
    [197, 0.0620],
    [198, 0.0625],
    [199, 0.0629],
    [200, 0.0634],
    [201, 0.0638],
    [202, 0.0641],
    [203, 0.0645],
    [204, 0.0648],
    [205, 0.0652],
    [206, 0.0655],
    [207, 0.0659],
    [208, 0.0662],
    [209, 0.0666],
    [210, 0.0669],
    [211, 0.0673],
    [212, 0.0676],
    [213, 0.0680],
    [214, 0.0683],
    [215, 0.0687],
    [216, 0.0690],
    [217, 0.0694],
    [218, 0.0697],
    [219, 0.0701],
    [220, 0.0704],
    [221, 0.0708],
    [222, 0.0711],
    [223, 0.0715],
    [224, 0.0718],
    [225, 0.0722],
    [226, 0.0726],
    [227, 0.0729],
    [228, 0.0733],
    [229, 0.0736],
    [230, 0.0740],
    [231, 0.0743],
    [232, 0.0747],
    [233, 0.0750],
    [234, 0.0754],
    [235, 0.0757],
    [236, 0.0761],
    [237, 0.0764],
    [238, 0.0768],
    [239, 0.0771],
    [240, 0.0775],
    [241, 0.0778],
    [242, 0.0782],
    [243, 0.0785],
    [244, 0.0789],
    [245, 0.0792],
    [246, 0.0796],
    [247, 0.0799],
    [248, 0.0803],
    [249, 0.0806],
    [250, 0.0810],
    [251, 0.0813],
    [252, 0.0816],
    [253, 0.0819],
    [254, 0.0822],
    [255, 0.0825],
    [256, 0.0828],
    [257, 0.0830],
    [258, 0.0833],
    [259, 0.0836],
    [260, 0.0839],
    [261, 0.0842],
    [262, 0.0845],
    [263, 0.0848],
    [264, 0.0851],
    [265, 0.0854],
    [266, 0.0857],
    [267, 0.0860],
    [268, 0.0863],
    [269, 0.0865],
    [270, 0.0868],
    [271, 0.0871],
    [272, 0.0874],
    [273, 0.0877],
    [274, 0.0880],
    [275, 0.0883],
    [276, 0.0886],
    [277, 0.0889],
    [278, 0.0892],
    [279, 0.0895],
    [280, 0.0898],
    [281, 0.0901],
    [282, 0.0903],
    [283, 0.0906],
    [284, 0.0909],
    [285, 0.0912],
    [286, 0.0915],
    [287, 0.0918],
    [288, 0.0921],
    [289, 0.0924],
    [290, 0.0927],
    [291, 0.0930],
    [292, 0.0933],
    [293, 0.0936],
    [294, 0.0938],
    [295, 0.0941],
    [296, 0.0944],
    [297, 0.0947],
    [298, 0.0950],
    [299, 0.0953],
    [300, 0.0956],
    [301, 0.0956],
    [399, 0.0956],
    [400, 0.0956],
  ];

  var prevX = 0, prevY = 0;
  var acaTax = irsData.map(function(x) {
    var tax = x[0] &lt;= 100 ? 0 : (x[0]*x[1] - prevX*prevY)/(x[0] - prevX);
    var income = Math.round(prevX*fpl/100)
    prevX = x[0]; prevY = x[1];
    return [income, tax];
  });

  var bracketData = [
    {
      name: 'Marginal Tax Rate',
      xy: [[0,0], [income10 - 50, 0], [income10, 0.10], [income15 - 50, 0.10], [income15, 0.15], [income25 - 50, 0.15], [income25, 0.25], [incomeMax, 0.25]],
      color: '#2020aa'
    },
  ];

  var acaData = [
    {
      name: 'ACA Tax Credit Reduction',
      xy: acaTax.concat([[4*fpl+1, 0], [incomeMax, 0]]),
      color: '#20a020'
    },
  ];

  var combinedData = [
    {
      name: 'Effective Marginal Tax Rate',
      xy: acaTax.map(function(x) {
        income = x[0];
        tax = x[1] + ((income &lt; income10) ? 0 : ((income &lt; income15) ? 0.1 : (income &lt; income25 ? 0.15 : 0.25)));
        return [income, tax];
      }).concat([[4*fpl+1, 0.15], [income25 - 50, 0.15], [income25, 0.25], [incomeMax, 0.25]]),
      color: '#a02020'
    },
    {
      name: bracketData[0].name,
      xy: bracketData[0].xy,
      color: bracketData[0].color,
      disabled: true
    },
    {
      name: acaData[0].name,
      xy: acaData[0].xy,
      color: acaData[0].color,
      disabled: true
    },
  ];

  var capGainsData = [
    {
      name: 'Effective Capital Gains Rate',
      xy: acaTax.concat([[4*fpl+1, 0], [income25-50, 0], [income25, 0.15], [incomeMax, 0.15]]),
      color: '#a02020'
    },
  ];

  function newChart(data, selector, interactive) {

    var aChart = nv.models.lineChart()
                  .interactive(interactive)
                  .useInteractiveGuideline(interactive)
                  .showLegend(true)
                  .showYAxis(true)
                  .showXAxis(true);

    aChart.xAxis
        .axisLabel('Income (AGI)')
        .tickFormat(d3.format('$,r'))
        .showMaxMin(false);

    aChart.yAxis     //Chart y-axis settings
        .axisLabel('Marginal Tax Rate')
        .tickFormat(d3.format('.3p'))
        .showMaxMin(false);

    aChart.xDomain([0, incomeMax*1.01]);
    aChart.yDomain([0, 0.355]);

    var chartData = chartifyData(data);

    d3.select(selector)
        .datum(chartData)
        .call(aChart);

    //Update the chart when window resizes.
    nv.utils.windowResize(function() {
      aChart.update();
    });

    return aChart;
  }

  function chartifyData(data) {
    //Line chart data should be sent as an array of series objects.
    return data.map(function(obj) {
      return {
        values: transformXY(obj.xy),
        key: obj.name,
        color: obj.color,
        disabled: obj.disabled ? true : false
      }
    });
  }

  function transformXY(data) {
    var result = [];
    for (i = 0; i &lt; data.length; i++) {
      var point = data[i];
      result.push({x: point[0], y: point[1]});
    }
    return result;
  }

  nv.addGraph(newChart(bracketData, '#brackets svg', true));
  nv.addGraph(newChart(acaData, '#acacredits svg', true));
  nv.addGraph(newChart(combinedData, '#effective svg', true));
  nv.addGraph(newChart(capGainsData, '#capgains svg', true));

&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 07 May 2016 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        
          <link>http://www.moneycle.com/affordable-care-act-may-increase-your-marginal-tax-rate/</link>
        
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.moneycle.com/affordable-care-act-may-increase-your-marginal-tax-rate/</guid>
        
        <category>investing</category>
        
        <category>spending</category>
        
        <category>other</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>HSA Tax Advantages</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This time of year has me thinking more about taxes than normal because I recently
took a first stab at income taxes for 2015.  While doing my taxes I noticed the
subject of Health Savings Accounts (HSAs) coming up in a couple different places
so I thought I would share why HSAs can be an awesome place to invest your savings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main reason that HSAs are great is the ability to pay for things with pre-tax
dollars.  Depending on your tax bracket, this can be a huge “investment”.  Consider
going to the doctor and spending $100 from an HSA with before-tax dollars.
If you had to use after-tax dollars for that same $100 expense, and you were in
the 25% tax bracket, you would need to earn $133.33 in order to have the $100 left
over to pay the doctor.  Or to look at it another way, by using an HSA
you avoided spending $33.33 before tax, which is $25 after tax.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put that mathematically, the money saved by using money
from an HSA instead of after-tax dollars is,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;money_saved = (money_without_hsa - money_with_hsa)*(1-tax_rate)
money_without_hsa = invoice_amount/(1-tax_rate)
money_with_hsa = invoice_amount
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which reduces to,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;money_saved = invoice_amount*tax_rate
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if you know you are going to have X dollars in medical expenses, it behooves
you to have X dollars sitting in your HSA because you will save X dollars
multiplied by your marginal tax rate in after tax dollars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;common-hsa-uses&quot;&gt;Common HSA uses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common uses for HSAs are basic medial expenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dentist - use your HSA card to pay for that cleaning or root canal.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Doctor - doctor bills could be has high as your deductible, so you probably
want to build your HSA up to the amount of your deductible to cover large
expenses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prescriptions - those Viagra pills are expensive!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vision - in addition to regular visits to the eye doctor, you can use HSA funds
to pay for eyeglasses and eye surgeries including laser surgeries.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lesser-known-hsa-uses&quot;&gt;Lesser Known HSA uses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some ways to use HSA dollars that you may not have heard about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Long-Term Care (LTC) premiums - there are limits, but LTC policy premiums
can be paid in part using HSA dollars.  The older you are, the more of your
premiums are allowed to be paid using HSA dollars.  For tax-year 2015 the
limits are as follows:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;40 years old and younger – $380&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;41–50 years old – $710&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;51–60 years old – $1,430&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;61–70 years old – $3,800&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;70 years old and older – $4,750&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Medicare premiums - you can’t continue contributing to your HSA after you
hit medicare age (65).  But you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; use your HSA funds to pay for supplemental
Medicare insurance such as Medicare Part B, D or Medicare Advantage.  This
is a good reason to contribute above and beyond your deductible level before
you hit age 65.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Construction expenses - as you get older, you may find you need to need to
make modifications to your house.  Construction expenses to accommodate
somebody with medical issues may be paid for using HSA funds.  Examples include
wheelchair ramps, hand rails, widening doorways, etc..&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vasectomy - pair your vasectomy operation with your Viagra prescription and
put the whole thing on your HSA debit card!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a ton of other things you can use HSA funds for.  Check out
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.irs.gov/pub/irs-pdf/p502.pdf&quot;&gt;the IRS publication&lt;/a&gt; for details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the grand scheme of investing, HSAs are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bogleheads.org/wiki/Prioritizing_investments&quot;&gt;generally considered the 3rd priority&lt;/a&gt;
behind (1) getting your 401k match if you have it and (2) paying off credit cards.
Besides the advantages described above, HSAs also act like an IRA in that the
growth of funds inside the HSA are tax deferred.  While you can take the funds
out after age 65 and be taxed on them just like an IRA, it’s probably best to
leave your money in the HSA and continue using it to pay for medical expenses
until the HSA is drained.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jan 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
          <link>http://www.moneycle.com/hsa-tax-advantages/</link>
        
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.moneycle.com/hsa-tax-advantages/</guid>
        
        <category>investing</category>
        
        <category>spending</category>
        
        <category>other</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
