<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Moneycle</title>
    <description>Don your money monocle (top hats are optional) as we explore topics related to money, investing and early retirement.
</description>
    <link>http://www.moneycle.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.moneycle.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 09 Dec 2015 00:48:24 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Dec 2015 00:48:24 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>The 30-30 Withdrawal Strategy</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Withdrawing funds from your portfolio can be tricky.  On the one hand,
you want to make sure you take enough income to support your expenses.  On the other hand,
you want make sure you don’t run out of money by taking too much.
Most &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bogleheads.org/wiki/Withdrawal_strategies&quot;&gt;withdrawal strategies&lt;/a&gt; break down as either a constant dollar or constant percentage or a hybrid of the two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Constant-dollar withdrawal strategies tend to start with some amount, like 4%, and take that dollar amount
each year.  Optionally, the amount could be increased to account for inflation each year.
While these constant dollar strategies are a great tool for academia to study the effects of different rates,
they have the possibility of failure (running out of money) if you continue to withdraw the same
amount of money without regard for what your portfolio is doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Constant-percentage withdrawal strategies get rid of the possibility of failure
by just taking a fixed percentage out of the portfolio every year,
regardless of what the market does.  This is an improvement over
constant dollar strategies because you can’t run out of money,
but it does mean that your income will be subject to the vagaries of the market.
If you can stomach those swings or have other sources of income to buffer
those swings, then this strategy might work fine for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “30-30 Withdrawal Strategy” described by this article has the advantages of a
constant-percentage strategy but attempts to buffer the market variations by using
shock-absorbing buffer.  The name of the strategy comes from the withdrawal rate and buffer size.
The basic idea of this strategy is that you move a fixed percentage of your portfolio (1/30) into
a spending buffer each year, then you use take a fixed amount from that buffer (1/30)
for monthly living expenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/withdrawal-30-30.png&quot; alt=&quot;30-30 Withdrawals&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;withdrawal-rate-of-130&quot;&gt;Withdrawal Rate of 1/30&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “30-30 Withdrawal Strategy” uses a withdrawal rate of 3.33% for a couple of reasons.
First, it’s easy to remember.  Second and more importantly, it’s in the realm of
withdrawal rates that should, over time, allow you to keep up with inflation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where does the 3.33% come from?  Recall from the &lt;a href=&quot;/safe-withdrawal-rates-for-vampires/&quot;&gt;Safe Withdrawal Rates for Vampires&lt;/a&gt; article that the safe withdrawal
rate for someone who needs their money to last forever is given by the following equation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
withdrawal_rate &amp;lt;= (appreciation - inflation) / (1 + appreciation)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not possible to know what future portfolio appreciation will be, but historically
a 50/50 stock/bond portfolio would have returned around 7-8%.  But when it comes to
retirement, I prefer to be a little more conservative.  So let’s chop about 2% off of 7.5%
to get a conservative future appreciation estimate of 5.5%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inflation is also a little tricky.  Currently inflation is running &lt;a href=&quot;http://inflationdata.com/Inflation/Inflation_Rate/CurrentInflation.asp&quot;&gt;close to zero&lt;/a&gt; but
the Fed has said that they are aiming to keep it close to 2%.  So, for the sake
of this calculation, let’s assume the Fed is able to keep inflation near 2%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plugging those numbers into the above equation, we get&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
withdrawal_rate &amp;lt;= (0.055 - 0.02) / (1 + 0.055) = 3.32%
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This withdrawal rate is also very close to 1/30 which means that you can just
divide your entire portfolio value by 30 to arrive at the amount needed for
an annual withdrawal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may disagree with the assumptions or have a different type of investment portfolio
with different return assumptions.  But understanding how I arrived at the
number may allow you to choose your own number for the withdrawal rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;month-buffer&quot;&gt;30-month Buffer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buffering the annual withdrawals will help to smooth out the bumps in the portfolio
returns.  The idea of the buffer is that, each year, you take your annual withdrawal and immediately
put that into your income buffer.  Then you divide that income buffer by the size
of the buffer in months to arrive at your income level for the next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a 30-month buffer is frankly, somewhat arbitrary.  I chose 30 months (2.5 years)
partly because it has the number 30 in it, but also because I personally want to keep
the buffer relatively small so that I can keep as much of my portfolio invested as
possible. As with the withdrawal rate, you can use a buffer size of your choosing.
The bigger the buffer is, the smoother your income variations will be, but a bigger
buffer also means that less of your money is invested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-by-step&quot;&gt;Step-by-Step&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s go through an example portfolio to see how this works.  First, let’s start
with a portfolio of $900,000 (it divides by 30 nicely).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create your initial spending buffer by dividing your portfolio by 30
  then multiplying by 2.5.  This represents 2.5 years worth of future spending so
  put it in a safe place like an interest-bearing account, short-term bonds, money-market,
  or similar.  For the example $900,000 portfolio, $900,000/30 = $30,000 so you would
  put $75,000 into your initial buffer.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Divide your buffer balance by 30 to get your monthly income level and set up an
  automatic withdrawal of that amount that goes into your spending/checking account.
  In our example, $75,000/30 = $2500/month.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Live off of the income for 12 months.  After 12 months your buffer should
  have approximately $45,000 left in it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;At the end of each year, recompute your portfolio value and move 1/30 of it
  into your buffer.  In our example, let’s assume that the invested portion
  of $825,000 increased to $885,000.  Add that to the remaining buffer ($45,000)
  to get your new portfolio value of $930,000.  Divide that by 30 and move that
  amount into your spending buffer.  $930,000/30 = $31,000.  Your spending buffer
  should now have $76,000.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Go back to Step 2 and repeat annually.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing to note is that I am including the buffer as part of the overall portfolio
value when doing the above calculations.  If you prefer to keep it separate from
the investment portfolio, then you could use a divisor of 27.5 (instead of 30)
on just the investment portfolio to achieve similar results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Astute readers might notice that, even though the investment portfolio increased
by (885/825) 7.3%, the income in the next year will only rise by (76000/75000) 1.33%
which is below our assumed inflation rate of 2%.
This is because the initial buffer was created without taking inflation into account.
Over time this effect should go away and the average increases will keep pace with inflation.
If you want to take that into account from the get-go, you could create a smaller
initial buffer (e.g. 2.4x) which means you would receive less income initially.
But, I personally prefer to &lt;em&gt;start&lt;/em&gt; with a slightly larger income and suffer
the smaller initial income adjustment until the buffering “catches up”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;variation-different-withdrawal-rates&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Variation:&lt;/em&gt; Different Withdrawal Rates&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The withdrawal rate of 3.33% was chosen with a fair amount of hand-waving but represents
what I would consider to be a fairly safe rate that has a reasonable chance of keeping up
with inflation.  However, if you’re a risk taker and/or have other streams of income to
buffer your income, then higher rates aren’t unreasonable.  For example, if you are
comfortable with a 4% withdrawal, then you could use 25 as your divisor instead of 30.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, maybe you could start with 30 then decrease it until you settle in on
a number that seems to suit you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;variation-different-buffer-sizes&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Variation:&lt;/em&gt; Different Buffer Sizes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While 2.5 years is a handy size for the “30-30 Strategy”, it’s certainly not written in stone.
For example a 6-year strategy might play well into a Roth ladder if so you might choose to create
a buffer of 72 months.  Bigger buffers also have the advantage of smoothing out the
investment returns even more and giving you a more predictable income stream.  But the downside
of larger buffers is removing money from your investment pool so you might want to consider investing part
of a larger buffer into a medium-term bond fund or something similar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “30-30 Withdrawal Strategy” is an easy mechanism for taking income from a portfolio.
Divide your portfolio by 30 to figure out much to put into your spending buffer.
Then divide the spending buffer by 30 to figure out how much to withdraw as income every month.
Rinse and repeat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;related&quot;&gt;Related&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/safe-withdrawal-rates-for-vampires/&quot;&gt;Safe Withdrawal Rates for Vampires&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/buffer-withdrawals-to-stabilize-income/&quot;&gt;Buffer Withdrawals to Stabilize Income&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 09 Dec 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
          <link>http://www.moneycle.com/the-30-30-withdrawal-strategy/</link>
        
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.moneycle.com/the-30-30-withdrawal-strategy/</guid>
        
        <category>investing</category>
        
        <category>spending</category>
        
        <category>other</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Two Types of Income</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been noticing that every income stream follows one of two basic patterns.
It is either an indefinite stream that will go as long as you live, or it is
a finite stream that will end at some point in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, income streams either start now, or in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think about income in these terms it helps to give you a mental
framework when trying to structure your portfolio
to give you the income you need, when you need it.  For example, if you will have
an indefinite income stream (like a pension) that starts in the future,
then you may want to create some other income stream now that will last until that
future date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;indefinite-income-streams&quot;&gt;Indefinite Income Streams&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indefinite income streams are those that are expected to last as long as you
and your spouse are alive.  The most common examples of this type of income are
as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Social Security&lt;/strong&gt; - It will still be there when you need it.  Ignore those
 who say otherwise.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pensions&lt;/strong&gt; - Pensions from a company you worked at tend to kick in at your
 retirement (or when you reach a particular age).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Annuities&lt;/strong&gt; - You can buy an annuity from an insurance company that will give
 you income for as long as you live.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Systematic Withdrawals&lt;/strong&gt; - If you withdraw funds from your portfolio at a prudent
  rate (3-4%) then there is a pretty good chance that it will last last long as you do.
  The only question is whether or not it will keep pace with inflation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;finite-income-streams&quot;&gt;Finite Income Streams&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finite income streams are those that you expect to end at some point.  Here are
some examples of those:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Your Job&lt;/strong&gt; - This is the quintessential finite income stream.  You can’t work
  forever.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bridge Fund&lt;/strong&gt; - See my article on &lt;a href=&quot;./building-a-bridge-to-social-security&quot;&gt;creating a bridge to social security&lt;/a&gt;
 for an example of how to use funds to bridge to a future date.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Income Replacement Funds&lt;/strong&gt; - Fidelity offers a particular type of fund called
&lt;a href=&quot;http://moneyover55.about.com/od/investmentincome/a/incomereplacement.htm&quot;&gt;Income Replacement Funds&lt;/a&gt;
that are designed to provide income until some future date.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bonds&lt;/strong&gt; - You could buy a portfolio of bonds that return the principal in different
years and spend that money as it is returned to you.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lending Money&lt;/strong&gt; - You can lend funds to somebody with the promise that they
 will pay it back with some agreed-upon rate.  Micro-lending companies like Lending
 Club and Prosper are a good way to do this efficiently.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Imprudent Systematic Withdrawals&lt;/strong&gt; - if you draw down your portfolio too quickly,
 you could deplete it in a finite period of time.  Don’t do this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;income-start-dates&quot;&gt;Income Start Dates&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the duration of an income stream, you need to consider when they
income starts.  For example, if you are retiring at age 62, you &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; start taking your
Social Security right at age 62.  However, it is often beneficial for you to delay
taking your benefits until age 70.  In that scenario, you would need to figure out
how to get an income stream that lasts 8 years until your social security kicks in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, your goal as a retiree is to arrange these blocks of income to give you
an income stream that lasts indefinitely but is relatively smooth.  I like to think
of it using building blocks.  Here’s a crude drawing of what I mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;                                   +-----------------------------&amp;gt;
                                   | Longevity Annuity (age 80)
+----------------+-----------------+-----------------------------&amp;gt;
|  Bridge Fund   |          Pension (age 65)
+----------------+----------+------------------------------------&amp;gt;
|  Income Replacement Fund  | Social Security (age 70)
+---------------------------+------------------------------------&amp;gt;
|  Systematic Withdrawals of remaining portfolio
+----------------------------------------------------------------&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this drawing, time goes from left to right.
This example depicts having a relatively steady stream of income until age 80
at which point your income is boosted by a longevity annuity.
The “Longevity Annuity” is one income stream you might want to purchase if you
anticipate needing extra future income to help with age-related expenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also in this example, I am also showing a couple of different finite income stream types being
used to bridge forward to indefinite income streams (pension and social security)
in the future.  The type of bridge isn’t important, I’m just trying to illustrate
the concept of bridging forward to that indefinite future income stream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article doesn’t introduce much in the way of new concepts.  But I have found
it useful in structuring my own portfolio to think of income streams as one of two
basic types that can be combined like building blocks to give you the income you
need in retirement.  Hopefully this framework will help you too.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 31 Oct 2015 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        
          <link>http://www.moneycle.com/two-types-of-income/</link>
        
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.moneycle.com/two-types-of-income/</guid>
        
        <category>spending</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Comparing Target-Date Fund Glide Paths</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Target-date funds are relative newcomers in the investment world.  Most of today’s
target-date funds were created in the last 10 years or so.  Their popularity has
grown largely since the passage in 2006 of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pension_Protection_Act_of_2006&quot;&gt;Pension Protection Act&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pension Protection Act stipulates that employers provide what are called
“Qualified Default Investment Alternatives” which is a fancy way of saying that
they need to provide default investment alternatives that don’t suck.
And target-date funds are generally considered to not suck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;typical-target-date-fund&quot;&gt;Typical Target-Date Fund&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The general idea of the target-date fund is to invest for growth when the investor
is young and gradually decrease the amount of risky investments as the investor
approaches retirement age.  Typically the risky investment takes the form of
stocks and the safer investment is in bonds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The transition from the early growth period to the later safe period is called
the “glide-path”.  In visual form, here’s what a typical glide path looks like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;example&quot;&gt;
    &lt;svg&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This plot shows the glide-path continuing to decrease a little past the retirement
age. This is fairly common and is often referred to as a “glide-through” fund
versus a fund that stops chaning right at the target-date which is called a “glide-to”
fund.  It’s good to understand these differences so that you aren’t surprised to
find that your fund is still changing allocation after the target-date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the purposes of this article, I was focused on some of the
more popular target-date funds.  Defining popularity is tricky so I chose to just
consider the biggest and cheapest funds.  “Biggest” funds are defined by their
assets under management, and “cheapest” funds are defined by their expense ratios.
The data for this article came mostly from a comprehensive article published by
Morningstar titled &lt;a href=&quot;http://corporate1.morningstar.com/ResearchArticle.aspx?documentId=705998&quot;&gt;“2015 Target-Date Fund Landscape”&lt;/a&gt;, and was verified by looking
at the individual mutual-fund companies’ websites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;biggest-target-date-funds&quot;&gt;Biggest Target-Date Funds&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following table lists the 4 biggest target-date funds in terms of total market share:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table id=&quot;funds-by-share&quot;&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;Fund Family&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th&gt;2014 Market Share (%)&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th&gt;Expense Ratio (%)&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody /&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These four funds make up wholly two thirds of all target-date funds so they are the gorillas.
Vanguard is the clear market share leader with over a quarter of the entire target-date fund market.
But Fidelity has a couple of entries that add up to over 20% of the market.  From what I’ve been
able to glean, Fidelity’s “K” series of funds is similar to the non-K series except
that it is only available to 401k plans run by Fidelity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cheapest-target-date-funds&quot;&gt;Cheapest Target-Date Funds&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here are the 4 funds with the smallest expense ratios:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table id=&quot;funds-by-expense&quot;&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;Fund Family&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th&gt;2014 Market Share (%)&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th&gt;Expense Ratio (%)&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody /&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not surprisingly, the low-cost leader Vanguard is also on this list.
But the “Fidelity Freedom Index” fund has a slight edge on expense.
Note that the “Fidelity Freedom Index” is yet another target-date fund
from Fidelity.  The “Index” variant from Fidelity appears to be their low-cost variant
composed of only low-cost Fidelity index funds.  The “Index” variant is also only
available via certain employer-sponsored plans which is why you can’t easily
find information about them on their public website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;glide-paths&quot;&gt;Glide Paths&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the glide paths for all of the funds mentioned above&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  The zero point
on the time axis represents the relative target date.  For example, the point
-10 for a 2040 fund maps to the year 2030.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;chart&quot;&gt;
    &lt;svg&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of these 7 funds, only BlackRock is the only “glide-to” fund that stops changing its
allocation right at the target date.  BlackRock is also unique in that its equity
percentage contains a fair amount of real-estate (REIT) investments (15% early on,
dwindling to near 0% at the end of the glide path).
I decided to lump the REIT into the “equity” bucket for this graph
but some would argue that you should put a portion of it into the “bond” bucket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All funds except BlackRock start at 90% equities.  If I had allocated 1/3 of the REIT
to equities then BlackRock would also have close to a 90% equity position at the
beginning too so consider that when looking at the graph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most funds have finished their glide paths within 7 years but T. Rowe Price continues
the glide down for 30 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;general-thoughts&quot;&gt;General Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plotting the different glide paths is an interesting exercise and tool for comparing
funds to see which one most closely aligns with your goals.  But you don’t have to
pick the fund that matches your exact retirement date.  For example, if you want
the glide path to stop right at your retirement date and you like Vanguard,
then you might want to pick the Vanguard fund that is your retirement date minus
7 years to line that up with your goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that most of these funds end at a very “safe” level of equities, perhaps too
safe for my tastes, but maybe just right for you.  I suspect that the fund companies
err on the side of being too conservative to avoid controversy.
As such, my preference would be to use a target date fund mostly during your
accumulation years then switch to a balanced fund (or set of funds) that match
your long-term risk tolerance when you are near your target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing, a big thing, that these funds can’t account for is how much money
you have in a pension or social security.  For example, if your social security
will cover 50% of your future spending, do you really need the rest of your
portfolio to glide to a 30% equity level?  You may conclude that you can take
more risk in your portfolio when social security has your back.
In the end, it comes down to your personal situation and your comfort level with risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
  #example {
    clear: both;
  }
  #example, svg {
    height: 360px;
  }

  #chart {
    clear: both;
  }
  #chart, svg {
    height: 360px;
  }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
  var exampleData = [
    {
      name: &#39;Accumulation&#39;,
      glide: [[-40,90], [-25,90]],
      color: &#39;#a02020&#39;
    },
    {
      name: &#39;Glide Path&#39;,
      glide: [[-25,90], [0,40]],
      color: &#39;#2020aa&#39;
    },
    {
      name: &#39;Preservation&#39;,
      glide: [[0,40], [5,30], [30,30]],
      color: &#39;#20a020&#39;
    }
  ];

  var allData = [
    {
      name: &#39;Fidelity Freedom&#39;,
      glide: [90, 90, 90, 90, 90, 80, 65, 59, 52, 43, 34, 24, 24, 24, 24],
      expense: 0.71,
      share: 9.3,
      color: &#39;#887722&#39;,
      url: &#39;https://www.fidelity.com/mutual-funds/asset-allocation-funds/freedom-funds/overview&#39;
    },
    {
      name: &#39;Fidelity Freedom K&#39;,
      glide: [90, 90, 90, 90, 90, 80, 65, 59, 52, 43, 34, 24, 24, 24, 24],
      expense: 0.61,
      share: 12.8,
      color: &#39;#dd6633&#39;,
      url: &#39;https://www.fidelity.com/mutual-funds/asset-allocation-funds/freedom-funds/overview&#39;
    },
    {
      name: &#39;Fidelity Freedom Index&#39;,
      glide: [90, 90, 90, 90, 90, 80, 65, 58, 52, 43, 33, 24, 24, 24, 24],
      expense: 0.16,
      share: 1.7,
      color: &#39;#408800&#39;,
      url: &#39;https://www.fidelity.com/mutual-funds/asset-allocation-funds/freedom-funds/overview&#39;
    },
    {
      name: &#39;T. Rowe Price Retirement&#39;,
      glide: [90, 90, 90, 90, 85, 78, 71, 64, 54, 45, 40, 35, 31, 27, 20],
      expense: 0.78,
      share: 17.3,
      color: &#39;#40a9f0&#39;,
      url: &#39;http://individual.troweprice.com/public/Retail/Mutual-Funds/Target-Date-Funds&#39;
    },
    {
      name: &#39;TIAA-CREF Lifecycle Index&#39;,
      glide: [90, 90, 90, 90, 81, 73, 65, 57, 50, 44, [9,40], 40, 40, 40, 40, 40],
      expense: 0.21,
      share: 0.5,
      color: &#39;#0b7599&#39;,
      url: &#39;https://www.tiaa-cref.org/public/products-services/mutual-funds/lifecycle/index.html&#39;
    },
    {
      name: &#39;Vanguard Target Retirement&#39;,
      glide: [90, 90, 90, 90, 81, 75, 67, 59, 50, 37, [7,30], 30, 30, 30, 30, 30],
      expense: 0.17,
      share: 27.3,
      color: &#39;#96151d&#39;,
      url: &#39;https://investor.vanguard.com/mutual-funds/target-retirement/&#39;
    },
    {
      name: &#39;BlackRock LifePath Index&#39;,
      glide: [98, 98, 93, 90, 85, 75, 64, 59, 40, 40, 40, 40, 40, 40, 40],
      expense: 0.23,
      share: &#39;0.6&#39;,
      color: &#39;#000000&#39;,
      url: &#39;http://www.blackrock.com/investing/financial-professionals/defined-contribution/investment-strategies/lifepath-index-portfolios&#39;
    }
  ];

  function newChart(data, selector, interactive) {

    var aChart = nv.models.lineChart()
                  .interactive(interactive)
                  .useInteractiveGuideline(interactive)
                  .showLegend(true)
                  .showYAxis(true)
                  .showXAxis(true);

    aChart.xAxis
        .axisLabel(&#39;Years from Target Date&#39;)
        .tickFormat(d3.format(&#39;r&#39;));

    aChart.yAxis     //Chart y-axis settings
        .axisLabel(&#39;Equity Percentage&#39;)
        .tickFormat(d3.format(&#39;.2p&#39;));

    aChart.yDomain([0, 1]);

    var chartData = fundData(data);

    d3.select(selector)
        .datum(chartData)
        .call(aChart);

    //Update the chart when window resizes.
    nv.utils.windowResize(function() {
      aChart.update();
    });

    return aChart;
  }

  function fundData(data) {
    //Line chart data should be sent as an array of series objects.
    return data.map(function(obj) {
      return {
        values: transformXY(obj.glide),
        key: obj.name,
        color: obj.color
      }
    });
  }

  function transformXY(data) {
    var result = [];
    var year = -40;
    while (data.length &gt; 0) {
      var percent = data.shift();
      if (Array.isArray(percent)) {
        result.push({x: percent[0], y: percent[1]*.01})
      } else {
        result.push({x: year, y: percent*.01})
        year += 5;
      }
    }
    return result;
  }


  nv.addGraph(newChart(exampleData, &#39;#example svg&#39;, false));

  allData.sort(function(a,b) { return b.share - a.share; }).slice(0,4).forEach(function(fund) {
    tr = d3.select(&#39;#funds-by-share tbody&#39;).append(&#39;tr&#39;)
    tr.append(&#39;td&#39;).html(&#39;&lt;a href=&quot;&#39; + fund.url + &#39;&quot;&gt;&#39; + fund.name + &#39;&lt;/a&gt;&#39;);
    tr.append(&#39;td&#39;).attr(&quot;style&quot;, &quot;text-align: center&quot;).html(fund.share);
    tr.append(&#39;td&#39;).attr(&quot;style&quot;, &quot;text-align: center&quot;).html(fund.expense);
  });

  allData.sort(function(a,b) { return a.expense - b.expense; }).slice(0,4).forEach(function(fund) {
    tr = d3.select(&#39;#funds-by-expense tbody&#39;).append(&#39;tr&#39;)
    tr.append(&#39;td&#39;).html(&#39;&lt;a href=&quot;&#39; + fund.url + &#39;&quot;&gt;&#39; + fund.name + &#39;&lt;/a&gt;&#39;);
    tr.append(&#39;td&#39;).attr(&quot;style&quot;, &quot;text-align: center&quot;).html(fund.share);
    tr.append(&#39;td&#39;).attr(&quot;style&quot;, &quot;text-align: center&quot;).html(fund.expense);
  });

  nv.addGraph(newChart(allData.sort(function(a, b) {
    return d3.descending(a.expense, b.expense); }), &#39;#chart svg&#39;, true));

&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;click on a fund name to remove it or double click to remove all others &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2015 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        
          <link>http://www.moneycle.com/comparing-target-date-fund-glide-paths/</link>
        
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.moneycle.com/comparing-target-date-fund-glide-paths/</guid>
        
        <category>investing</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Estimating Your Social Security Benefit for an Early Retirement</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As demonstrated in the &lt;a href=&quot;./building-a-bridge-to-social-security&quot;&gt;Social Security bridge&lt;/a&gt; article,
knowing how much your benefit will be could have a large bearing on when you will be able to retire.
Unfortunately, the benefits statement that the Social Security Administration (SSA) provides
only estimates your benefit amount in terms of your continued employment until
your full retirement age.  But you may want to know how much your benefit would
be if you retired before your full retirement age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prerequisite&quot;&gt;Prerequisite&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before you can estimate your benefit at all, you need to suck it up and get
your last Social Security statement.  If you’ve never logged into the SSA website
then you may have already received a statement.  By default the SSA sends these
statements every 5 years starting at age 25.  But if you want the most up-to-date statement then
you’ll need to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ssa.gov/signin&quot;&gt;log in to the SSA website&lt;/a&gt; to see it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;quick-estimate&quot;&gt;Quick Estimate&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you just want a quick back-of-the-envelope estimate of your benefits then you
can project the estimated benefit that the SSA provides to the number of years
you hope to work.  Near the top of the Social Security statement is a section titled
“Your Estimated Benefits”.  Because delaying benefits to age 70 is usually the smartest
choice, get the number on the line that says “if you continue working until age 70”.
This number represents what your benefit might be at age 70 if you continued working at your
current level of income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way social security works is that they use your top 35 earning years, adjusted for inflation,
in a formula to calculate your benefits.  And because the estimate on your statement assumes
you will work until age 70 which is likely more than 35 years, the estimate assumes
you will not retire early.  For a quick estimate, in the case where you will work less
than 35 years, you can estimate your benefit as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
  estimated_benefit = ssa_estimate * years_worked / 35
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s demonstrate this with an example.  If the SSA says your estimated benefit is
$2800/month but you want to quit working after 25 years of employment, then your
early-retirement estimate would be about &lt;code&gt;2800 * 25 / 35&lt;/code&gt; or $2000/month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see that each additional year, up until your 35th working year increases
your benefit by about &lt;code&gt;1/N&lt;/code&gt; percent.  So working 26 years instead of 25 years means you
would get about 26/25 or 4% more than if you stopped working after 25 years.  But
working 11 instead of 10 years could increase that future benefit by 10%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, working more than 35 years likely will have little effect on your
benefit except that it might replace one of your lower-earning years in the calculation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep in mind that you don’t qualify for Social Security benefits until you have worked
40 quarters (10 years).  So if you’re a super saver and are tempted to retire after
9.9 years, you might want to see if it’s worth working another month or two to qualify
for the benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;better-estimate&quot;&gt;Better Estimate&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are quite a few Social Security calculators out there but most of them are
more geared towards what the best strategy is for taking social security.  The
best calculator I’ve found for estimating your social security benefits is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ssa.gov/planners/retire/AnypiaApplet.html&quot;&gt;the
“Online Calculator” on the SSA website&lt;/a&gt;.
Let’s go through how to utilize this calculator for estimating early retirement
benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After setting your birthday, the first entry to change on the calculator is the “Age at Retirement”.
Change that from the default value of 66 to 70 because delaying benefits until age 70
is usually the best thing to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ss_estimate_age_at_retirement_70.png&quot; alt=&quot;age at retirement = 70&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Filling in the earnings section on the calculator is somewhat tedious.
There’s no easy way to do it, just type all your earnings into the calculator.
It’s important that they are entered on the correct years because the calculator will apply
different adjustments for inflation depending on the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have all the numbers entered, it’s time to sanity check your numbers.
Take the number in the last year of the table (2014 as of this writing), and
put that same number in the “Earnings for 2015” and “Earnings for 2016 and later”
fields then click “Calculate Benefit.”  For example, if you earned $60,000 in 2014,
enter that for 2015, 2016 and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ss_estimate_verify.png&quot; alt=&quot;verify amounts&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now calculate your benefits by pressing the “Calculate Benefit” button and vieiwing
the estimates in the “Benefit estimates” section of the calculator.
If you entered all of your data correctly into the calculator then the field labeled
“Your monthly retirement benefit” on the calculator should exactly match the amount
labeled “if you continue working until age 70” on your Social Security statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ss_estimate_result.png&quot; alt=&quot;estimate results&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it’s time to play with the numbers.  What if you want to retire at the beginning
of next year.  You can enter your estimated earnings for the current year and
enter zero for “Earnings in 2016 and later”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ss_estimate_retire_next_year.png&quot; alt=&quot;retire next year&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this tool isn’t great for what-if scenarios a few years into the
future.  But you can trick it into giving an answer that might be close to your
scenario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, what if you have worked 20 years and want to retire 5 years from now.
The tool doesn’t let you enter 5 future years of income followed by zeroes.
So instead, you could take that 5 years of earnings and spread it over the remainder
of the 35 year timespan and enter that number as your future earnings.  Mathematically,
the number to enter for future earnings is,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
fake_future_earnings = actual_earnings * years_until_retirement / (35 - years_worked)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By way of example, if you have worked 20 years and expect to earn $60,000 for the next
5 years, that’s $300,000 total.  Spreading that $300,000 over 35-20 = 15 years means
that you would enter $20,000 for your future earnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ss_estimate_retire_5_years.png&quot; alt=&quot;retire in 5 years&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it’s time for a disclaimer.  Estimating future benefits based on several years
of fake earnings is probably not going to be terribly accurate because you won’t
actually be working those future years until you hit 35 years of employment and future
inflation could wreak havoc with such an estimate.  So take this part with a grain of salt.
But it should be at least as accurate as the “quick estimate” above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowing your future Social Security benefits can be important when determining when you will be able
to retire.  For example, if you want to &lt;a href=&quot;/building-a-bridge-to-social-security/&quot;&gt;build a Social Security bridge&lt;/a&gt;
you need to know how much money to dedicate to the bridge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article gives you both a quick-and-dirty method and a more accurate method using the calculator
provided by the Social Security Administration.  So dust off your monocle and figure out how much your
benefit will be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;related&quot;&gt;Related&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/building-a-bridge-to-social-security/&quot;&gt;Building a Bridge to Social Security&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 20 Aug 2015 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        
          <link>http://www.moneycle.com/estimating-your-social-security-benefit-for-an-early-retirement/</link>
        
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.moneycle.com/estimating-your-social-security-benefit-for-an-early-retirement/</guid>
        
        <category>investing</category>
        
        <category>spending</category>
        
        <category>other</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Building a Bridge to Social Security</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If you read any early &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mrmoneymustache.com/2012/05/29/how-much-do-i-need-for-retirement/&quot;&gt;retirement blogs&lt;/a&gt;,
you may have encountered a rule of thumb that says something like
“you need to save 25 times your annual expenses in order to retire”.  That 25
number, the &lt;em&gt;expense multiplier&lt;/em&gt;, comes from a 4% withdrawal assumption. So
if you withdraw 4% from your portfolio to cover your expenses, that means your
portfolio must be at least as big as the inverse of 4% or 25.
Because you only retire once, I prefer to be a little more conservative
and use an expense multiplier of 30 which corresponds to a 3.33% withdrawal rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this kind of rule is a great rule of thumb for giving people an idea of
how much money they will need to save, it tends to ignore the income that
you will earn from a future income stream such as social security or a pension&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.
In the early retirement circles the effects of social security tend to be ignored
perhaps because it seems like far-off and insignificant event.  But the effects
of that extra income increase over time so your financial independence could be
closer than you previously thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;simple-example&quot;&gt;Simple Example&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To illustrate the effects with an extreme example, consider the case of somebody
named Woodrow who is 69 years old and has expenses of $40,000/year. Furthermore,
if Woodrow expects to receive $40,000/year from social security at age 70&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;,
then he will only need to have savings of $40,000 to be able to retire right now.
In this extreme example, Woodrow’s expense multiplier is 1 because he only needs
to have saved 1 times his annual expenses in order to retire now.
Think of needed savings as a 1-year bridge that allow Woodrow to live
comfortably until his full social security benefits kick in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ss-bridge-short.png&quot; alt=&quot;Retiring a little early&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the illustration above, the green area represents the funds that are
needed to fill the gap until social security kicks in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In scenarios like this, where your future social security payments will cover your expenses,
it’s fairly easy to extrapolate this simple example to longer time periods.
In such scenarios you only need to save enough money to get to the age when
you will begin collecting social security.
So if Woodrow had been age 60 in the above example, he would need to have savings
of &lt;code&gt;10*$50,000&lt;/code&gt; or $500,000 in order to cover his expenses for the 10 years before
he received social security.  His expense multiplier is the number of
years until he begins collecting social security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also of note, if Woodrow is 30 or more years from receiving social security,
he doesn’t necessarily need a portfolio bigger than 30 times his expenses because,
theoretically he should be able to live off of the 3.33% withdrawal indefinitely
(or whatever you consider to be a safe withdrawal rate).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;early-retirement-example&quot;&gt;Early Retirement Example&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above example is interesting and illustrates how accounting for
social security can dramatically reduce a person’s expense multiplier.
But early retirees are more likely to be in a situation where the social security
amount will not cover all of their expenses in the future because they may not
have contributed a full 35 years into the system.  In this case, a social security
bridge may need to be supplemented by additional withdrawals to meet spending needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ss-bridge-medium.png&quot; alt=&quot;Retiring early&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s consider another person named Priscilla who is aged 55 and estimates that
she will receive $30k/year (in today’s dollars) from social security if she waits
until age 70.
But Priscilla’s expenses are $40k/year.  To bridge the 15-year social security gap,
Priscilla needs 15 times the $30k, or $450k to get her to the level of income
that social security will provide.
Then she will need an additional piece of her portfolio to get her the
extra $10k/year needed to cover her expenses.  Using a 3.33% withdrawal rate
means Priscilla will need an additional &lt;code&gt;30*$10k&lt;/code&gt; or $300k.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Priscilla’s example she would need $750k to retire at age 55 with $40k in
expenses.  This means that her expense multiplier is reduced from 30
(inverse of 3.33%) to &lt;code&gt;750k/40k&lt;/code&gt; or 18.75.
To put it another way, without considering social security Priscilla might have
concluded that she needed to save &lt;code&gt;30*40k&lt;/code&gt; or $1.2m, which is 60% more than the $750k
she actually needs when taking social security into account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;very-early-retirement-example&quot;&gt;Very Early Retirement Example&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retiring very early can put you into a situation where building a social
security bridge doesn’t make sense initially.  For example, if you retire at age 30, then
building a bridge for 40 years means you might start withdrawing funds at a 2.5%
rate which is likely more conservative than necessary.
To get around this problem, you can initially take withdrawals at your preferred
safe withdrawal rate until you hit the age of &lt;code&gt;70-1/withdrawal_rate&lt;/code&gt;.
Then you can implement a social security bridge from that age forward.
This is illustrated below where initially all income is from safe withdrawals,
then a social security bridge kicks in later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ss-bridge-long.png&quot; alt=&quot;Retiring Even Earlier&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the case of Gunther who is retiring at age 35.  Good for you Gunther!
Because Gunther has contributed into social security for much less time than the
maximum of 35 years&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, his estimated social security payments at age 70 will only
be $10k.  Because his social security payments are so far in the future, he needs to have
an initial portfolio equal to his expenses divided by his withdrawal rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if Gunther needs $40k of income and wants to use a 3.33% withdrawal rate,
he should start with a portfolio of &lt;code&gt;30*$40k&lt;/code&gt; or $1.2m.  Then, at age 40, he
can break his portfolio into two pieces.  One piece, $300k (or higher depending
on inflation and social security adjustments), will be used as
a social security bridge.  The remaining part of his portfolio can continue
at the safe withdrawal rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why would Gunther do use a social security brige at all?  The funds
in the social security bridge piece of his portfolio will be withdrawn at ever
increasing withdrawal rate until age 70. This means that Gunther’s overall
withdrawal rate that is effectively higher than 3.33% and increases as he
approaches age 70 when social security will takes over.  In other words, he
can safely increase his income between ages 40 and 70 beyond what he would have
received if he had maintained a 3.33% withdrawal rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that very early retirees should be aware of is that you need to
contribute into the social security system at least 40 quarters (10 years)
in order to be eligible for social security payments.  So if you’re an extreme
saver and can retire in 9 years and 11 months, it would probably be a good idea
to work that extra month to become eligible for social security benefits later
in life.  If you’re lucky enough to be in this situation, check the social
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ssa.gov/OACT/COLA/QC.html&quot;&gt;security site&lt;/a&gt; to make sure you don’t
leave yourself short.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-bridge-fund&quot;&gt;The Bridge Fund&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you build a social security bridge?  The trick is to allocate a chunk
of money that will pay you an income equal to what you expect to receive from
social security in the future.  Fortunately, the social security administration
reports your expected benefits in today’s dollars and adjusts them up every year
based on current inflation.  This makes it easier to project how much money
you need now because the calculations are done in current dollars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several ways you could build a bridge fund.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bond ladder&lt;/strong&gt; - you could build a bond ladder for the bridge period.  This might
 work well for somebody between 65 and 70 who wants to delay taking social security for
 a few years.  But if you are more than 5 years from taking social security, you
 might want to take a little more risk so that you can keep up with inflation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Single Premium Immediate Annuities&lt;/strong&gt; - an insurance company would be happy to
sell you a SPIA that is “term certain”.  For example, if you are 60, you could
buy a 10-year term-certain immediate annuity that pays you a fixed income for the next 10
years.  You could also buy one with inflation protection but that will cost a little more.
While I think &lt;strong&gt;lifetime&lt;/strong&gt; annuities are a really good option to protect against
longevity risk (outliving your money), a term-certain annuity doesn’t have an
actuarial component associated with it so you might be able to do better elsewhere.
But there’s something to be said for a guaranteed stream of income so perhaps this
option will appeal to you.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Income Replacement Funds&lt;/strong&gt; - Fidelity offers a particular type of fund called
&lt;a href=&quot;http://moneyover55.about.com/od/investmentincome/a/incomereplacement.htm&quot;&gt;Income Replacement Funds&lt;/a&gt;
that are designed to distribute your invested funds over a particular period of time.
One of the stated purposes of these funds is as a bridge to a future income stream
such as a pension or social security.  The funds do this by investing in a mix of stocks,
bonds, and cash equivalents and become more conservative as the they nears their
end date.  Think of this as a period-certain annuity with more risk and possibly more return.
This might be a good choice if you can handle a little more risk and like something simple.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DIY Bridge Fund&lt;/strong&gt; - You could build your own bridge fund using low-cost index funds.
In a future article I will propose a way to build your own bridge fund using a simple
allocation of low-cost funds.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;math&quot;&gt;Math&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now is the time for the geeky part of the article.  Let’s try to develop an
equation to describe the effective expense multiplier that takes future social
security income into account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The equation for your future income can be written as,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
income_total = income_ss + porfolio_remaining*withdrawal_rate
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you consider that your future portfolio will be reduced by the amount of
income that was used as a social security bridge, then the amount of income you
have left to apply your withdrawal rate to is approximately,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
porfolio_remaining = portfolio_current - years_until_ss * income_ss
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2nd term of the above equation represents an approximation of how much
your portfolio will be reduced by building your social security bridge.
This will vary depending on how you build that bridge but this is a good
ballpark estimate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately we’re interested in determining the expense multiplier needed for
retirement.  In other words, how big would my portfolio need to be in
order to be retire today.  Defining the effective expense multiplier as,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
multiplier_effective = portfolio_current / income_total
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, let’s define the safe withdrawal rate multiplier as just&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
multiplier_safe = 1 / withdrawal_safe
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plugging all those equations in and solving for &lt;code&gt;multiplier_effective&lt;/code&gt;
gives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
multiplier_effective = multiplier_safe - (income_ss/income_total) * (multiplier_safe - years_until_ss)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice that the closer you are to collecting social security, the smaller your
effective expense multiplier is.  So each year you do this calculation will bring you
closer to retirement even if your portfolio doesn’t grow.  The amount you will
reduce your effective expense multiplier each year is the ratio of your social security
income to your total needed income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s try applying this equation to Woodrow’s example where he will retire in 1 years:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
multiplier_effective = 30 - (50k/50k) * (30 - 1) = 30 - 29 = 1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is exactly as we expect.  In fact, in cases like Woodrow’s, where the income
from social security equals (or exceeds) the total income needed, then the equation
for the effective expense multiplier reduces to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
multiplier_effective = multiplier_safe - 1 * (multiplier_safe - years_until_ss)
                     = years_until_ss
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now try Priscilla’s example,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
multiplier_effective = 30 - (30k/40k)*(30-15) = 30 - 11.25 = 18.75
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Priscilla’s effective withdrawal rate in the first year would be approximately
&lt;code&gt;1/18.75&lt;/code&gt; or 5.33%. You may be thinking that a withdrawal of 5.33% is too high
but remember, she is still withdrawing a conservative 3.33% on the funds outside
of the bridge fund.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, if Priscilla waits one more year to retire, then her effective expense multiplier
would go down by (30k/40k) or 0.75, so if she waits until age 56 her expense multiplier
would be 18.0 so she could be closer to retirement even if her portfolio didn’t
grow at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people would have you believe that social security will be greatly diminished
in the future.  Whether or not that’s true, time will tell.  If you are worried about
this possibility then simply adjust downward your social security estimate in the
above equations to a level you feel comfortable with&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inverse of the withdrawal rate is often used as an expense multiplier to figure
out how big a person’s portfolio needs to be to cover retirement expenses.
Oftentimes this is stated in terms of how big a portfolio needs to be in order
to cover expenses &lt;em&gt;above&lt;/em&gt; social security income.  It’s common for early retirees
to assume that this expense multiplier also applies to their total income but it doesn’t
account for future income streams like social security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By considering how much your future social security income will affect your expense
multiplier, you may find that you can retire earlier than you previously thought.
And every year you wait, your expense multiplier goes down so you can move closer to
achieving retirement even when your portfolio stagnates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;related&quot;&gt;Related&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/estimating-your-social-security-benefit-for-an-early-retirement/&quot;&gt;Estimating Your Social Security Benefit for an Early Retirement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Most of this article refers to social security for brevity’s sake but the same principles apply equally to other future income streams such as pensions. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For most people, delaying social security benefits to age 70 is the best decision, so all examples in this article assume that social security benefits will start at that age. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The Social Security Administration uses the maximum 35 years of earnings over your entire working career in their formula to determine your benefits. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Yes, I ended that sentence with a preposition.  And I also think that social security will be available when I’m eligible for it.  That’s how crazy I am. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jul 2015 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        
          <link>http://www.moneycle.com/building-a-bridge-to-social-security/</link>
        
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.moneycle.com/building-a-bridge-to-social-security/</guid>
        
        <category>spending</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Buffer Withdrawals to Stabilize Income</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&quot;/safe-withdrawal-rates-for-vampires/&quot;&gt;previous article&lt;/a&gt;, the concept of buffered
withdrawals was introduced, but some details were omitted.
This article will explore that idea with a little more depth
and describe how such a strategy could be implemented in practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before moving on, I would like to give credit for the idea of this strategy.
I first encountered the idea of buffered withdrawals on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bogleheads.org/wiki/Withdrawal_methods#Combination&quot;&gt;bogleheads.org site’s
wiki page for withdrawal methods&lt;/a&gt;.
This page alludes to the Galeno Strategy but doesn’t describe what it is.
Intrigued, I set out to find
&lt;a href=&quot;http://boards.fool.com/galenos-mechanical-retirement-strategy-11114923.aspx&quot;&gt;The&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.early-retirement.org/forums/f26/hi-im-galeno-13957.html&quot;&gt;Galeno&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://socialize.morningstar.com/NewSocialize/asp/FullConv.asp?forumId=F100000001&amp;amp;convId=31854&quot;&gt;Strategy&lt;/a&gt;
and discovered that it is just a way to buffer the withdrawals.
In Galeno’s case, he uses a 5-year buffer with the buffer invested in safe money-market
funds and the rest of his portfolio invested in stocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to take this a step further and look at different size buffers and
different stock allocation strategies to see how this affected the math.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-basics&quot;&gt;The Basics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic idea of the spending buffer is to split your portfolio (&lt;code&gt;P&lt;/code&gt;) into the
investments (&lt;code&gt;V&lt;/code&gt;) and withdrawal buffer (&lt;code&gt;U&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
P = V + U
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each year, you take a percentage of your portfolio (your withdrawal rate) and add
it to your buffer.  Then you divide that buffer by the size (in years) and withdraw
that amount as your income for the coming year.  If your buffer size is &lt;code&gt;k&lt;/code&gt; years,
this means that normally you will have &lt;code&gt;k-1&lt;/code&gt; years worth of spending sitting in the buffer.
Your buffer will only temporarily have &lt;code&gt;k&lt;/code&gt; years of spending in the short time
between when you add annual withdrawal to the buffer and then withdraw your
spending funds from the buffer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do this?  The main reason to do this is to buffer the ups and downs of the
stock market.  The bigger your buffer is, the smaller the variation will be
on your withdrawal income.  Statistically, if you sample data that has a
standard deviation of &lt;code&gt;σ&lt;/code&gt;, then taking &lt;code&gt;N&lt;/code&gt; samples of that data will have
a standard deviation of &lt;code&gt;σ/sqrt(N)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  Applying that principal to a
withdrawal buffer, if we sample a portfolio that has a 20% standard deviation
per year, a 4-year buffer of that data would have a 10% standard deviation.
In short, a withdrawal buffer reduces the volatility of your income compared to
directly withdrawing a fixed percentage from your portfolio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-math&quot;&gt;Some Math&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s define a single years’ worth of the buffer to be &lt;code&gt;W&lt;/code&gt;, then&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
P = V + (k-1)W
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically the invesment piece (&lt;code&gt;V&lt;/code&gt;) would be made up of some combination of stocks (&lt;code&gt;S&lt;/code&gt;)
and bonds (&lt;code&gt;B&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
V = S + B
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the withdrawal buffer would be invested conservatively in cash-equivalents
since that is the money will support your living expenses in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;pieWithBuffer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;stock-slider&quot; style=&quot;width: 300px;&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
var pieData = [
  {
    &quot;label&quot;: &quot;Buffer&quot;,
    &quot;value&quot;: 13,
    &quot;color&quot;: &quot;#387e45&quot;,
    &quot;caption&quot;: &quot;{percentage}%, withdrawal = 3.2%&quot;
  },
  {
    &quot;label&quot;: &quot;Bonds&quot;,
    &quot;value&quot;: 27,
    &quot;color&quot;: &quot;#386a7e&quot;,
    &quot;caption&quot;: &quot;{percentage}%&quot;
  },
  {
    &quot;label&quot;: &quot;Stocks&quot;,
    &quot;value&quot;: 60,
    &quot;color&quot;: &quot;#7e3838&quot;,
    &quot;caption&quot;: &quot;{percentage}%&quot;
  }
];
stockReturn = 0.102;
bondReturn = 0.053;
inflationRate = 0.032;
bufferSize = 5;

updateData = function(stockPercent) {
    var stock = stockPercent * 0.01
  var bufferlessReturn = stock*stockReturn + (1-stock)*bondReturn;
  var a = bufferSize*(bufferSize-1)*bondReturn;
  var b = 1+(bufferSize-1)*bondReturn+bufferSize*bufferlessReturn;
  var c = bufferlessReturn - inflationRate;
  var withdrawalRate = (b-Math.sqrt(b*b-4*a*c))/(2*a);
  var bufferPercent = (bufferSize-1)*withdrawalRate*100;
  var bondPercent = 100-stockPercent-bufferPercent;

  pieData[0].value = bufferPercent;
  pieData[0].caption = &quot;{percentage}%, withdrawal = &quot; + Math.round(withdrawalRate*1000)/10 + &quot;%&quot;
  pieData[1].value = bondPercent;
  pieData[2].value = stockPercent;
}
updateData(55);

var pie = new d3pie(&quot;pieWithBuffer&quot;, {
	&quot;header&quot;: {
		&quot;title&quot;: {
			&quot;text&quot;:     &quot;Portfolio Allocation with a Spending Buffer&quot;,
			&quot;fontSize&quot;: 22
		},
    subtitle: {
      text:     bufferSize + &quot;-year buffer, 10.2% stock returns, 5.3% bond returns, 3.2% inflation&quot;,
      color:    &quot;#666666&quot;,
      fontSize: 14,
    }
	},
  footer: {
    text: 	  &quot;use slider to change stock allocation&quot;,
    color:    &quot;#666666&quot;,
    fontSize: 10,
    location: &quot;bottom-center&quot;
  },
	&quot;size&quot;: {
		&quot;canvasHeight&quot;: 400,
		&quot;canvasWidth&quot;: 430,
		&quot;pieOuterRadius&quot;: &quot;88%&quot;
	},
	&quot;data&quot;: {
		&quot;content&quot;: pieData
	},
	&quot;labels&quot;: {
		&quot;outer&quot;: {
			&quot;format&quot;: &quot;none&quot;,
			&quot;pieDistance&quot;: 32
		},
		&quot;inner&quot;: {
			&quot;format&quot;: &quot;label&quot;
		},
		&quot;mainLabel&quot;: {
			&quot;color&quot;: &quot;#e1e1e1&quot;,
			&quot;font&quot;: &quot;verdana&quot;,
			&quot;fontSize&quot;: 12
		},
		&quot;percentage&quot;: {
			&quot;color&quot;: &quot;#e1e1e1&quot;,
			&quot;font&quot;: &quot;verdana&quot;,
			&quot;decimalPlaces&quot;: 0
		},
		&quot;value&quot;: {
			&quot;color&quot;: &quot;#e1e1e1&quot;,
			&quot;font&quot;: &quot;verdana&quot;
		},
		&quot;lines&quot;: {
			&quot;enabled&quot;: true,
			&quot;color&quot;: &quot;#cccccc&quot;
		},
		&quot;truncation&quot;: {
			&quot;enabled&quot;: true
		}
	},
	&quot;tooltips&quot;: {
		&quot;enabled&quot;: true,
		&quot;type&quot;: &quot;caption&quot;,
		&quot;string&quot;: &quot;{label}: {percentage}%&quot;
	},
	&quot;effects&quot;: {
		&quot;pullOutSegmentOnClick&quot;: {
			&quot;effect&quot;: &quot;linear&quot;,
			&quot;speed&quot;: 200,
			&quot;size&quot;: 12
		}
	},
	&quot;callbacks&quot;: {
    &quot;onload&quot;: function() { pie.openSegment(0); },
		&quot;onMouseoverSegment&quot;: null,
		&quot;onMouseoutSegment&quot;: null,
		&quot;onClickSegment&quot;: null
	}
});

d3.select(&#39;#stock-slider&#39;).call(d3.slider().axis(true).min(0).max(85).step(5).value(pieData[2].value).on(&quot;slideend&quot;, function(evt, stockPercent) {
  updateData(stockPercent);
  pie.updateProp(&quot;data.content&quot;, pieData);
}));
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Galeno’s version of this strategy invests everything in stocks which means that
the percentage of the overall portfolio in stocks fluctuates.
I would prefer to keep the stock percentage at some fixed value so I will
diverge from the Galeno Strategy on this point.
If the stock percentage is &lt;code&gt;s&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
  S = sP
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason I like to keep the stock percentage fixed is to that it enables you to
take gains when the market is up and move more money back into stocks when the market
is down, simply by rebalancing to that fixed percentage.  This is in keeping with the
asset allocation strategies that we all know and love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we define the withdrawal rate (&lt;code&gt;w&lt;/code&gt;) as a percentage of the overall portfolio,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
W = wP
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The portfolio equation now looks like this,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
P = sP + B + (k-1)wP
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bond piece is the part of the portfolio that fluctuates to accommodate swings
in the stock market and can be written as,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
B = (1-s)P - (k-1)wP
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice that for the degenerate case of no buffer (k=1), the bond percentage is
simply &lt;code&gt;(1-s)&lt;/code&gt;.  So for a 60% stock target, the bonds would be 40% as expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;keeping-up-with-inflation&quot;&gt;Keeping Up with Inflation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want your portfolio to keep pace with inflation, then you could require
that the portfolio that is left over after a withdrawal must increase enough
to cover the money lost to the withdrawal as well as covering the effects of
inflation,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
(P - kW)(1 + r) + (k-1)W &amp;gt; P(1 + i)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Substituting &lt;code&gt;W=wP&lt;/code&gt; and solving for &lt;code&gt;w&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
w &amp;lt; (r - i) / (1 + kr)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, even in the degenerate case where we don’t have a buffer (k=1),
then the maximum withdrawal rate that keeps up with inflation is not simply &lt;code&gt;r-i&lt;/code&gt;
but is reduced by &lt;code&gt;1/(1+r)&lt;/code&gt;.  For example, if your portfolio returns 7% and inflation
is 3%, then the maximum withdrawal would not be 4% but rather it would be,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
w &amp;lt; (.07-.03)/(1.07) = 3.74%
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is because your portfolio remaining after the withdrawal has to overcome
both inflation &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; the effects of withdrawing part of the portfolio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also notice that your withdrawal rate decreases with bigger buffer sizes.
This is because it is assumed that the buffer has zero gains.  You could mitigate
this by investing a part of your buffer in bonds but you will be increasing your
income volatility slightly if you do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;roth-ladder&quot;&gt;Roth Ladder&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The buffering concept plays really well with a &lt;a href=&quot;http://jlcollinsnh.com/2013/12/05/stocks-part-xx-early-retirement-withdrawal-strategies-and-roth-conversion-ladders-from-a-mad-fientist/&quot;&gt;Roth conversion ladder&lt;/a&gt;.
A Roth conversion ladder is a way to convert traditional IRA funds to Roth IRA funds in
an attempt to avoid early withdrawal penalties.  The IRS allows you to
convert a traditional IRA to a Roth IRA and may use the converted funds without
penalty after a 5-year waiting period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you pair a buffered withdrawal strategy using a buffer of 6 years, with a
Roth ladder, your buffer could be entirely made up of Roth IRA funds that are
converted annually from traditional IRA funds.  Then you simply withdraw 1/6th
of that buffer each year for living expenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason for choosing a 6-year buffer instead of a 5-year buffer is to avoid
the possibility of withdrawing slightly more than 1/5 of your buffer due to
market fluctuations.  But a 6-year buffer is a pretty large amount to not be invested
so it makes sense to invest 1-3 years of that buffer in something relatively
conservative like bonds.  One safe way to do that would be to simply buy bonds
with a 3-5 year maturity using the withdrawn funds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;implementing-the-buffered-strategy&quot;&gt;Implementing the Buffered Strategy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the basic steps for using a buffered withdrawal.  In these
steps, by way of example, let’s assume a buffer size of 6 years and a withdrawal
rate of 3%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Determine your initial buffer size.  Simply multiply your buffer size by
  your withdrawal rate (6*3% = 18%).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Set aside your initial buffer size somewhere in an account with safe funds.
  For example, if your portfolio is $1,000,000 then set aside 18% or $180k
  as your spending buffer.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Divide your buffer by the buffer size (in years) to get this year’s spending.
  For example, if your buffer has $180k and you have a 6-year buffer,
  remove $30k of spending for this year.  There is now $150k left in your
  buffer that you will not touch until next year.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rebalance your stock allocation.  For example, if you use a 60% stock allocation,
  rebalance your remaining portfolio so that you have 60% in stocks
  (e.g. 60% of $970k = $582k).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Invest the remainder in bonds (e.g. 970-582-150=$240k).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Enjoy life for 1 year.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After 1 year, recompute the size of your portfolio, including the buffer.
  For example, if your stocks went up to $640k, and your bonds went up to
  $250k and your buffer is $150k, then your total portfolio now has
  $1,040,000.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Multiply your new portfolio value by your withdrawal rate to get your
  buffer increment.  For example, $1,040,000*3% = $31,200.  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Move the buffer increment amount into your existing buffer.  You might
  want to consider your allocation before moving funds so as to avoid moving
  funds twice.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Go back to step 3 and repeat.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Implementing a buffered withdrawal strategy is one way to reduce the volatility
of spending in early retirement by spreading portfolio gains and losses between
multiple years.  It also can be used in conjunction with a Roth conversion ladder
for retirees needing to convert the tax-deferred IRA funds to Roth IRA funds.
Implementing such a strategy is fairly easy if you follow the steps outlined above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;related&quot;&gt;Related&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/safe-withdrawal-rates-for-vampires/&quot;&gt;Safe Withdrawal Rates for Vampires&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/the-30-30-withdrawal-strategy/&quot;&gt;The 30-30 Withdrawal Strategy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Standard_error#Standard_error_of_the_mean&quot;&gt;standard error of the mean&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        
          <link>http://www.moneycle.com/buffer-withdrawals-to-stabilize-income/</link>
        
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.moneycle.com/buffer-withdrawals-to-stabilize-income/</guid>
        
        <category>investing</category>
        
        <category>spending</category>
        
        <category>other</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Safe Withdrawal Rates for Vampires</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If you search the web for retirement withdrawal strategies,
you can find countless articles about how to withdraw your fund within the
construct of a 30-year retirement.  The most commonly cited strategy is the 4%
withdrawal strategy which starts withdrawing 4% of the initial portfolio value
and increases spending each year by the rate of inflation.
Using monte carlo analysis techniques, such a portfolio
may be found to have some small probability of exhausting the portfolio before
30 years have passed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if you’re a Vampire named Vlad and want your assets to last forever, you can’t
afford to have your portfolio run dry in 30 years or even 100 years.
Or maybe you aren’t not a vampire but are retiring early and want your funds to last
50 years, which seems like forever.
Let’s explore the idea of withdrawing funds from a portfolio indefinitely
to try to gain some insights into long-term safe withdrawal rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-vampire-strategy&quot;&gt;The Vampire Strategy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way Vlad can ensure that he never runs out of money is to just withdraw a fixed
percentage from the portfolio every year.  But Vlad doesn’t want his spending power
to decrease each year, so he needs to be careful with how much he spends.  In other
words, he wants his portfolio on average to grow by the rate of inflation while at
the same time withdrawing some amount of money to live on.  In equation form:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
(portfolio-withdrawal)(1+appreciation) &amp;gt;= portfolio(1+inflation)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This equation says that the portfolio in a given year will appreciate by at
least the rate of inflation after subtracting the withdrawal amount.
Let’s use shorter variable names to help make it more readable&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
(P - W)(1 + r) &amp;gt;= P(1 + i)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;P = portfolio value&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;W = withdrawal amount&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;w = withdrawal rate = W/P&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;r = porfolio appreciation&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;i = inflation rate&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Replacing withdrawal amount with &lt;code&gt;W = Pw&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we can divide both sides of the equation by the &lt;code&gt;P&lt;/code&gt; we get:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
(1 - w)(1 + r) &amp;gt;= (1 + i)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now it’s fairly simple to solve the &lt;code&gt;withdrawal rate&lt;/code&gt; as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
w &amp;lt;= (r - i) / (1 + r)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice that the numerator is the difference between Vlad’s portfolio return
and long-term inflation.  So if his portfolio appreciates at a rate less than
inflation, he’ll have to work forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stocks-only&quot;&gt;Stocks Only&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s see what happens if we assume Vlad invests everything in stocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moneychimp has an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.moneychimp.com/features/market_cagr.htm&quot;&gt;excellent tool&lt;/a&gt;
for getting historical stock returns.
With this tool you can see that for the past 100 years (1915-2014) stocks have
returned a compounded average rate of 10.31%.
If Vlad could invest in Vanguard Total Stock Market ETF (VTI),
he would incur a fee of 0.05% for a total return of 10.26%.  To be a little
conservative, let’s round that down to 10.2%.
Moneychimp also has an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.moneychimp.com/articles/econ/inflation_calculator.htm&quot;&gt;inflation calculator&lt;/a&gt;
which shows a historical inflation rate of 3.2% over the same time period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plugging those numbers into the above equations gives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
withdrawal rate &amp;lt;= 6.35%
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, with average stock returns and average inflation values, a withdrawal of 6.35%
or less could allow Vlad to keep up with inflation.  Keep in mind that average
returns are not realistic.  In fact, those average returns have a standard deviation
of 19.9% so if Vlad just used a 100% stock portfolio, he would have about a 95%
chance that his portfolio would return between -30% and +50%.  A 30% loss would
be a big hit to his annual income so Vlad probably wants to consider ways to smooth
out the market swings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stocks-and-bonds&quot;&gt;Stocks and Bonds&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to reduced volatility to a portfolio is by adding bonds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Historical bond rates are harder to come by but over period of 1926-2014
bonds have returned approximately 5.4% with a standard deviation of 5.6%&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:11&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:11&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.
So if Vlad invests his bond portfolio in Vanguard Total Bond Market ETF (BND)
with an expense ratio of 0.07%, let’s assume he gets a return of 5.3% on the bonds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following table shows the maximum withdrawal rates for different portfolio
allocations based on the returns estimated for each allocation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Stocks/Bonds =&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;20/80&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;40/60&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;60/40&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;80/20&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Historical Portfolio Return&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6.6%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7.3%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8.2%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;9.2%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Spending Standard Deviation&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;11%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;15%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Maximum Withdrawal Rate&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2.9%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3.8%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;4.7%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5.5%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Expense Multiplier&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;35&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;27&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;22&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;18&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “Expense Multiplier” value represents the amount of money that Vlad needs
to save before he begins his retirement in terms of his annual expenses.
So for a moderate 60/40 portfolio, Vlad would need to save at least 22 times his
annual expenses before he could retire from his night job, and he could withdraw
up to 4.7% to keep up with inflation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;buffer-the-vampire-strategy22&quot;&gt;Buffer the Vampire Strategy&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:22&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:22&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even with the moderate 60/40 portfolio, Vlad has a decent chance that his portfolio
(and spending) could drop by 14%&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; in any given year.&lt;br /&gt;
One way he could reduce the volatility of his expenses even further is to allocate
a portion of his portfolio to a spending buffer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To describe how a spending buffer works, consider a 5-year spending buffer
as an example.  With a 5-year buffer, Vlad would carve out 4 times his annual
expenses as part of his portfolio.  Since this represents the next 4 years of
his spending, it would be invested conservatively in short-term bond and cash
equivalents.  At the end of each year, Vlad applies his withdrawal rate to his
entire portfolio then moves that amount into his spending buffer (now the buffer
has 5 years worth of spending).  He then withdraws 1/5th of the spending buffer
for spending in the following year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;pieWithBuffer&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&quot;stock-slider&quot; style=&quot;width: 300px;&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
var pieData = [
  {
    &quot;label&quot;: &quot;Buffer&quot;,
    &quot;value&quot;: 13,
    &quot;color&quot;: &quot;#387e45&quot;,
    &quot;caption&quot;: &quot;{percentage}%, withdrawal = 3.2%&quot;
  },
  {
    &quot;label&quot;: &quot;Bonds&quot;,
    &quot;value&quot;: 27,
    &quot;color&quot;: &quot;#386a7e&quot;,
    &quot;caption&quot;: &quot;{percentage}%&quot;
  },
  {
    &quot;label&quot;: &quot;Stocks&quot;,
    &quot;value&quot;: 60,
    &quot;color&quot;: &quot;#7e3838&quot;,
    &quot;caption&quot;: &quot;{percentage}%&quot;
  }
];
stockReturn = 0.102;
bondReturn = 0.053;
inflationRate = 0.032;
bufferSize = 5;

updateData = function(stockPercent) {
    var stock = stockPercent * 0.01
  var bufferlessReturn = stock*stockReturn + (1-stock)*bondReturn;
  var a = bufferSize*(bufferSize-1)*bondReturn;
  var b = 1+(bufferSize-1)*bondReturn+bufferSize*bufferlessReturn;
  var c = bufferlessReturn - inflationRate;
  var withdrawalRate = (b-Math.sqrt(b*b-4*a*c))/(2*a);
  var bufferPercent = (bufferSize-1)*withdrawalRate*100;
  var bondPercent = 100-stockPercent-bufferPercent;

  pieData[0].value = bufferPercent;
  pieData[0].caption = &quot;{percentage}%, withdrawal = &quot; + Math.round(withdrawalRate*1000)/10 + &quot;%&quot;
  pieData[1].value = bondPercent;
  pieData[2].value = stockPercent;
}
updateData(55);

var pie = new d3pie(&quot;pieWithBuffer&quot;, {
	&quot;header&quot;: {
		&quot;title&quot;: {
			&quot;text&quot;:     &quot;Portfolio Allocation with a Spending Buffer&quot;,
			&quot;fontSize&quot;: 22
		},
    subtitle: {
      text:     bufferSize + &quot;-year buffer, 10.2% stock returns, 5.3% bond returns, 3.2% inflation&quot;,
      color:    &quot;#666666&quot;,
      fontSize: 14,
    }
	},
  footer: {
    text: 	  &quot;use slider to change stock allocation&quot;,
    color:    &quot;#666666&quot;,
    fontSize: 10,
    location: &quot;bottom-center&quot;
  },
	&quot;size&quot;: {
		&quot;canvasHeight&quot;: 400,
		&quot;canvasWidth&quot;: 430,
		&quot;pieOuterRadius&quot;: &quot;88%&quot;
	},
	&quot;data&quot;: {
		&quot;content&quot;: pieData
	},
	&quot;labels&quot;: {
		&quot;outer&quot;: {
			&quot;format&quot;: &quot;none&quot;,
			&quot;pieDistance&quot;: 32
		},
		&quot;inner&quot;: {
			&quot;format&quot;: &quot;label&quot;
		},
		&quot;mainLabel&quot;: {
			&quot;color&quot;: &quot;#e1e1e1&quot;,
			&quot;font&quot;: &quot;verdana&quot;,
			&quot;fontSize&quot;: 12
		},
		&quot;percentage&quot;: {
			&quot;color&quot;: &quot;#e1e1e1&quot;,
			&quot;font&quot;: &quot;verdana&quot;,
			&quot;decimalPlaces&quot;: 0
		},
		&quot;value&quot;: {
			&quot;color&quot;: &quot;#e1e1e1&quot;,
			&quot;font&quot;: &quot;verdana&quot;
		},
		&quot;lines&quot;: {
			&quot;enabled&quot;: true,
			&quot;color&quot;: &quot;#cccccc&quot;
		},
		&quot;truncation&quot;: {
			&quot;enabled&quot;: true
		}
	},
	&quot;tooltips&quot;: {
		&quot;enabled&quot;: true,
		&quot;type&quot;: &quot;caption&quot;,
		&quot;string&quot;: &quot;{label}: {percentage}%&quot;
	},
	&quot;effects&quot;: {
		&quot;pullOutSegmentOnClick&quot;: {
			&quot;effect&quot;: &quot;linear&quot;,
			&quot;speed&quot;: 200,
			&quot;size&quot;: 12
		}
	},
	&quot;callbacks&quot;: {
    &quot;onload&quot;: function() { pie.openSegment(0); },
		&quot;onMouseoverSegment&quot;: null,
		&quot;onMouseoutSegment&quot;: null,
		&quot;onClickSegment&quot;: null
	}
});

d3.select(&#39;#stock-slider&#39;).call(d3.slider().axis(true).min(0).max(85).step(5).value(pieData[2].value).on(&quot;slideend&quot;, function(evt, stockPercent) {
  updateData(stockPercent);
  pie.updateProp(&quot;data.content&quot;, pieData);
}));
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a 5-year buffer for his spending means that Vlad’s spending will only be
impacted by 1/5th of the fluctuations in the market.  The standard deviation of
Vlad’s spending will be reduced&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; by approximately &lt;code&gt;1/sqrt(5)&lt;/code&gt;.
In our example with a 60/40 split, the standard deviation goes from 11% down to 5%.
Vampires get grumpy with big swings in spending so this helps to prevent Vlad
from biting people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One possible downside of the buffering is that the returns from Vlad’s portfolio
would be slightly reduced.  Assuming that the buffer piece is allocated to the
bond side of the portfolio, then the bond returns would be reduced if the buffer
is allocated to cash or cash equivalents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Re-working the original equations with a spending buffer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
(P - kW)(1 + r) + kW - W &amp;gt;= P(1 + i)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where &lt;code&gt;k = spending buffer size in years&lt;/code&gt;.  In this equation &lt;code&gt;P-kW&lt;/code&gt; represents
the piece of the portfolio that is invested and &lt;code&gt;kW-W&lt;/code&gt; represents the buffer after
1 year’s worth of spending has been withdrawn.  In short, we want the appreciation
from the invested part of the portfolio to be enough so that the &lt;strong&gt;entire&lt;/strong&gt;
portfolio keeps up with inflation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solving this equation for withdrawal rate,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
w &amp;lt;= (r - i) / (1 + kr)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking this a little further, if Vlad wants to keep the stock portion of the
portfolio fixed at some percentage while bonds and the buffer make up the remainder,
then the rate of return could be written in terms of this percentage,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
r = s*r_s + (1 - s)*r_b - (k - 1)*w*r_b
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;s = percentage of portfolio in stocks&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;r_s = rate of return on stocks&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;r_b = rate of return on bonds&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first 2 terms of this equation represent the return we would have had without
buffering and the last term represents the amount of potential returns lost to
the buffering (assuming it would have been invested in bonds).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Substituting &lt;code&gt;r&lt;/code&gt; from the last equation into the equation before that gives us
a quadratic equation to solve for withdrawal rate (I may expand this
in another article but will leave this detail out for now).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this math probably is putting you to sleep so let’s look at some portfolios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Stocks/Bonds&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;/Buffer&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; =&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;20/72/8&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;40/50/10&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;60/27/13&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;80/5/15&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Historical Portfolio Return&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5.9%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6.7%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7.6%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8.4%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Spending Standard Deviation&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3.5%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;5%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;7%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Maximum Withdrawal Rate&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2.0%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;2.6%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3.2%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;3.7%&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Expense Multiplier&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;50&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;38&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;31&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;27&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if our friend Vlad has a portfolio with 60% in stocks and transfers 3.2%
of his portfolio to his 5-year spending buffer every year, his portfolio should roughly
keep pace with inflation.  The buffer needed for this withdrawal would account for
about 13% of his overall portfolio initially and would fluctuate with the market.
And the reduced variations in his income due to the buffering should help Vlad
sleep during the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;caveats&quot;&gt;Caveats&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this article explores the safe withdrawal rates for a portfolio that follows
historical returns, this is known to not be a good strategy for determining actual
safe withdrawal rates.  This is really more of a thought experiment to think about
long-term withdrawals combined with the spending buffer concept in order to reduce
income volatility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably a better way to complete this analysis would be to do a monte-carlo simulation
with an appropriate success criterion.  For example, most studies of 30-year withdrawal
rates consider how a withdrawal performs relative to how often the portfolio drops to
zero during the 30-year period.  For a vampire, the measure of success would probably
be whether the portfolio has kept pace with inflation over 50 years (or more).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;insights&quot;&gt;Insights&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of it’s weaknesses, this analysis does shed some light on very-long-term
withdrawals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For an aggressively allocated (80% stock) 5-year buffered portfolio, the
withdrawal rate of 3.7% could keep up with inflation. This rate isn’t too
far off from the widely discussed 4% rates you see in the financial press but it
is for a pretty aggressive allocation.  Reducing stock allocation quickly reduces the “safe”
withdrawal rate.  A much safer 40% allocation requires reducing the withdrawal rate all
the way down to 2.6%.  This highlights the need to
stay invested in higher-performing assets in order to keep up with long-term inflation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The buffered withdrawal strategy could be employed to cushion the ups and down of the
markets.  One cost of a buffered strategy is that it will reduce overall returns
by about 0.6% for moderate allocations.
But that lost return could be recouped by increasing the stock allocation by about 10%.
The 5-year buffer suggested here has a good chance of spanning at least 1 or 2 good
years even over the course of a bear market.  Over all 5-year periods stock returns
have been &lt;a href=&quot;http://awealthofcommonsense.com/u-s-stock-investors-doomed-high-returns/&quot;&gt;positive about 87% of the time&lt;/a&gt;.
This suggests that 87% of the time the 5-year buffered income would continue to increase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another cost of buffering is that it reduces the withdrawal rate that can keep
up with inflation.  So the ultimate balance is between stability and income.
If you want more income, you &lt;strong&gt;could&lt;/strong&gt; reduce the buffer size and take a higher
amount of income with full understanding that you should see larger swings in the market.
You could also do away with buffering and reduce the volatility by choosing a less
risky allocation.  Over the very long term it seems like Vlad would do better by
keeping his portfolio as heavily invested as is bearable and using buffering to
reduce the volatility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a vampire who wants to implement a Roth ladder strategy, you might
want to consider a 6-year buffer. This would allow you convert your traditional IRA
to a Roth IRA and wait the required 5 years before withdrawing the money without
penalty&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  But 6-years is a long time to not keep money invested so with such
a large buffer it might make sense to invest 1 or 2 years of a bigger buffer into
a bond fund.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;next-steps&quot;&gt;Next Steps&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there’s any interest, the next logical step for this analysis would be to
take it to the domain of monte-carlo simulations to see how the estimated rates
do over very long periods with the given portfolios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interesting variation of this analysis would be to include the effects
of social security on withdrawal rates.  Future social security or
pension earnings will probably allow for increased withdrawals until that income
stream kicks in.  It would be interesting to see how much of an effect that is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;related&quot;&gt;Related&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/buffer-withdrawals-to-stabilize-income/&quot;&gt;Buffer Withdrawals to Stabilize Income&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/the-30-30-withdrawal-strategy/&quot;&gt;The 30-30 Withdrawal Strategy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:11&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Bond Performance - 1926-2014: 5.4%, std dev = 5.6%, comes from a combination of &lt;a href=&quot;https://personal.vanguard.com/us/insights/saving-investing/model-portfolio-allocations&quot;&gt;Vanguard data&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jvlassociates.com/files/Performance%20Probabilities%20(Bell%20Curve%20)%20%201926%20-%202014.pdf&quot;&gt;comparable intermediate govt bond&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:11&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Portfolio return for mixed portfolios are crude approximations for illustrative purposes only. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Standard deviations for different allocations estimated from graph on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.forbes.com/sites/rickferri/2015/02/06/the-center-of-gravity-for-retirees/2/&quot;&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:22&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;No relation to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buffy_the_Vampire_Slayer&quot;&gt;Buffy the Vampire Slayer&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:22&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;14% drop is 2 standard deviations, or 22%, below average return of 8.2% &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Standard_error#Standard_error_of_the_mean&quot;&gt;standard error of the mean&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Bonds and buffer percentages are initial values, buffer size varies slightly after the first year. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Based on portfolio deviation divided by sqrt(5) for the buffering effect. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I’m pretty sure vampires are not subject to the rules concerning age of 59.5 and withdrawals. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 29 May 2015 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        
          <link>http://www.moneycle.com/safe-withdrawal-rates-for-vampires/</link>
        
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.moneycle.com/safe-withdrawal-rates-for-vampires/</guid>
        
        <category>investing</category>
        
        <category>spending</category>
        
        <category>other</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Maximize Your Employer Match before Using a Roth 401(k)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;While the Roth 401(k) is still a fairly new&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; option in the 401(k) world,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://aon.mediaroom.com/2014-04-28-Aon-Hewitt-Analysis-Finds-More-Employers-Adding-Roth-Features-to-Expand-Savings-Options&quot;&gt;half of employers&lt;/a&gt;
now offer a Roth option.  While contributing
to a Roth is not necessarily the best choice for everyone, it can be a good
choice for younger workers who haven’t reached their peak earnings potential
(and tax bracket).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, younger workers also tend to be those who are struggling to survive and
may have a hard time contributing enough to get the full match that their employer
provides.  For workers in this donut hole, it may make more sense
to contribute to the traditional 401(k) to get the maximum benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;example&quot;&gt;Example&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s look at a hypothetical example.  Let’s say your employer matches 50% of
your contribution up to 8%.  So if you are able to contribute 8%, the company
will match 4%.  And let’s assume you are single and making $75,000 which puts
you in the 25% tax bracket. Further, let’s assume that the most
you can afford to contribute to your 401(k) is $6,000 (before taxes)
or 8% of your income.  In other words, in order to cover your cost of living,
you need an income stream of $69,000/year after your 401(k) contributions are taken out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re contributing to a Roth, your $6000 becomes $4,500 after taxes which
is how much you can actually afford to contribute.  In this scenario,
you are getting 3% of the company match, but are missing out on the other 1% of
free money that your company could match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conversely, if you defer your taxes and contribute the entire $6,000 to a traditional
401(k), you will get the entire match from your employer which amounts to an
additional $750 added to your 401(k).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Roth 401(k)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Traditional 401(k)&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Gross Income&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$75,000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$75,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;401(k) Contribution&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$4,500&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$6,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;401(k) Taxes&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$1,500&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$0 (deferred)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Livable Income&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$69,000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$69,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Employer Match&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$2,250&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$3,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, eventually you will have to pay taxes on your traditional 401(k)
contribution.  If your future tax rate is still 25%, then you will pay the same
$1,500 (adjusted for gains) as you would have in the Roth case.  So you’re still
ahead by $750 (plus future gains).  Or in percentage terms, you would be ahead by
&lt;code&gt;(6000(1-0.25)+3000)/(6000-1500+2250)&lt;/code&gt; or 7.14%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are able to reduce your tax rate in retirement, which most early retirees
do, then the gain is even higher.  For example, if you pull your money out while in
a 15% tax bracket, then your potential gain is &lt;code&gt;(6000(1-0.15)+3000)/(6000-1500+2250)&lt;/code&gt;
or 20%!  A 20% future gain just by picking the right type of 401(k) is a pretty
big deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if your rate is higher in the future?  At what higher tax rate would you
break even?  To figure that out we solve the equation
&lt;code&gt;6000(1-rate)+3000 = 6000(1-0.25)+2250&lt;/code&gt; which gives a rate of 37.5%.
That means your future tax rate would have to be above 37.5% in order for the
Roth to be the right choice in this scenario.
And since you’d have to earn over $425,000 to hit the 39% tax rate, this is
what I would call a good problem to have and you can afford to hire a
financial advisor to help you figure it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;counter-example&quot;&gt;Counter Example&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if you have enough money to contribute fully to either a Roth or a traditional
401(k)?  In the above example, instead of assuming you can invest $6000, let’s assume
you can invest $8,000 (and live off of $67,000) which will give you the maximum
employer match either way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Roth 401(k)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Traditional 401(k)&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Gross Income&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$75,000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$75,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;401(k) Contribution&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$6,000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$8,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;401(k) Taxes&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$2,000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$0 (deferred)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Livable Income&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$67,000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$67,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Employer Match&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$3,000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$3,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, it comes down to what your current tax rate is versus your future
tax rate.  With these numbers the comparison is between &lt;code&gt;(8000(1-current_tax)+3000)&lt;/code&gt;
(Roth) and &lt;code&gt;(8000(1-future_tax)+3000)&lt;/code&gt; (traditional).  In other words, the decision
comes down to a simple comparison of tax rates and whether you think you will be
able to reduce your future tax rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there’s actually more to it than that.
It’s really a comparison between today’s &lt;em&gt;marginal&lt;/em&gt; tax
rate versus your retirement’s &lt;em&gt;total&lt;/em&gt; tax rate&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  Why?  Because if you’re living
off of your money in the future, some of the money you withdraw will be at a 0%
tax rate, and some at 10%, and so-on up to your marginal tax rate.
So even if your future marginal tax rate is the same as your current tax rate,
your future total tax rate would be lower because you have to fill
in those lower tax buckets first.  In other words, there’s a good chance that the
traditional 401(k) will still fare better than the Roth 401(k) if you don’t
inflate your future lifestyle spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Younger workers in lower tax brackets are often encouraged to invest in the Roth
option provided by their employers so that they can take advantage of their lower
career tax rates.  However, these workers should also consider that they could
be giving up free money if they are unable to contribute up to the full value
matched by their employers.  When in doubt, make sure you
get your full employer match using traditional 401(k) contributions before
contributing to a Roth 401(k).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roth_401(k)&quot;&gt;Roth 401(k)&lt;/a&gt; first went into effect in 2006. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://thefinancebuff.com/case-against-roth-401k.html&quot;&gt;“The Case Against Roth 401(k)”&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 23 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        
          <link>http://www.moneycle.com/maximize-your-employer-match-before-using-a-roth-401-k/</link>
        
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.moneycle.com/maximize-your-employer-match-before-using-a-roth-401-k/</guid>
        
        <category>investing</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to Take Early IRA Withdrawals without Penalty</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If you are like many early retirees, then you may find most
of your savings are tied up in your &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.investopedia.com/terms/d/deferredaccount.asp&quot;&gt;tax-deferred accounts&lt;/a&gt;
like traditional 401k or IRA accounts when you are ready to retire.
If you are younger than 59.5 years old,
then how do you withdraw your funds without penalty?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are three possible choices for withdrawing your money without penalty:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Roth Ladder - a Roth ladder is where you convert your traditional IRA
  funds to Roth then withdraw them 5 years later.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Annuities - traditional IRA funds can be used to purchase a single premium
  immediate annuity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Substantially Equal Period Payments (SEPP) - also referred to as 72(t) which
  is the section of the tax code that allows this withdrawal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-sepp&quot;&gt;Why SEPP?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I prefer the Roth Ladder approach for withdrawing fund, it may not be enough
to meet your spending needs if you don’t have enough in your Roth to begin with.
Annuities have their place in retirement too, but for early retirees they are
less attractive (rates go up as you get older).  The SEPP withdrawal can help
fill the spending gap until you are 59.5 at which point you will have other
options to avoid penalties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sepp-rules&quot;&gt;SEPP Rules&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of things you need to be aware of when setting up a SEPP
withdrawal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The account you from which you do you SEPP withdrawals needs to be a stand-alone
  account.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You cannot trade in or out of the SEPP account after the payments have begun.
  Doing so will result in stiff penalties, so don’t do it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You must continue withdrawals for at least 5 years and until you are age
  59.5 or greater.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You must calculate your withdrawal using one of three methods:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;amortization&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;annuitization&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;required-minimum distributions (RMD)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you ever get audited you may need to show the calculation, so document
  the calculation and save it somewhere you can find later.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there are 3 approved methods for withdrawing your money, I suggest you stick
with amortization.  The RMD method will give the smallest amount of money, especially
for younger retirees, since it is just your account value divided by your remaining
life expectancy. Amortization and annuitization tend to result in similar payouts
that are both larger than RMD.  And a larger payout is good because it means you can
use a smaller portion of your retirement funds for the SEPP withdrawals and retain some
flexibility with your remaining funds.  Between amortization and annuitization
I prefer the amortization method because it is a easier to calculate and
therefore less prone to error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;setup-the-sepp-account&quot;&gt;Setup the SEPP Account&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you have decided to setup a SEPP withdrawal, the first thing you should do
is create a separate account inside of your existing brokerage account.  For example,
if you have funds at Vanguard, you can break your accounts into separate sub-accounts
that each have their own set of funds in them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amount you put into your SEPP account depends largely on the calculation
you’ll be doing below.  I recommend that you first determine how much &lt;strong&gt;income&lt;/strong&gt; you
will need from the SEPP withdrawal and then reverse the calculation to determine how much
money to put into your newly created account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;doublecheck-the-calculation&quot;&gt;Doublecheck the Calculation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are three ways to do this calculation: spreadsheet formula, web calculators
and good old mathematics. All 3 methods should give you the same number so it’s
a good idea to try at least 2 of these methods to sanity check that you’re doing
it right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all of these methods, you will need the following 3 numbers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;rate&lt;/code&gt; = 120% of the Applicable Federal Rate.  Don’t worry, you’re not alone,
  nobody else has heard of this number either.  It’s a number that the IRS
  publishes monthly and can be
  &lt;a href=&quot;http://apps.irs.gov/app/picklist/list/federalRates.html&quot;&gt;found here&lt;/a&gt;.
  You are allowed to choose one of the past 2 months when you do the calculation
  but to be safe I would just choose the rate from the most recent month.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;expectancy&lt;/code&gt; = your remaining life expectancy in years.  This is also published
  by the IRS and can be &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.irs.gov/pub/irs-pdf/p590b.pdf&quot;&gt;found here&lt;/a&gt;.
  Look in Appendix B for the life expectancy tables using the age you will be on
  your birthday this year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;principal&lt;/code&gt; = the size of the account you will be taking distributions from.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spreadsheet-formula&quot;&gt;Spreadsheet Formula&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spreadsheet formula that I have tested using Google Spreadsheet is simply:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
=-pmt(rate, expectancy, principal)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will give you the amount you can withdraw annually so divide by 12 if you
are going to make monthly withdrawals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sepp-calculators&quot;&gt;SEPP Calculators&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several calculators that will help you figure out the SEPP withdrawals.
I recommend the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://72t.net/72t/Calculator/Distributions&quot;&gt;72t.net Calculator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dinkytown.net/java/Retire72T.html&quot;&gt;Dinkytown Calculator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I prefer the 72t.net calculator since it gives results to the nearest penny.
But go ahead and verify that you get the same number to the nearest dollar from
both calculators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;math-equation&quot;&gt;Math Equation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the mathematically inclined, you can also plug your numbers into
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amortization_calculator#The_formula&quot;&gt;the annuity formula&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
income = principal * rate / (1 - (1+rate)^-expectancy)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;account-size-needed-for-a-desired-income&quot;&gt;Account Size Needed for a Desired Income&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are thinking about using SEPP withdrawals, there’s a good chance that you
already know how much income you need and just want to figure out how much principal
you need to put aside to generate that income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One approach would be to calculate how much income you get from $100,000 then
use that to figure out how much you need for your desired income level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, let’s say you want an annual income of $12,000,
the current mid-term rate is 2.04%, and your remaining life expectancy is 36 years.
Plugging in those numbers for $100,000 of principal gives you an income of $3,948.53.
To get to your desired income of $12,000 you then divide $12,000 by $3,948.53 and
multiply by $100,000 to arrive at a principal of $303,910.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more direct approach, is to invert the ‘math equation’ above and calculate
your payment directly with this formula:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
principal = income * (1 - (1+rate)^-expectancy) / rate
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, once you arrive at what you think the correct principal amount is,
double check it by any of the above methods to make sure it gives you the desired
income.  Then set aside that amount in an account that you won’t touch except to
do the SEPP withdrawals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SEPP withdrawals aren’t for everyone.  But if you find yourself in a situation
where you need to use them, this article should help you figure out how to do the
calculations needed. Regardless of what happens in the market you should
continue withdrawing the exact same amount, so have your brokerage do
an automatic withdrawal so that you aren’t tempted to mess with it.
Also, don’t forget that you will need to pay income taxes on your withdrawals
since this is just income that you deferred from the past.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 27 Mar 2015 18:55:50 -0600</pubDate>
        
          <link>http://www.moneycle.com/how-to-take-early-ira-withdrawals-without-penalty/</link>
        
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.moneycle.com/how-to-take-early-ira-withdrawals-without-penalty/</guid>
        
        <category>spending</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Penny Saved Is Four Dollars Earned</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We’ve all heard the phrase “a penny saved is a penny earned”, which is usually
attributed to Benjamin Franklin, inventor of the bifocals.
And while Benjamin Franklin is revered by the monocle-loving crowd,
his adage does not accurately represent the true worth of a penny saved in the
context of an early retirement.  Let’s take a look at what a penny saved in your
monthly expenses equals in terms of how much money you need to save.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;retirement-income&quot;&gt;Retirement Income&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When thinking about retirement income, a good rule-of-thumb is to use the 4% rule.
This isn’t a hard and fast rule, but it does give us a good idea of how much
money we need to save for a particular income.  For example, a portfolio of
$300,000 can reasonably be expected to generate an income of $12,000 per year
(4% of $300,000), or $1000 per month.  Conversely, if we want an
income of $1000 per month, we need to save 300 times that amount in our retirement
account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we talk about income needs in retirement, all we’re really talking about
is covering our living expenses.  So, if we can reduce our expenses by
$1 per month, then we can retire with $300 less in our portfolio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;taxes&quot;&gt;Taxes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accounting for taxes can be a little more tricky because the tax rate depends
on when the money is taxed.  If it is taxed while you are in your peak earning
years, you might be paying a combined 33% or more federal and state taxes,
not to mention sales tax on whatever your are spending your money on.
But after retirement, you should be in a lower tax bracket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the sake of argument, let’s assume you have deferred your taxes until retirement
and that the money you’re spending is coming out of a traditional IRA.
And let’s say you’re in the 15% federal bracket, 5% state and 5% sales tax.
It’s pretty easy to get to 25% combined taxes even at lower tax brackets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this 25% tax rate, instead of saving $300 now to spend $1 later, we would
have to save $400.  So, if you start with $400, and subtract 25%, or $100 for
taxes, then you arrive at the $300 needed to sustain $1 in monthly spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In equation form, you need to save &lt;code&gt;$300/(1-tax_rate)&lt;/code&gt; to sustain a dollar of monthly
expenses.  For example, if you’re combined tax rate is 40%, then the
amount you need to earn to save for a $1 monthly expense would be &lt;code&gt;$300/0.6&lt;/code&gt; or $500!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;monthly-expenses&quot;&gt;Monthly Expenses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the $400 multiplier from above, consider some typical monthly expenses and their
impact on your savings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;If you will be spending …&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;You need to save…&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;$8 your Hulu subscription&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$3,200&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;$30 to have your dachshund bathed&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$12,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;$50 extra on your phone bill&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$20,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;$100 extra on your cable bill&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$40,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The math on this is easy to do in your head, which is partly why I chose the
25% tax rate for our examples.  Multiplying by 400 is simply multiplying by
2 twice then adding 2 zeroes.  So, when you consider the money you need to
save to cover a cost of say, $6.35, times 2 is $12.70, times 2 is $25.40,
and add 2 zeros to arrive at $2540.  You don’t need a fancy monocle to do
that in your head!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;daily-expenses&quot;&gt;Daily Expenses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daily expenses have an even bigger impact per dollar.  If you consider a daily
expense to be around 25 times per month, then you need 25*$400, or $10,000,
to cover every $1 of daily expenses in the future.
The math couldn’t be easier, just add 4 zeros.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;If you will be spending …&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;You need to save…&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;$1 to have your monocle cleaned&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$10,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;$2 for a fountain drink with lunch&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$20,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;$5 for a venti Starbucks Frappucino&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$50,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if you can’t live without your Starbucks, maybe just downgrading to the
grande size will save you $10,000.  And maybe you could even learn to clean
your own damn monocle and save another $10,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been a little bit loose with the numbers partially because it’s hard to
know exactly what your withdrawal and tax rates will be.  But the point of this
article is to give you some ballpark numbers with which to evaluate whether an
added expense is worth it.  Simply put, to figure out how much money you’ll
need to support a spending level in retirement:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for monthly expenses, multiply the expense by 400.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for daily expenses, multiply the expense by 10,000.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully this rule-of-thumb will help you think about the impact of
spending on your retirement.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
          <link>http://www.moneycle.com/a-penny-saved-is-four-dollars-earned/</link>
        
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.moneycle.com/a-penny-saved-is-four-dollars-earned/</guid>
        
        <category>investing</category>
        
        <category>spending</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
