<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Moneycle</title>
    <description>Don your money monocle (top hats are optional) as we explore topics related to money, investing and early retirement.
</description>
    <link>http://www.moneycle.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.moneycle.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 29 Mar 2015 11:57:13 -0600</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Mar 2015 11:57:13 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>How Lending Club and Prosper Fit With Stocks and Bonds</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Peer-to-peer (P2P) lending could be thought of as another asset class for
your portfolio.  This article from LendingMemo suggests it’s somewhere between
stocks and bonds.
Since it is still a nascent type of investment, the jury is out on how it will
perform in different kinds of markets.  I think it has great promise
as a part of your portfolio, however I wouldn’t go up to 20% as suggested
by the article unless you have a higher tolerance for risk.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 29 Mar 2015 11:42:09 -0600</pubDate>
        
          <link>http://www.lendingmemo.com/stocks-bonds-lending-club-prosper/</link>
        
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.moneycle.com/how-lending-club-and-prosper-fit-with-stocks-and-bonds/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to Take Early IRA Withdrawals Without Penalty</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If you are like many early retirees, when you are ready to retire you may find most
of your savings will end up in you &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.investopedia.com/terms/d/deferredaccount.asp&quot;&gt;tax-deferred accounts&lt;/a&gt;
like a traditional 401k or IRA.  If you are younger than 59.5 years old,
 then how do you withdraw your funds without penalty?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three possible choices for withdrawing your money without penalty are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Roth Ladder - a Roth ladder is where you convert your traditional IRA
  funds to Roth then withdraw them 5 years later.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Annuities - traditional IRA funds can be used to purchase a single premium
  immediate annuity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Substantially Equal Period Payments (SEPP) - also referred to as 72(t) which
  which is the section of the tax code that allows this withdrawal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-sepp&quot;&gt;Why SEPP?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I prefer the Roth Ladder approach for withdrawing fund, it may not be enough
to meet your spending needs if you don’t have enough in your Roth to begin with.
Annuities have their place in retirement too, but for early retirees they are
less attractive (rates go up as you get older).  The SEPP withdrawal can help
fill the spending gap until you are 59.5 at which point you will have other
options to avoid penalties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sepp-rules&quot;&gt;SEPP Rules&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of things you need to be aware of when setting up a SEPP
withdrawal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The account you from which you do you SEPP withdrawals needs to be a stand-alone
  account.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You cannot trade in to or out of the SEPP account after the payments have begun.
  Doing so will result in stiff penalties, so don’t do it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You must continue withdrawals for at least 5 years and until you are age
  59.5 or greater.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You must calculate your withdraw using one of three methods:
    * amortization
    * annuitization
    * required-minimum distributions (RMD)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you ever get audited you may need to show the calculation, so document
  the calculation and save it somewhere you can find later.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there are 3 approved methods for withdrawing your money, I suggest you stick
with amortization.  The RMD method will give the smallest amount of money, especially
for younger retirees, since it is just your account value divided by your remaining
life expectancy. Amortization and annuitization tend to result in similar payouts
that are both larger than RMD.  And a larger payout is good because it means you can
use a smaller portion of your retirement funds for the SEPP withdrawals and retain some
flexibility with your remaining funds.  Between amortization and annuitization
I prefer the amortization method because it is a easier to calculate and
therefore less prone to error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;setup-the-sepp-account&quot;&gt;Setup the SEPP Account&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you have decided to setup a SEPP withdrawal, the first thing you should do
is create a separate account inside of your existing brokerage account.  For example,
if you have funds at Vanguard, you can break your accounts into separate sub-accounts
that each have their own set of funds in them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amount you put into your SEPP account depends largely on the calculation
you’ll be doing below.  I recommend that you determine how much &lt;strong&gt;income&lt;/strong&gt; you
will need from the SEPP withdrawal and reverse the calculation to determine how much
money to put into your newly created account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;doublecheck-the-calculation&quot;&gt;Doublecheck the Calculation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are three ways to do this calculation: spreadsheet formula, web calculators
and good old mathematics. All 3 methods should give you the same number so it’s
a good idea to try at least 2 of these methods to sanity check that you’re doing
it right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all of these methods, you will need the following 3 numbers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;rate&lt;/code&gt; = 120% of the Applicable Federal Rate.  Don’t worry, you’re not alone,
  nobody else has heard of this number either.  It’s a number that the IRS
  publishes monthly and can be
  &lt;a href=&quot;http://apps.irs.gov/app/picklist/list/federalRates.html&quot;&gt;found here&lt;/a&gt;.
  You are allowed to choose one of the past 2 months when you do the calculation
  but to be safe I would just choose the rate from the most recent month.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;expetancy&lt;/code&gt; = your remaining life expectancy in years.  This is also published
  by the IRS and can be &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.irs.gov/pub/irs-pdf/p590b.pdf&quot;&gt;found here&lt;/a&gt;.
  Look in Appendix B for the life expectancy tables using the age you will be on
  your birthday this year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;principal&lt;/code&gt; = the size of the account you will be taking distributions from.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spreadsheet-formula&quot;&gt;Spreadsheet Formula&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spreadsheet formula that I have tested using Google Spreadsheet is simply:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
=-pmt(rate, expectancy, principal)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will give you the amount you can withdraw annually so divide by 12 if you
are going to make monthly withdrawals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sepp-calculators&quot;&gt;SEPP Calculators&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several calculators that will help you figure out the SEPP withdrawals.
I recommend the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://72t.net/72t/Calculator/Distributions&quot;&gt;72t.net Calculator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dinkytown.net/java/Retire72T.html&quot;&gt;Dinkytown Calculator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I prefer the 72t.net calculator since it gives results to the nearest penny.
But go ahead and verify that you get the same number to the nearest dollar from
both calculators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;math-equation&quot;&gt;Math Equation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the mathematically inclined, you can also plug your numbers into
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amortization_calculator#The_formula&quot;&gt;the annuity formula&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
income = principal * rate / (1 - (1+rate)^-expectancy)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;account-size-needed-for-a-desired-income&quot;&gt;Account Size Needed for a Desired Income&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a good chance that, if you are thinking about using SEPP withdrawals, you
know how much income you need and just want to figure out how much principal you
need to put aside generate that income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One approach would be to calculate how much income you get from $100,000 then
divide that into your desired income to figure out how much to scale up the $100,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, let’s say you want an annual income of $12,000,
the current mid-term rate is 2.04%, and your remaining life expectancy is 36 years.
Plugging in those numbers for $100,000 of principal gives you an income of $3,948.53.
To get to your desired income of $12,000 you then divide $12,000 by $3,948.53 and
multiply by $100,000 to arrive at a principal of $303,910.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more direct approach, is to invert the ‘math equation’ above and calculate
your payment directly with this formula:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;
principal = income * (1 - (1+rate)^-expectancy) / rate
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, once you arrive at what you think the correct principal amount is,
double check it by any of the above methods to make sure it gives you the desired
income.  Then set aside that amount in an account that you won’t touch except to
do the SEPP withdrawals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SEPP withdrawals aren’t for everyone.  But if you find yourself in a situation
where you need to use them, this article should help you figure out how to do the
calculations needed. Regardless of what happens in the market you should
continue withdrawing the exact same amount, so have your brokerage do
an automatic withdrawal so that you aren’t tempted to mess with it.
Also, don’t forget that you will need to pay income taxes on your withdrawals
since this is just income that you deferred from the past.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 27 Mar 2015 18:55:50 -0600</pubDate>
        
          <link>http://www.moneycle.com/how-to-take-early-ira-withdrawals-without-penalty/</link>
        
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.moneycle.com/how-to-take-early-ira-withdrawals-without-penalty/</guid>
        
        <category>spending</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Case Against Roth 401(k)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is an older article by The Finance Buff but still a relevant explanation
about why contributing to a traditional 401k/IRA is usually better than 
contributing to a Roth 401k/IRA.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 04 Mar 2015 23:12:57 -0700</pubDate>
        
          <link>http://thefinancebuff.com/case-against-roth-401k.html</link>
        
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.moneycle.com/the-case-against-roth-401-k/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Penny Saved Is Four Dollars Earned</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We’ve all heard the phrase “a penny saved is a penny earned”, which is usually
attributed to Benjamin Franklin, inventor of the bifocals.
And while Benjamin Franklin is revered by the monocle-loving crowd,
his adage does not accurately represent the true worth of a penny saved in the
context of an early retirement.  Let’s take a look at what a penny saved in your
monthly expenses equals in terms of how much money you need to save.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;retirement-income&quot;&gt;Retirement Income&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When thinking about retirement income, a good rule-of-thumb is to use the 4% rule.
This isn’t a hard and fast rule, but it does give us a good idea of how much
money we need to save for a particular income.  For example, a portfolio of
$300,000 can reasonably be expected to generate an income of $12,000 per year
(4% of $300,000), or $1000 per month.  Conversely, if we want an
income of $1000 per month, we need to save 300 times that amount in our retirement
account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we talk about income needs in retirement, all we’re really talking about
is covering our living expenses.  So, if we can reduce our expenses by
$1 per month, then we can retire with $300 less in our portfolio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;taxes&quot;&gt;Taxes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accounting for taxes can be a little more tricky because the tax rate depends
on when the money is taxed.  If it is taxed while you are in your peak earning
years, you might be paying a combined 33% or more federal and state taxes,
not to mention sales tax on whatever your are spending your money on.
But after retirement, you should be in a lower tax bracket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the sake of argument, let’s assume you have deferred your taxes until retirement
and that the money you’re spending is coming out of a traditional IRA.
And let’s say you’re in the 15% federal bracket, 5% state and 5% sales tax.
It’s pretty easy to get to 25% combined taxes even at lower tax brackets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this 25% tax rate, instead of saving $300 now to spend $1 later, we would
have to save $400.  So, if you start with $400, and subtract 25%, or $100 for
taxes, then you arrive at the $300 needed to sustain $1 in monthly spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In equation form, you need to save &lt;code&gt;$300/(1-tax_rate)&lt;/code&gt; to sustain a dollar of monthly
expenses.  For example, if you’re combined tax rate is 40%, then the
amount you need to earn to save for a $1 monthly expense would be &lt;code&gt;$300/0.6&lt;/code&gt; or $500!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;monthly-expenses&quot;&gt;Monthly Expenses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the $400 multiplier from above, consider some typical monthly expenses and their
impact on your savings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;If you will be spending …&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;You need to save…&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;$8 your Hulu subscription&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$3,200&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;$30 to have your dachshund bathed&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$12,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;$50 extra on your phone bill&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$20,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;$100 extra on your cable bill&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$40,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The math on this is easy to do in your head, which is partly why I chose the
25% tax rate for our examples.  Multiplying by 400 is simply multiplying by
2 twice then adding 2 zeroes.  So, when you consider the money you need to
save to cover a cost of say, $6.35, times 2 is $12.70, times 2 is $25.40,
and add 2 zeros to arrive at $2540.  You don’t need a fancy monocle to do
that in your head!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;daily-expenses&quot;&gt;Daily Expenses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daily expenses have an even bigger impact per dollar.  If you consider a daily
expense to be around 25 times per month, then you need 25*$400, or $10,000,
to cover every $1 of daily expenses in the future.
The math couldn’t be easier, just add 4 zeros.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;If you will be spending …&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;You need to save…&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;$1 to have your monocle cleaned&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$10,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;$2 for a fountain drink with lunch&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$20,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;$5 for a venti Starbucks Frappucino&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;$50,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if you can’t live without your Starbucks, maybe just downgrading to the
grande size will save you $10,000.  And maybe you could even learn to clean
your own damn monocle and save another $10,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been a little bit loose with the numbers partially because it’s hard to
know exactly what your withdrawal and tax rates will be.  But the point of this
article is to give you some ballpark numbers with which to evaluate whether an
added expense is worth it.  Simply put, to figure out how much money you’ll
need to support a spending level in retirement:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for monthly expenses, multiply the expense by 400.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for daily expenses, multiply the expense by 10,000.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully this rule-of-thumb will help you think about the impact of
spending on your retirement.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        
          <link>http://www.moneycle.com/a-penny-saved-is-four-dollars-earned/</link>
        
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.moneycle.com/a-penny-saved-is-four-dollars-earned/</guid>
        
        <category>investing</category>
        
        <category>spending</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
